<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Homelies sette forth by the righte reuerende father in God, Edmunde Byshop of London, not onely promised before in his booke, intituled, A necessary doctrine, but also now of late adioyned, and added thereunto, to be read within his diocesse of London, of all persons, vycars, and curates, vnto theyr parishioners, vpon sondayes, &amp; holydayes.</title>
            <author>Bonner, Edmund, 1500?-1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3285.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103088</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920309</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 44920309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173756</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173756)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2095:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Homelies sette forth by the righte reuerende father in God, Edmunde Byshop of London, not onely promised before in his booke, intituled, A necessary doctrine, but also now of late adioyned, and added thereunto, to be read within his diocesse of London, of all persons, vycars, and curates, vnto theyr parishioners, vpon sondayes, &amp; holydayes.</title>
                  <author>Bonner, Edmund, 1500?-1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>73 [i.e. 146], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Ihon Cawodde, Prynter to the Kyng and Queenes Maiesties,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London in Poules churcheyarde, at the sygne of the holy Ghost, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno M.D.L.V [1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint (except date) from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-S⁴, T².</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border (McK. &amp; Ferg. 83 with printer's mark of John Cawood in sill); historiated initials.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio maiestatis." -- Colop.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p rend="blackletterType">
               <hi rend="roman">HOME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> ſette forth by the righte reuerende father in God, Edmunde Byſhop of London, not onely promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before in his booke, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, A neceſſary doctrine, but alſo now of late adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and added therevnto, to be read within his dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of London, of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, vycars, and curates, vnto theyr pariſhioners, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſondayes, &amp; holydayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Anno.</hi> 
               <hi rend="roman">M.D.LV.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>surrounding the title, decorative border (McKerrow &amp; Ferguson 83): "A compartment with a small medallion of a man's head at top; pillars at sides; and a shield below." Initials of the printer, John Cawood, in the shield.</figDesc>
               <p>
                  <hi>I.C.</hi>
               </p>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:2"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>i. Of the creation and fall of Man.</item>
               <item>ii. Of the miſery of all mankynde and of hys condempnation to death.</item>
               <item>iii. Of the redemption of Man.</item>
               <item>iiii. Howe the redemption in Chryſt is apliable to man.</item>
               <item>v. Of chryſten loue and Charitie.</item>
               <item>vi. Howe daungerous a thinge the breake of Charitie is.</item>
               <item>vii. Of the Churche what it is, and of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie thereof.</item>
               <item>viii. Of the aucthoritie of the Churche.</item>
               <item>ix. Of the Supremacy.</item>
               <item>x. Of the Supremacy.</item>
               <item>xi. Of the true preſence of Chryſtes body &amp; blud in the ſacrament of the Aultare.</item>
               <item>xii. Of tranſſubſtantiation.</item>
               <item>xiii. Of certen Aunſwers agaynſt ſome commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obiections, made agaynſt the ſacrament of the Aultare.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface_to_parsons_and_curates_in_the_diocese_of_London">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:173756:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Byſſhoppe of London to all perſons, and curates, within his dioces of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the people of my dioces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng within your ſeueral cures, &amp; charge, do (as in dede of reaſon they maye) loke for to haue at theyr paſtours hand, or at the leaſt way, by his prouiſion, &amp; meane, good inſtruction, and teachinge, eſpeciallye howe to ſerue and pleaſe God, and how alſo otherwyſe to do their dutie, as to any one of them in theyr degre doth appertayne. And foraſmuch alſo as there is not now a dayes that multitude, and plenteth of preachers, whiche in tymes paſt hath ben, and by Gods grace, hereafter ſhalbe. And fynallye, for that euery one of you in your owne perſon, is not able to diſcharge the office of preaching, which many good folke do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wyſhe, and deſyre ye could, and woulde. Therfore deſyrynge to haue ſomethyng done onward, til God of his goodnes prouide ſomething better, I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with my chapleyns, &amp; frendes, to haue theſe Homelies prynted, that ye may haue ſomewhat to inſtruct, and teache your flocke withall, requyrynge, and charginge euerye one of you, that diligentlye, vpon the ſondayes, and holydayes, ye reade to youre flocke, frutefully, and deliberately, one of the ſaid Homelies. And thus fare you well.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Geuen at my houſe in London, <date>the fyrſte daye of Iuly. M.D.LV.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:3"/>
            <head>¶ An Homely, of the creation and fall of man.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Prophette,</hi> Dauid in his fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcore and ninte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th pſalme, exhortyng all people to ſynge prayſe to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti god, to ſerue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gladnes, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyſe in his ſight, alledgeth thys as a ſufficient cauſe thereof. <hi>Scitote quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ipſe est dominus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme, cxix.</note> 
               <hi>ipſe fecit nos et non ipſi nos.</hi> which is to ſaye. <hi>Know you that he is our Lord it is he that made vs, and we made not our ſelfes.</hi> And in dede, who y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diligently wayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, can not but therin moſt highly laude, &amp; prayſe almighty god, his creator. For wher in the creation of al other viſible thinges, he did but onely commaunde, &amp; will that they ſhould be made, and incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they were made, in the creatyng of man, he vſed great ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and many notable circumſtaunces. Fyrſt tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Geneſ. i.</note> he ſaid, <hi>let vs make ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which words be as it were the wordes of god the father, to God the ſonne, &amp; to the holy ghoſt, ſpoken after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, when they go about ſome great matter, at what time they take good aduiſement or they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn, and doo ioyne with the beſt, &amp; wyſeſt counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173756:3"/> that they can get. Thys circumſtaunce (not beyng neceſſary of goddes parte, as withoute the which he might haue created man) doth moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſtly declare the ſpecial fauour, of almyghty god to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes mankynde: but that nexte circumſtaunce, which doth immediatly folowe thys fyrſt, is a more ſurer profe, and declaration of gods tender loue, towardes ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth. <hi>Let vs make man to our owne ſimilitude &amp; likenes,</hi> Now mark, good people, howe much god dyd for vs in our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He made vs in very dede like vnto himſelfe, &amp; in ſo doynge what could he haue done more for vs? A wonderfull excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t benefite &amp; comfort is it vnto vs, to conſyder that man was made like vnto god. And to vnderſtand this thyng the better, you ſhall know that the ſimilitude, and likenes of man to god, was not in the body of man (for this you muſt mooſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenly beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the godhed is a ſpirite, &amp; not a bodely ſubſtaunce) but this ſimilitude and likenes was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, which was endued, with moſt heuenly &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like qualities, as vnderſtandyng, memory, and wil, with ſondry gyftes alſo of grace. And here is to be noted by the way, that where almighty god ſayeth, <hi>Let vs make man to our owne ſimilitude, &amp; lykenes,</hi> he geueth vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be three parſons in trinitie, &amp; yet but one god. For in that he ſayeth let vs make man, therein is ſignified, a plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, or number of perſones: agayne, in that he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our ſimilitude and likenes, and not to oure ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes and lykeneſſes, by thys is ſignyfyed the
<pb facs="tcp:173756:4"/> vnitie alſo of one nature and ſubſtaunce. But to procede further concernyng the creation of man, ye ſhall vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Geneſis. 2.</note> that the ſecond chapter of Moyſes boke, called geneſis, in ſpeciall maner doth recorde the ſeuerall making, as well of the bodye of man, by it ſelfe, as alſo of the ſoule by it ſelfe. And as touching the body, ſcrypture doth there ſay, that. <hi>God four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or ſhaped it, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe</hi> Noting therby the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of mans body, aboue the bodyes of other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge creatures. For we rede not of anye other ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng creature, that god ſhaped, or fourmed, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of it, but onely that he made it, and that at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement of almighty god,<note place="margin">Geneſis. i.</note> 
               <hi>the earth brought fourth foure foted beaſtes, &amp; the water, in like maner, brought fourth fyſſhes, &amp; foules.</hi> Only of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcripture witneſſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>God ſhaped it.</hi> And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is written of it, in the ſayd ſecond chapter of geneſis,<note place="margin">Geneſis. 2.</note> howe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed it into the body, which .ii. circumſtaunces, as they import a marueylous excellency of man, aboue other bodely creatures, ſo they moſt clerely declare thexcedyng great goodnes of God, towardes man. Now when god had, in ſuch a ſinguler faſhion, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man, he gaue hym ſouereigntie ouer all the fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of the ſea, ouer the foules of the ayer, and ouer the beaſtes of the lande, yea and made him a Kyng, and Emperour on the earth. And yet not ſatiſfyed with al this, he placed man in Paradyſe, that is in a moſt pleaſaunt garden, where he had planted all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173756:4"/> kynd of frute, beautifull to beholde, and delicious to eate, for man to fede vpon, onely one kynde of fruyte he charged hym on payne of death, (and that not of the body alone, but of the ſoule alſo) vtterlye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne from, which was the fruyte of the tree called in ſcrypture, the tre of knowledge of good, and euyl. And lyke as in a moſt maruelous ſorte he made A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the fyrſte man, ſo in as marueylous, &amp; ſtraunge a ſort he made Eue the firſt woman, euen of a rybbe taken out of Adams lefte ſyde, and her he made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte, and furnyſhed her with like gyftes as he had done Adame the firſt man: What canne we then thinke, or deuyſe, that God might haue don more for vs in our creation, then herein he dyd: He made the ſoule immortall, that is ſuch as ſhulde continue for euer without ende. He furniſhed it with moſte ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler gyftes both of nature and of ſpecial grace alſo The body of man, in the eſtate of originall innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, had in it helth, ſtrength, cumlines, and other like qualities, in the higheſt degre of perfection, it had in it ſelfe then, no fond luſt, or concupiſcens, no pronitie or inclination to euyl, no lothſumnes in doing good, no infirmitie or wekeneſſe, no lacke or want of any qualitie fyt and decent for it. The body of man was then obediente to the ſoule, the ſoule altogether obedient to God. So that on Gods parte, oure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and creator, there is nothyng towardes vs but all perfection, all great kyndnes, al fatherly loue, &amp; fauour, Holy ſcrypture moſt euydently affyrmeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al creatures were made good in their creation, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Vidit deus omnia que fecerat et erant ualde bona. Gene. i.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> That
<pb facs="tcp:173756:5"/> is. <hi>God ſawe al things which he had made, and they were very good.</hi> Which thyng as it is generally true in all creatures concerning their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, ſo is it in a certen degre of excellencye to be verified in man touchyng the eſtate of his originall innocency. Thus we may perceaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the creation of man, al was excellent &amp; parfytte, whiche oughte greatly to inflame vs the more to loue and ſerue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God our moſt louynge creator. But for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as that bleſſed eſtate is loſt, &amp; mankynd by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe thereof, fell into extreme miſerie and wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it is conſequently to be well conſidered of our part, by what meanes man was brought from ſoo good and bleſſed a caſe, to ſo euyll and miſerable an eſtate, whiche poynte well wayed, is a ſufficiente grounde to cauſe vs on the other ſyde vtterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt &amp; abhorre al ſynne. For that greuous fal of man came of ſynne. Synne it was, for which God thruſt man oute of paradyſe, ſynne it was that cauſed the fleſhe to ſtriue agaynſte the ſpirite, and the ſpirite, agaynſt the fleſhe, ſynne it was that broughte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mankynde neceſſitie of bodyly death, and all the infirmities and diſeaſes, which man in thys tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory lyfe ſuſtayneth, ſynne fynally it was, that cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed all the poſteritie of Adam and Eue to be borne in ſtate of dampnation. But ſome perchaunce are deſyrous fardar to knowe, by what meanes man was fyrſt brought to commytte ſynne. For the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng whereof,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> lette vs haue recourſe to the iii. chap. of Geneſis, where it is wrytten: how that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyly ſerpent the deuyll came vnto Eue and ſayde
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173756:5"/> vnto her: <hi>Why hath God gyuen you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement not to eate of euery tree in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radyſe? where vnto the woman anſwered and ſayde: of the fruyte which is in paradiſe we eate, but of the frute of that tree y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the myddeſt of paradyſe, GOD hath charged vs not to eate or touche it? leſte, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce we dye. Then ſayde the ſerpente to the woman: Naye, you ſhall not dye. For God knoweth that whatſoeuer daye you ſhall eate thereof, youre eyes ſhalbe opened, and you ſhalbe like Gods, knowynge good and euyll. The woman therefore ſaw that the tree was good to eate of, and beautifull to the eye, and pleaſaunte to beholde, and ſhe tooke of the fruyte thereof and dyd eate, and gaue part to her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, who alſo dyd eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus through the prouocation of the deuyll, man firſt fell into ſynne. Wherefore as we muſt alwayes abhorre ſynne and forbeare it, bycauſe of the greate miſery it brought vs vnto, ſo ſhould we no les hate, and to the vttermoſt of our power, fly the deuyl and all his ſuggeſtions, knowing that thereby we were fyrſt induced to commytte ſynne. For as thys oure aduerſary was buſye at the begynnynge with oure fyrſt parentes, ſo is he no les,<note place="margin">i. Peter. 5.</note> but rather more buſye with vs at thys preſent, as wytneſſeth Saynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the .v. chapiter of his firſt epyſtle, ſaying.
<pb facs="tcp:173756:6"/> 
               <hi>Youre aduerſary the deuyl, as a roryng lion goeth about, ſeking whom he may deuour.</hi> Thys aduerſary of mankynde, diſdaynynge at the greate felycytye that Adam and Eue were in, neuer ceaſyd queſtionynge, and craftyng with the woman, being the weker and trayler veſſell, vntyll he had made them diſobey gods commaundement: by which their doyng, they loſt the orygynall great innocency which they had at there creation, which being loſt, nether the body woulde be obedient to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, nor the ſoule to god, but al was in man turned vpſidoune: yea therby they fel alſo into neceſſitie of temporall death of body, and (which is worſt of all) into the eſtate of eternall damnation, and euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death, both of body and ſoule. But now, becauſe it maye paraduenture ſeme in ſome mans iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſeyng the thing that Adam and Eue did; was but the eatynge of an appell, therefore their faut was not great, nor deſerued ſo greuous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let vs conſider the circumſtaunces, and we ſhall ſone perceyue the offence not lyght, but verye ſore and heynous. Fyrſt the thyng which god com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded man to forbeare, was a thyng moſt eaſye for hym to forbeare, and ſo much was his faute the greater. Beſides this, whan a man is tolde before of great peryll and daunger that ſhall lyght vpon him if he doo this or that, in caſe after ſuch warnyng he offende therein, his fault is thereby made the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſer. Thyrdly, the leſſe inclination a man hath to any ſynne, the more he ſynneth yf he doo the ſame. Nowe Adam and Eue, had in them no inclination
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173756:6"/> at al, nother to one vice nor to other. Fourthly, when a man hath late receyued great benefites at hys ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygns handes, if he incontinently breake his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe wyll, the contempt and diſobedience is made therby the greater. The thyng that Adam and Eue dyd eate, was in dede but an appell, yet the eatyng thereof in that caſe, was an high diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce againſt god, and the corrupting of all mankynd, for as much as they two were the very route, whereof all men muſt ryſe, and the route being once naughte, howe can the tree or braunches, cummynge of that route, be good? Therfore S. Paule in his Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in the .v. chapiter thereof ſaieth.<note place="margin">Roma. 5.</note> 
               <hi>By the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one man, ſynne came vpon all men, to condempnacion,</hi> and in the ſame chapiter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after, he ſayeth to lyke purpoſe, <hi>throughe the diſobedience of one man, manye became ſynners.</hi> And within a lytle after he ſaieth. <hi>Sinne came into this world by one man, &amp; through ſynne came death, &amp; ſo death paſſed to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Thus haue you hard fyrſte the louynge kyndnes of God to man, in that he created hym in ſo worthye a maner, nexte ye haue harde the myſchyfe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to mankynd by ſynne, and thirdly what an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme enemy alſo the deuyll is vnto vs. In an other homily hereafter, ye ſhal heare of the exceding great mercy of god, in deliuering ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind by a meruelous maner, out of the eſtate of this dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore to conclude for thys preſente tyme, this ſhalbe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb facs="tcp:173756:7"/> you, that you fayle not daylye and howrelye to geue moſt harty thankes to almyghty God, for that he of his mere goodnes created you, &amp; created you, not without ſenſe, as the ſtones, not without reaſon as the brute beaſtes, but hathe gyuen you all nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities and powers that other corporall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures haue, and beſydes, hathe perticularlye planted in you reaſon and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, and ſondry goodly qualities of body and ſoule, ſeuerall to the nature of man only, and not commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to man, and other erthly creatures. This is furthermore alſo to exhorte you, that remembryng what miſerye came to mankynde by ſynne, and by ſuch a ſynne, as in ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might ſeme to be but very ſmale, it is to wytte, by eatynge of an appel, you wyl be circumſpecte in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding of al kinde of ſynne, and diſobedience, be the thinge in hys owne nature neuer ſo ſmale a thynge, whyche is by God hym ſelfe, or by ſuche as we owe obedience vnto, commaunded. Fynallye and laſte of al, this is to exhorte you, to conſyder dilygently that we haue a deadly ennemy, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyreth oure deſtruction, and doth mooſt craftely and buſely trauayle by all meanes wyth vs, to worke the ſame, of whoſe mooſte ſubtyll and wilye traynes, we muſte principally take hede of, whiche graunt vnto vs all, the bleſſed trinitie, the father, the Sonne, and the holye ghoſte, to whome be all honoure and glorye worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ende. Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfeld ſacrae theologiae profeſſor Arch. London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173756:7"/>
            <head>¶ An homely of the miſery of all mankinde, and of hys condempnation to euerlaſtynge deathe, by hys owne ſynne.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holye ghoſte,</hi> in wryting the holy ſcripture, is in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, then to pull downe mannes vayne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and pryde, which of all vices, is mooſt vniuerſallye graffed in mankynde, euen from the fyrſte infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our fyrſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adam. And therefore, we reade in many places of ſcripture, many notable leſſons agaynſt this olde rooted vyce, to teache vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable vertue of humilitie, howe to know our ſelues, &amp; to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, what we be, of our ſelues. In the booke of Geneſis, almyghty God geueth vs all, a tytle &amp; name in oure great graunde father Adam, which ought to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vs al, to conſyder what we be, whereof we be, from whence we came, &amp; whyther we ſhall, ſayenge thus. <hi>In ſudore vultus tui veſceris pane tuo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene 3.</note> 
               <hi>donec reuertaris in terram de qua ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptus es: quia puluis es, et in puluerem reuerteris.</hi> That is to ſaye, <hi>In the ſweate of thy face thou ſhalt eate thy breade, vntyll thou retourneſt into the earth, oute of whyche thou waſte taken: for duſt thou art, &amp; into duſt thou ſhalt retourne,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173756:8"/> Here (as it were in a glaſſe) we may learne to know ourſelues, that we be but grounde, earthe, and duſt, and that to grounde, earthe, and duſte, we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne agayne, whyche name and title of earthe, and duſte, appoynted, and aſſigned by God, to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, the holye Patriarche Abraham, dyd well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member: and therefore he calleth hym ſelfe by that name, when he maketh his earneſt prayer for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorre, ſaying in the .xviii. of Geneſis. <hi>Cum ſim puluis et cuius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 18</note> that is to ſaye, <hi>ſeyng I am duſt and aſhes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudith. 3. and. 9. Iob. 13. Hiere. 6. and .25.</note> And we reade that Iudith, Heſter, Iob, Hieremye, with other holy men and women, in the olde teſtament, did vſe ſacke clothe, and did caſte duſte, and aſſhes vpon theyr heades, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled theyr ſynnefull lyuynge. They called and cryed to God for helpe, and mercy, with ſuche a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſacke clothe, duſte, and aſſhes, that thereby they might declare to the hole world, what an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and lowlye eſtimation, they had of theim ſelues, and howe well they remembred theyr name, &amp; tytle aforeſayde, theyr vyle, corrupte, frayle nature, duſte, earth, and aſſhes. The booke of wyſedome alſo, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge to pull downe oure proude ſtomakes,<note place="margin">Sapience. 7.</note> moueth vs diligently, to remember our mortall, and earthely generation, which we haue al of him, that was firſt made: and that all men, aſwell kynges, as ſubiectes, doo come into this worlde, and doo goo oute of the ſame in lyke ſorte, that is, as of oure ſelues, full myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as we maye daylye ſee. And almyghtye God commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded his Prophet Eſay, to make a proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Eſai. 11.</note> and to crye to the hole worlde: <hi>that all fleſſhe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173756:8"/> is graſſe, and that all the glorye of man, is as the flower of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feilde, the graſſe is wythered, and the flower doth fall away, for the winde of our Lord bloweth vpon it</hi> The people ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is graſſe, whiche dryeth vp, and the flower fadeth away, but the woorde of our Lord abydeth for euer. Accordynge wherevnto, the holye prophet Iob, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge in hym ſelfe great experience of miſerable and ſynnefull eſtate of man, dothe open the ſame to the worlde in theſe wordes. <hi>Homo natus de muliere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> 
               <hi>breui viuens tempore, repletur multis miſerijs, qui quaſi flos egreditur, et conteritur, et fugit velut vmbra, et nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in eodem ſtatu permanet et dignum ducis ſuper huiuſcemodi aperire oculos tuos, et adducere eum tecum in iudicium? quis poteſt facere mundum de immundo conceptum ſemine?</hi> That is to ſay <hi>Man beynge borne of a woman, lyuynge a ſhorte tyme, is full of manyfolde miſeries, he ſpryngeth vp lyke a flower, &amp; fadeth againe, vanyſhynge away</hi> (as it were <hi>a ſhadow, and neuer contineweth in one ſtate. And doeſt thou iudge it mete (O Lorde to open thyne eyes vpon ſuche a one, and to brynge hym to iudgement with thee? who can make hym cleane that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued of an vncleane ſeede?</hi> In dede all men of theyr euylnes and naturall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, were ſo vniuerſallye gyuen to ſynne, that God (as the ſcripture teſtifyeth) repented y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he made man. And by ſynne,<note place="margin">Gene. 5. and. 7.</note> his indignation was ſo muche prouoked agaynſte the worlde, that he drowned all the worlde wyth Noes fludde (except Noe him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:173756:9"/> and hys lytle houſeholde.) It is not withoute greate cauſe, that the ſcripture of God, dothe ſo many times call all menne here in this worlde earthe, ſayenge. <hi>(O thou earth, thou earth, thou earthe, heare the woorde of oure Lorde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiere. 22.</note>) Hiere. xxij. This, oure ryght name, vocation, and tytle: earthe, earthe, earth, pronounced by the prophet, ſheweth what we be in dede, by what ſoeuer other ſtyle, tytle, or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doo call vs. Thus, he plainly nameth vs, who knoweth beſt, bothe what we be, &amp; what we oughte of right to be called. And thus he deſcribeth vs, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge by hys faythfull Apoſtle S. Paule to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes the .iii.<note place="margin">Roma. 3.</note> Chapiter, ſaying. <hi>All men, Iewes and Gentiles, are vnder ſynne: there is none ryghteous, no, not one: there is none that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth, there is none that ſeketh after God, they are all goone out of the waie, they are all vnprofitable, there is none that dothe good, no not one, theyr throte is an open ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, with theyr tongues, they haue vſed crafte and deceyte, the poyſon of ſerpentes is vnder theyr lyppes, theyr mouthe is full of curſynge and bitternes, theyr feete are ſwifte to ſhed bloude, deſtruction and wretchednes are in theyr wayes, &amp; the waye of peace haue they not knowen, there is no feare of God be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore theyr eyes.</hi> And in an other place, that is to wit,<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> Galathians .iij. S Paule wryteth thus: (<hi>God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173756:9"/> hathe wrapped all nations in vnbeleif,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roma. 11</note> 
               <hi>that he myght haue mercy on all The ſcripture concludeth all vnder ſynne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> 
               <hi>that the promiſe by the faythe in Ieſus Chriſte, ſhould be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto theim that beleue.</hi> S. Paule in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, paynteth vs oute in our collours, callyng vs the chyldren of the wrathe of God, when we be borne: ſayenge alſo, that we cannot thinke a good thought of our ſelues, much leſſe, we can ſay wel, or doo wel, of our ſelues. And the wyſeman ſayeth, in the booke of Prouerbes,<note place="margin">Pro. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the iuſte man falleth ſeuen ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes a daye.</hi> The mooſte tried and approued man Iob, feared all his woorkes: S. Iohn the Baptiſte, beynge ſanctifyed in hys mothers wombe,<note place="margin">Luce. i.</note> and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before he was borne, called an aungel, and great before the Lord, replenyſhed euen from hys byrthe, with the holy ghoſte, the preparer of the way for our ſauioure Chriſte, to be more then a Prophet, and the greateſt that euer was borne of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet he plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely graunteth, that he had nede to be waſſhed of Chriſt: he worthely extolleth and glorifieth his lord, and mayſter Chriſte, and humbleth hym ſelfe, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to vnbuckle hys ſhooes, and geueth all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and glorye to God. So doeth ſaincte Paule, both oft, and euydently confeſſe hym ſelfe, what he was of hym ſelfe, euer geuynge (as a mooſt faythfull ſeruaunte oughte to doo) all prayſe to hys mayſter and ſauioure.<note place="margin">Iohn .i. and .2.</note> So doeth bleſſed ſainct Iohn the euangeliſt, in the name of hym ſelfe, and of all other holy men, be they neuer ſo iuſte, make this open con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion:
<pb facs="tcp:173756:10"/> 
               <hi>If we ſaye, that we haue no ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs: If we knowledge our ſynnes, God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and iuſt, to forgyue vs oure ſynnes, and to clenſe vs from all vnryghteouſnes: If we ſaye, we haue not ſynned, we make him a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and hys woorde is not in vs.</hi> Wherefore, the wyſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7</note> in the booke called Eccleſiaſtes, openly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clareth, that there is not one iuſte man vpon the earth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> that dothe good, and ſynneth not. And ſainct Dauid is aſhamed of hys ſynne, but not to confeſſe hys ſynne. Howe ofte, howe earneſtlye, and how la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentablye doeth he deſyre Gods greate mercye, for hys great offences, and that God ſhould not enter in to iudgement wyth hym? And agayne, howe well wayeth this holy man hys ſynnes, when he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that they be ſo many in number, and ſo hydde, and harde to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that it is in maner vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19</note> to knowe, vtter, or number them? Wherefore, he, hauyng an earneſt, and depe contemplation, and conſyderation of hys ſynnes, and yet not commyng to the bottome of them, maketh ſupplication to God, to forgyue hym hys priuye, ſecrete, hydde ſynnes: to the knowledge of the whyche, he cannot attayne. He wayeth ryghtlye hys ſynnes, from the originall roote, and ſprynge heade, perceyuinge inclinations, prouocations, ſtyrringes, ſtinginges, buddes, braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Pſal, 2.</note> dregges, infections, taſtes, felinges, and ſentes of them, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinewe in him ſtil. Wherfore he ſayeth: <hi>Marke, &amp; behold, I was conceiued in ſynnes:</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:173756:10"/> He ſaieth not ſinne, but in the plurel number, ſinnes: for aſmuche, as oute of one, as fountayne, ſpryngeth all the reſte.</p>
            <p>And oure ſauiour Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Math. 9</note> there is none good but God, and that we can doo nothing that is good, without hym, or no man can come to the father, but by hym. He commaundeth vs all to ſaye, that we be vnprofitable ſeruauntes, when we haue doone all that we can doo. He preferreth the penitente Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane, before the proudeholye, and gloryouſe Phary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey: He calleth hym ſelfe a phiſition, not to them that be hole, but to them that be ſicke, and haue nede of his ſalue, for theyr ſore. He teacheth vs in oure pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to reacknowledge oure ſelues ſynners, and to aſke forgeuenes, and deliueraunce from all euyls, at oure heauenly fathers hande. He declareth that the ſynnes of oure owne hartes, doo defyle oure owne ſelues. He teacheth that an euyll woorde, or thought, deſerueth condempnation, affyrmynge, that we ſhal geue an accompte, for euery ydle woorde: He ſayth, he came not to ſaue, but the ſhepe that were vtterlye loſt, and caſt awaye. Therefore, fewe of the proude, iuſt, learned, wyſe, perfite, and holy Phariſeis, were ſaued by hym, becauſe they iuſtified them ſelues, by theyr counterfeyte holynes, before men. Wherefore good people, let vs beware of ſuch Hypocriſie, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorye, and iuſtifieng of our ſelues. Let vs looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our feete, and then downe oure Pecockes fethers, downe proude harte, downe vayne claye, frayle, and brittle veſſels. Of our ſelues, we be crabbe trees, that can bryng furth no Aples, we be of our ſelues, of ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:173756:11"/> earth, as can bryng furth but weedes, nettels, bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, bryers, cocle, and darnell. Our fruytes be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the fyfte chapiter to the Galathians. We haue neither fayth, Charitie, hope, pacience, chaſtitie, nor any thinge els that good is, but of God: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, theſe vertues be called there, the fruytes of the holy ghoſt, and not the fruytes of man. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, acknowledge our ſelues before God, (as we be in dede) myſerable and wretched ſynners. And let vs earneſtly repent, and humble our ſelues hartelye, to crye to God for mercye. Lette vs all confeſſe with mouth, and harte, that we be full of imperfections. Let vs knowe our owne workes, of what imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they be, and then we ſhall not ſtande folyſhely, and arrogantly, in oure owne conceytes. For truely, there is imperfections, in our beſte woorkes: we doo not loue God, ſo muche as we are bounde to doo, with all our harte, mynde, and power: we doo not feare God ſo muche as we ought to doo: we doo not praye to God, but with great and many imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We geue, forgeue, beleue, loue, and hope vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye: we ſpeake, thinke, and doo, vnperfectlye, we fyght agaynſt the deuyll, the worlde, and the fleſſhe, vnperfectlye.<note place="margin">Luke. 5.</note> Let vs therfore, not be aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe playnely, oure ſtate of imperfection: yea, let vs not be aſhamed to confeſſe imperfection, euen in all our workes: Let none of vs be aſhamed, to ſay with holye S. Peter: <hi>I am a ſynfull man.</hi> Let vs all ſaye with the holye prophet Dauyd:<note place="margin">Pſal. 160.</note> 
               <hi>We haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with our fathers, we haue done amyſſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173756:11"/> and dealte wyckedlye.</hi> Let vs all make confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the prodigall ſonne to oure father,<note place="margin">Luce. 15.</note> and ſaye with him: We haue ſynned agaynſt heauen, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee (O father) we are not worthye to be called thy ſonnes. Lette vs all ſaye with holye Baruch:<note place="margin">Baruch. 2.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord our God, to vs is worthely aſcribed ſhame and confuſion, and to thee, ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. We haue ſynned, we haue done wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we haue behaued our ſelues vngodlye, in all thy ryghteouſnes</hi> Let vs all ſay with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophete Danyell: <hi>O Lorde, rightuouſnes belongeth to thee, vnto vs belongeth confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. We haue ſynned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daniel. 9</note> 
               <hi>we haue bene naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we haue offended, we haue fled from the, wee haue gone backe from all thy preceptes, and iudgementes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we learne of all good men, in holy ſcripture, to humble oure ſelues, and to exalte, extoll, prayſe, magnifye, and glorifye God.</p>
            <p>Thus ye haue hearde, howe euil we be of our ſelues, how of our ſelues, &amp; by our ſelues, we haue no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, helpe, nor ſaluation: but contrarywyſe, ſynne, dampnation, and deathe euerlaſtynge: whyche, yf wee depely weyghe, and conſyder, we ſhall the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtande, the great mercy of God, and howe our ſaluacion commeth onely by Chriſte: for in oure ſelues, as of our ſelues, we fynde nothynge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be delyuered from this miſerable capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitye, into the whyche we were caſte throughe the
<pb facs="tcp:173756:12"/> enuye of the deuyll, by tranſgreſſion of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, in our fyrſte parent Adam. We are al become vncleane: but we al of our ſelues, are not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe our ſelues, nor to make one an other of vs cleane. We are by nature, the chyldren of Gods wrathe: we are not hable of oure ſelues, to make vs the children and inheritours of Gods glorye. We are ſhepe that runne aſtray: we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not without god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des grace,<note place="margin">i. Peter. 2.</note> and helpe, come agayne to the ſhepe folde: ſo great is our imperfection and weakenes. In our ſelues therefore, maye not we glorye, which of oure ſelues are nothynge but ſynnefull, neyther maye we bragge of our woorkes that we doo, whyche all be ſo vnperfecte and vnpure, that they are not of them ſelues, hable to ſtande before the ryghteous throne of GOD, as the holye Prophete Dauid ſayeth: <hi>Enter not into iudgemente wyth thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte, O Lorde, for no man that lyueth, ſhalbe founde ryghtuous in thy ſyghte.</hi> To God therefore, muſte wee flye, or els ſhall we neuer fynde peace, reſt, and quyetnes of conſcience, in oure hartes. For he is the father of mercyes, and God of all conſolation, he is the Lord, wyth whome is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſe redemption.<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.</note> He is the God, whyche of his owne mercy ſaueth vs, and ſetteth out hys charitie, and exceadyng loue toward vs, in that of his owne voluntary goodnes, when we were peryſhed, he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, and prouyded an euerlaſtynge kyngedome for vs. And all theſe heauenly treaſures are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, of hys mere mercy, freelye. And for whoſe ſake? Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173756:12"/> for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that pure, and vndefiled Lambe of God. He is that dearely beloued ſonne, for whoſe ſake, God is fullye pacifyed, ſatyſfyed, and ſet at one with man. He is the Lambe of God,<note place="margin">i. Peter. 2</note> whyche taketh away the ſynnes of the worlde, of whome it maye be truely ſpoken, that he dyd all thynges well, and in his mouthe was founde no crafte, nor ſubtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. Lykewyſe he maye ſaye: the prynce of the world came, and in me he hath nothyng. He maye ſay alſo: whiche of you ſhall reproue me of anye faulte: He is that hyghe and euerlaſtynge prieſt, whyche hathe offred him ſelfe to God, when he inſtituted the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aultar, and once for all, in a bloudye ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce, doone vpon the croſſe, with which oblation, he hath made perfecte for euermore, theim that are ſanctifyed. He is the mediatoure,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3</note> betwene God and man, which payed our raunſome to God, wyth hys owne bloude, and wyth that, hathe clenſed vs from ſynne. He is the Phiſition, whiche healeth all our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. He is that ſauioure,<note place="margin">Math. 1</note> whiche ſaueth the people from al theyr ſinnes. To be ſhort, he is that flowing, and mooſt plenteous fountayne, of whoſe fulnes, all we haue receyued. For in him are all the treaſures of the wyſedome, and knowledge of God hydden. And in hym, and by him, haue we from God the father, al good thinges, perteyning eyther to the bodye, or to the ſoule. O how muche then, are we bounde to this oure heauenlye father, for theſe, his greate mercyes, whiche he hathe ſo plenteouſly declared vnto vs, in Chriſte Ieſu oure Lorde, and ſauioure: What than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, worthy, and ſufficiente, can we giue to him? Let
<pb facs="tcp:173756:13"/> vs all with one accorde, burſte oute wyth ioyful voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, euer prayſynge, and magnifyenge this Lorde of mercy, for hys tender kyndenes ſhewed to vs, in hys dearely beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt oure Lorde.</p>
            <p>Let vs nowe learne to know our ſelues, our frayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and weakenes, withoute anye oſtentation, or boaſtynge of oure owne good deedes, and merites. Let vs alſo knowledge the exceadynge mercye of God, towarde vs, and confeſſe, that as of our ſelues commeth all euyll, and dampnation, ſo lykewyſe of hym, commeth all goodnes and ſaluation, as God him ſelfe ſaieth by the Prophet Oze:<note place="margin">Oze. 13</note> 
               <hi>O Iſrael, thy deſtruction commeth of thy ſelfe, but in me onely is thy helpe and comforte.</hi> If wee thus humbly ſubmyt our ſelues in the ſyghte of God, we maye be ſure, that in the tyme of hys viſitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he wil lyfte vs vp, vnto the kyngedome of hys dearely beloued ſonne, Chriſte Ieſu our Lorde: to whome with the father, and the holy gooſte, be all honoure and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, for euer. Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfeld ſacrae theologiae profeſſor. Arch. London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:173756:13"/>
            <head>¶ An Homelye of the redemption of man.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was declared</hi> vnto you, good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten people, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt homelye, howe oure fyrſte parentes Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Eue, were by the ſynguler good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and eſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of almyghtye God, created ryghte worthye creatures, and in the eſtate of parfytte innocencye. It was alſo ſhewed howe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough diſobedience to theyr creator, they broughte them ſelues, and all mankind, into the eſtate of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge damnation. Nowe ſhall you conſequentlye heare, of the delyueraunce of man, out of that damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eſtate, that is, of oure redemption. For the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge whereof, you muſt perfytlye beare in mynde, that the whole nature of man, both in bodye and ſoule, was thorough orygynall ſynne, greatelye defiled. For the ſoule (which is the cheif part of man) loſte thereby the eſpeciall gyftes of grace, with whiche it was indued in the creation, and beſydes that, it was alſo maymed in the gyftes of nature, as in memorye, intelligence, wyll, and other lyke. And the body (whiche is the inferior parte) it alſo was by the meanes of orygynall ſynne, brought to the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye eſtate of mortalitie, ſo that it muſte nedes die,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:14"/> and was throughe that ſynne of our ſayde fyrſte pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, made weke, and brought to be ſubiecte, to ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye kyndes of infirmities, and ſyckenes: and nother coulde God, of his iuſtice, receaue man agayne to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, and ſtate of eternall lyfe (beynge thus in bodye and ſoule, by his owne defaulte defyled) vnles he were fyrſt made pure, and cleane, againe nether man was able to helpe him ſelfe herein, no, nor yet anye angell at al. Wherefore, almyghty God (whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy excedeth all his workes) pytienge the wretched caſe that mankynde was in, dyd appoynt, euen from the begynnynge, his onely ſonne, the ſeconde perſon in trinitie, to be the ſauiour of the worlde, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore man againe, to perfit clennes, both in body, and ſoule, and that, by the way of very iuſtice, in making a full amendes, and payinge a ſufficiente raunſome for ſynne. And this ſonne of God (accordynge to the wyll of his father,) dyd take vpon hym the nature of man, ioyninge to his euerlaſtynge Godheade, the whole, and perfyte nature of manhode, not making that nature of man, which he toke, a new of nothing, as he dyd heauen and earth, nor yet makynge it, of a clod of earth, as he dyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Adam, but he toke the nature of man, of the very ſubſtaunce of the vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn Mary his mother, that lyke as Adam and Eue, brought them ſelues, &amp; all theyr poſteritie, through ſinne, into the eſtate of eternal dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo Chriſt, takynge vpon him, the very ſelfe ſame nature, beyng deſcended from Adam and Eue, vnto. the Vyrgin Mary, and of her beynge taken, and ioyned in hym to the godhead, in vnitie of perſon, ſhould by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173756:14"/> &amp; through death, wyllyngly ſuffered in that his moſt innocent bodye, not only hym ſelf, become immortal ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; haue glory euerlaſting, but make ſo many alſo, partakers of lyke bleſſednes, as ſhuld en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the merites of his paſſion. Wherefore, it is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pernicious errour, to thynke that chriſt tooke not his fleſhe, of the verye fleſhe of the bleſſed Vyrgyn Mary his mother. Howe could his death haue done me good, if it were not of the ſame nature that I am of?<note place="margin">Heb. ii.</note> &amp; therefore S. Paule in his ſeconde chapiter of his Epiſtle to the Hebrues ſayeth. <hi>Qui ſanctificat, et qui ſanctificantur, ex vno omnes,</hi> that is. <hi>He that ſanctyfyeth, and they which are ſanctifyed, are all of one:</hi> and within a lyttle after he ſayeth farther, <hi>Debuit per omnia fratribus aſſimulari, vt miſericors fieret, et fidelis pontifex, ad deum, vt repropitiaret delicta populi,</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſte muſte in all poyntes, become lyke to his brethren, that he myght be a merciful and fruteful Biſſhop to Godward, to procure mercy for the ſinnes of the people.</hi> If Chriſt tooke not the fleſh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Virgin Marye, howe is that promyſe fulfylled, which God made immediatly after the falle of our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, when he thruſt them out of paradiſe, at which tyme, he ſaid vnto the ſerpente (as it is written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde chapiter of Geneſis.) <hi>I wyl ſet enmitie betwixt the, and the womans ſede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and it ſhall treade downe thy hedde:</hi> Lo, how mercifully God dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth wyth mankynde, He promyſed that one ſhoulde be borne of the ſede and ſtocke of Eue, which ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:173756:15"/> vanquyſhe our ghoſtly enemy the diuell. Nowe in that he calleth hym the ſede of the woman, he moſte playnely declareth, that he muſt nedes haue in him the ſelfe ſame nature that the woman had. Agayne God makyng the ſecond promyſe of the ſame ſede, to come of the ſtocke of Abraham the patriarke, ſaid vnto Abraham, (as is wytneſſed in the .xxii. of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſys) <hi>In thy ſede ſhall all the nations of the world be bleſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 22</note> &amp; many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeares after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, he promyſſed lykewyſe to Kyng Dauyd, that, that ſede ſhould come of hym to. Which promyſes of almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, were not to be verified in Chryſt, if he toke not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his fleſh, of the Virgin Mary his mother. But here it may ſeme ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to ſome, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty god (ſeing he inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginninge, to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his ſonne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to be incarnate for mans rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption) did defer the ſendinge of hym ſoo longe, that is, the ſpace of foure thouſande yeares or ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboute. To whome it is to be aunſwered, that the long taryinge of Chryſte, before he was incarnate, came not of lacke of good wyl in god, towardes vs, but of vnredines, and lacke of good diſpoſition, to receyue hym on oure partes. For if Chryſte ſhoulde haue commen in the begynnyng of the worlde, men would haue thought, that if God had ſuffered them to vſe theyr owne natural powers, they would haue attayned ſaluation well inough, without any other helpe on Gods parte. Agayne, thoughe after longe experience, and trauayle of man, folowing the onelye lyghte of nature, it was euydente, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a ſpeciall ayde from God, to the attaynynge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173756:15"/> of euerlaſtynge lyfe, yet the worlde myghte haue demed, that in caſe God of hys goodnes, had geuen vnto manne ſome ſpeciall lyghte, and knowledge of hys wyll and pleaſure, that then vndoughtedlye, without farther helpe, he folowynge ſuche ſpecyall lyght, and knowledge, myght be able well inoughe to attayne to euerlaſtynge lyfe. Therefore, to take all ſuche excuſes awaye, and that we ſhould plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnderſtande, that after we once fell into ſinne, neither the light of nature in vs, neyther the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the wyll of God, by ſpeciall reuelation ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs, was able to helpe vs, god ſuffred man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde to trauel, fyrſt by the light of nature, ſecondly by the lawe of Moyſes, and yet man ranne ſtyll far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and farther, into damnation. Whereby it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that though knowledge of the truth be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, to the attayninge of euerlaſtinge lyfe, yet ſuche knowledge (be it neuer ſo great) beyng in a man cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with ſynne, is to feble and to weake to purge him of ſinne. For purgation &amp; clenſing of ſynne, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by ſome other meanes, beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of the truth: and therfore S. Paule in the fyrſte chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his epiſtle to the Romaines, moſt plainly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that in the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of nature, men knew inough of God, but yet, not withſtanding theyr kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they fell into abhominable idolatry. The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of S. Paule, in that place are theſe. <hi>So much as may be knowen of god, is manifeſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (that is to ſay, in thoſe whiche liued vnder the lawe of nature, from Adam vnto Moyſes) <hi>For his inui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible
<pb facs="tcp:173756:16"/> thinges, euen his eternal power, &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, were ſene of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being vnderſtanded by the works of the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, ſo that they are without excuſe, bicauſe, that when they knew God, they glorified hym not as god nether were thankeful, but becamful of vanitie in their imaginacions.</hi> And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght whiche men had by the lawes of nature, was not of force, to kepe them from ſynne, ſo nether the lawe of Moyſes, beyng opened from god him ſelfe by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, could ſuffice to ryde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from ſinne (as S. Paule in the ſecond chapiter of his foreſayde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle teſtifieth ſaying) <hi>Behold thou art a Iew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roma. 2</note> 
               <hi>and thou doeſt reſt in the law, and doeſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in god, and doeſt know his wyl and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; being inſtructed in the lawe, thou do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt allowe that is beſt, and doeſt truſte that thou art a guyde of the blinde, a light to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are in darkenes, an inſtructour of the folyſhe, a mayſter of the ignorante, and that thou knoweſt by the lawe the fourme of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens &amp; truth: but yet thou that teacheſt other, teacheſt not thy ſelfe, thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> precheſt againſt aduoutri, art an aduoutrer thy ſelf, thou that dooeſt defye Idoles, commytteſt ſacriledge thy ſelfe, thou that doeſt glorye in the lawe, through tranſgreſſing of the lawe, doeſt dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173756:16"/> God, for the name of God, throughe you, is blaſphemed amongeſt the gentyles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it is euydente, by the doctryne of Saynte Paule, that nother by the common lawe of nature, nether by the ſpecial knowledge of the law of Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, man was able to auoyde eternal da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnation, but that he neded, beſides ſuch knowledge, of ſome other helpe that is, of amendes, to be made for his ſinnes, and thereby, to be reduced into the fauour of god a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and to haue aboundaunce of grace geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hym, by which grace he ſhould both in his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better eſtabliſhed, &amp; be able alſo, according to knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, to walke in the truth. For this amendes to be made, the ſecond perſon in trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being god immortal, became mortal man, &amp; was made in all partes like vnto one of vs (ſinne only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and he did vnite vnto his godhead, the body and ſoule of man, in vnitie of perſon, in ſuch a merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſort, that as in vs, the body being of one nature, and the ſoule being of an other nature, doo make yet but one perſon, ſo in hym the nature of God, and the whole perfect nature of man, doo make but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Of this incomprehenſible vnion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godhed, &amp; manhed in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> S. Ihon ſpeaketh in the fyrſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of his goſpell, ſaying. <hi>Verbum caro factum eſt, et habitauit in nobis, the worde,</hi> (that is the ſonne of God) <hi>Was made fleſhe,</hi>) (that is man) <hi>&amp; dwelt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt vs.</hi> he dwelt here on the earth, (as ſcripture decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,) aboue .xxxiij. yeares, and when he had fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led al thynges, accordyng to the ſayinges of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:173756:17"/> prophetes, whiche were to be fulfylled of hym be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his paſſion, then he ſuffred death willingly, yea, the death of the croſſe, by ſuche payne, (wrongefullye procured of the deuil againſt him) to raunſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde oute of captiuitie, whiche it ſuſtayned vnder the deuyll mooſt iuſtly: and that this raunſome ſhold be perfyt, he ſuffred ſondry ſortes of mooſte ſpytefull wronges, and intollerable paynes, &amp; tormentes, in his moſt pure, and innocent body, as buffeting, bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, ſcourgyng, plattynge on his head, a crowne of thorne, hanginge on the croſſe, pearcing of his handes and fete with nayles, openynge of his ſyde with a ſpeare, and ſhedynge of his mooſte precious bloude, whiche paſſion of his, as it is a mooſt parfyt myrrour, and glaſſe for vs, therein to beholde the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedynge great loue of god towarde vs, whiche ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not his onelye ſonne, but for vs all gaue hym to dye, ſo it is a ſufficient occaſion, to brynge all men in extreme hatred of the deuyll, and ſynne: from daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of whome, mankynde coulde not be rydde, but onely by ſo paynefull a death, of the ſonne of God. What can we loke for at gods handes, yf we ſynne from hence forth, but wrath and vengeaunce, ſeynge he hath once delyuered vs from ſynne, by ſo merciful a meanes? All that our ſauyoure Chriſte ſuffered, he wyllingely ſuffered for our ſynnes, hym ſelfe hauing neuer deſerued anye whyt of payne, as who neuer ſynned. And yet his paſſion, though it be in it ſelfe a ſufficiente raunſome, for the ſynnes of the whole worlde, yet it taketh not place in all men: not for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie in it ſelfe, but for defaute in them, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173756:17"/> ſhoulde condignely receaue the merites thereof. For this you muſt know, that God requyreth in vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thinges, to be accompliſhed by our owne wil, and conſent, without the whiche, we can not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, no more, than yf Chriſt had neuer dyed for vs. What thinges theſe are, ſhalbe hereafter declared vnto you. In the meane ſeaſon, lyft vp your hartes, and open them awyde, to receaue in, vnto them, a great loue towardes God, who ſo nobylye created vs, and when we, through our owne defaute, were fallen into the eſtate of endles miſery, and wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, ſo mercyfully redemed vs, by the paſſion, and death of his onely ſonne our ſauiour Chriſt. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ſynne, and nought els, brought vs fyrſt oute of Gods fauour, and that to take awaye ſynne, the ſonne of God was incarnate, and ſuffered mooſte paynefull death on the croſſe, and therefore hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, flee you all kynde of ſynne, and fight inceſſantly, agaynſt your ghoſtly enemye the deuyll, who being vanquiſhed by Chriſt, is not able now to ouerthrow vs, if we, in the right fayth of Chriſt, valiantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande hym, whiche to doo, graunt vnto vs, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed trinitie, the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt, to whome be all honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſsor. Arch. London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:18"/>
            <head>¶ An Homely declaryng how the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſt is appliable to vs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the death and paſſion of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour chriſt, be in va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lue a ſufficient raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for the ſynnes of the whole world, yet in effect it taketh not place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world. For neyther Turke, Iew, nor in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidell, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting beleif in Chriſte, can take good by the death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, the ſcripture moſt manifeſtly affyrming in the .xvi.<note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> chapter of S. Marke, that <hi>Whoſoeuer doth not beleue ſhall be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned.</hi> Agayne, euyll lyfe, bryngeth to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyl lyuer, eternall death, beleue he neuer ſoo wel. As S. Paule witneſſeth, in the .v. chapiter of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Galathians,<note place="margin">Gala. 3.</note> where he ſayth: <hi>Walke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirite, and fulfyll not the luſtes of the fleſhe. For the fleſh luſteth contrary to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the ſpirit contrary to the fleſhe. Theſe are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary one to another, ſo that you do not what ye woulde: But and yf ye be led of the ſpirit, then are ye not vnder the law. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the fleſhe are manifeſt which are theſe aduoutry, fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnclennes, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonnes,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173756:18"/> ydolatry, wytchcrafte, hatred, variau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencion, wrath, ſtryfe, ſedition, ſectes, enuye, murder, dronkennes, glotony, and ſuch like, of which I tel you before (as I haue told you in tyme paſt) that they which commit ſuche thinges, ſhal not inherit the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Thus you perceaue that to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enioying of the death, and paſſion of Chriſte, theſe two poyntes are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit of our behalf, the one, to beleue rightly, the other, to lyue vpryghtlye, whiche two poyntes, no man is able otherwyſe to knowe (except it be by ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation from God) but onely by the catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, whiche catholyke churche, our ſauioure Chriſte hath appoynted, to be the onely ſcoole, for all men to come and repayre vnto, to learne ſuche truth, as is mete for them to know, for the attayning of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng life. This catholike church, and no other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vnderſtandinge of ſcripture, &amp; the knowledge of all thinges neceſſary to ſaluation. To this church, Chriſt maketh promis, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xvi. of Iohn,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> ſaying: <hi>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſpirite of truth ſhal come, he ſhal teache you al truth.</hi> To this churche alſo he maketh that other promis, written in the .xxviii. of Mathew, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Beholde I am with you, to the ende of the world.</hi> This Catholyke churche, thus gouerned by the holy Ghoſt, &amp; aſſiſted alwayes, of Chriſt him ſelfe, neuer yet fayled, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme of the Apoſtles, hitherto, ne ſhal fayl, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende, nether can it be deceaued in any neceſſarye
<pb facs="tcp:173756:19"/> truth, accordyng as Chryſt promyſeth in the .xvi. of Mathewe,<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> ſaying. <hi>That hell gates ſhal not pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle agaynſt the churche.</hi> where, by hel gates he meaneth errour, as yf he had ſayd, that the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche ſhall neuer be ouercome with erroure. For this cauſe S. Paule in the third chapiter of his firſt epiſtle to Timothe,<note place="margin">Timoth. 1.</note> calleth the catholike church, <hi>the piller and grounde of truth.</hi> This catholike churche, muſt in al ages nedes be an open knowen churche, and ſuch a company, as among whych, the trueth is openly preached, ells Chryſt woulde not haue ſayd, (as it is wrytten in the .v. of Mathewe) <hi>A citie that is ſet on a hyl,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math 5</note> 
               <hi>can not be hyd, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do men lyght a candel, and put it vnder a buſhel but on a candelſtycke, and it geueth lyght vnto all that are in the houſe.</hi> Wherfore they do great iniury to Chryſt, which ſaye, that the catholyke churche is an vnknowen churche, ſeing it is that citie, which our ſauiour there ment, and that candell, of whiche he there ſpeaketh. So manye as deuyde them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this open knowen Churche of Chryſte, and refuſe the doctryne thereof, thoughe they be neuer ſo diligent in readyng of ſcrypture, yet ſhall they neuer truely vnderſtande ſcrypture, but runne continually farther and farther into erroure, and ignoraunce, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a man that is once out of his way, the farther, and faſter he goeth furth, the more he loſeth his labour.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter</hi> 1</note> Saint Peter therefore in the fyrſt Chapiter of his ſecond epiſtle, geueth vs a moſt certayne and ſure rule, which if we folowe, we ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173756:19"/> not fayle, ryghtly to vnderſtande ſcripture: his rule is thys. <hi>We haue</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>A ryght ſure worde of prophecie, wherevnto yf ye take hede, as vnto a lighte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhineth in a darke place, you doo wel, vntyl the day dawne, and the daye ſtarre aryſe in your hartes. So that you firſt knowe this, that no prophecie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture hath any priuate interpretation. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture came neuer by the wil of man, but holy men of God ſpake, as they were moued by the holi ghoſt.</hi> Here you ſe, how ſaynt Peter wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth euery man, fyrſt of all, to knowe, that ſcripture muſt be vnderſtanded after the generall meanynge of Chryſtes churche, and not after the priuate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of any ſeuerall man, or companye: And in the thyrde chapiter of the ſame Epyſtle,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3</note> he ſayeth further, that in <hi>S. Paules epiſtles, are manye thinges harde to be vnderſtanded, whych they that are vnlearned, &amp; vnſtable, doo per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerte, as they doo alſo the other ſcriptures, to theyr owne deſtruction: ye therefore beloued (ſeing you be warned afore hand) beware, leaſte ye, with other men, be alſo plucked a waye through the errour of the wicked, and fall from your owne ſtedfaſtneſſe.</hi> Lo here S. Peter telleth the very cauſe, why men myſvnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſcrypture, which is lacke of knoweledge, and
<pb facs="tcp:173756:20"/> lacke of conſtancie, when men ether thorowe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, or thoroughe inconſtancie, ſwerue from the catholyke meanyng, and folowe pryuate interpreta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. Such men, he ſayeth, do peruerte the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to theyr owne deſtruction. Saynte Paule alſo wrytyng to Tymothe, and willing hym to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in the ſtudy of ſcripture,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo</hi> 9</note> geueth him withal this foreſayd rule, ſaying in the very ende of his fyrſt epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: <hi>O Timothie, kepe ſure that, whiche is committed to thy cuſtody, and auoide newe fangled termes, and boſting of ſcience, falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called, which ſcience whyle ſome dyd profeſſe, they haue erred from the fayth.</hi> The thinge, whiche S. Paule ſayth was commytted to Timothies cuſtody, was the truth of the catholyke fayth, which he ſayth, ſome fell frome, by reaſone of new fangled termes, and by reaſon alſo, that they tooke vpon them knowledge, beinge in dede igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte. And in the thyrd chapiter of his ſeconde epiſtle to Timothie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timothei.</hi> 3</note> he farther ſayeth. <hi>Contynue thou in the thinges which thou haſt learned which alſo were commytted vnto the.</hi> S. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneus alſo (a bleſſed martyr, and very nyghe to the tyme of the Apoſtles, a man of greate learning, and no leſſe vertue, and ſuch a one, as by the conſente of all men, had the perfyt knowledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of ſcryptures) in his third boke agaynſt Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentyne the arche heretyke, and in the fowrth chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſame boke ſayeth,<note place="margin">Ireneus in his third boke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, chap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> touchyng the catholyke churche in thys maner. <hi>We muſt not ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173756:20"/> among other, ſeing we may eaſely take it of the church, for as much as the Apoſtels haue fully lefte with it (as in a rych treſury) all truth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſo liſteth, may thence take the drinkes of lyfe, for this is the entre to life. All other are theues, and robbers, wherfore them muſt we auoyd: &amp; that doctryne that the church teacheth, we muſte loue, &amp; with great diligence embrace the tradition of the truth. For what and yf a controuerſy ſhould happen to ryſe vpon neuer ſo ſmal a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought not men in that caſe to haue recourſe to the moſt auncient churches, in which the Apoſtles were conuerſaunt, and ther learne the truth in that controuerſy? ye, what &amp; yf the Apoſtles had lefte behynde them no wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng at all, muſt we then not haue folowed the order of tradition, delyuered by them to ſuch as they committid the churches vnto? to which tradition manye barbarous nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beleuing in Chriſt, do giue credite, with out any other wrytyng, then that which is in their hartes wrytten.</hi> Al this wryteth Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and within a lytle after he ſayeth. <hi>Yf to theſe barbarous nations, any man ſhould preach in their owne language, theſe inuentions of
<pb facs="tcp:173756:21"/> heretikes, by and by they would ſtoppe their eares, and flye as farre as they could fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him and not once here his blaſphemous talke,</hi> thus ſayeth S. Ireneus. Now yf chriſten people at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, would folow this trade, which this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed martir here ſpeaketh of, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> runne into hereſy, but al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold cleue faſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine of the catholike church, &amp; abhorre and deteſt, whatſoeuer any precher wold vtter vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, contrary to the ſame. For whoſoeuer preacheth any doctrine, not agreable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> general receiued doctrine in the open knowen church, he it is, &amp; ſuch as be like to him, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſauiour biddeth vs to beware, ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. of Mathewe. <hi>Beware of falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7</note> 
               <hi>which come to you in ſhepes clothing but inwardly they are rauenynge wolues.</hi> Our ſauior calleth them wolues, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deuoure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules, of ſo many as giue credite vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fardar of them, that they come in lambes ſkins, becauſe they pretend the woord of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with bleare the eyes of poore ſimple men, and make them beleue, that it is as they ſaye, where in dede, whatſoeuer is taught contrary to that, that al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome openly teacheth, and from tyme to tyme hath taught, is falſe, and cannot poſſible be true, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we wold ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt him ſelfe were not true. For he promyſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym ſelfe wilbe for euer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy ghoſt, ſhal for euer gouerne the ſame. Foraſmuch than, as there is no other ſchole on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173756:21"/> earth, for men to learne theyr duety, towardes God, and the world, but the catholyke churche: nor no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctryne, auayleable to eternall lyfe, but that whiche the catholyke churche teacheth, therefore all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people are requyred, to make a ſolempne vow at theyr baptiſme, to beleue the catholyke churche. And he that ſo doeth, is in an aſſured trade of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if in his conuerſation, he folowe the ſame, but contrarywyſe, he that beleueth it not, is in a mooſte certayne eſtate of euerlaſtynge dampnation. Wherefore, that you maye knowe, what the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche dothe in all poyntes beleue, there ſhalbe hereafter particularly, ſet forth vnto you, the ſeuerall matters, requiſit to be beleued, and practiſed of all Chriſten people, that no man, maye haue iuſte cauſe hereafter, to pretende ignoraunce, but all men beynge ſufficiently inſtructed, maye, by folowynge ſuche doctryne, attayne to euerlaſtynge lyfe, whiche ſende vnto vs all, the bleſſed trinitie, the father, the Sonne, and the holye Ghoſte, to whom be all honoure, and glorye, worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſor. Arch. London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:22"/>
            <head>¶ An Homely of Chriſtian loue, or Charitye.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the</hi> pithe, and ſumme, of all thinges, which be conteyned, eyther in the lawe, or in the prophetes, doth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt, in the loue of God, and in the loue of oure neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, as our ſauiour Chriſt dothe plainely teſtifye, in the .xxii. Chapiter of ſainct Mathewe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 22.</note> ſayenge, <hi>One of the Phariſes beynge a doctoure of the lawe, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, did aſke him, and ſay, mayſter, what is the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law? Ieſus, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerynge, ſayd vnto hym. Thou ſhalte loue thy Lorde God, wyth all thy harte, wyth al thy ſoule, and wyth all thy hole mynde, this is</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>the greateſt, and fyrſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. And the ſeconde is lyke vnto it. Thou ſhalte loue thy neyghboure, as thy ſelfe, and of theſe two commaundementes al the lawe dothe hange, and the Prophetes.</hi> And foraſmuche alſo, as we can not loue God well, except we doo loue oure neyghboure, in a due order ne yet loue oure neyghboure well, excepte we doo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173756:22"/> loue God, in that due order, that we oughte to doo, (Sainct Ihon the Euangeliſt ſo teſtifyeng, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarynge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. <hi>and</hi> 4.</note> in the thyrde and fourthe Chapiters of his fyrſt canonicall Epiſtle.) And finally, foraſmuche as he that loueth not after this ſorte, is (by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of the ſayde ſainct Iohn, in the ſayde thyrd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter) iudged to be in death, therefore it is ryghte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediente, and neceſſarye, to haue alwayes this loue, whiche nowe in oure vulgare tongue, and common talke, is ofte named, by the name of Charitie, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry megerly, and coldely practiſed, and ſet fourthe in dede, as it ſhoulde be. And of trouthe, yf we woulde iudge vpryghtly, and well, we ought to ſaye, that of all thinges that be good, to be taught vnto Chriſten people, there is nothynge more neceſſarye to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and daylye called vpon, then charitie: aſwell for that all maner of woorkes of righteouſnes, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in it, as alſo, that the decaye thereof, is the ruyne of the worlde, the banyſhement of vertue, and the cauſe of all vice. And foraſmuche, as almoſt euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh, &amp; frameth to him ſelfe a charity, after his owne appetyte, and howe deteſtable ſo euer his lyfe be, bothe vnto God, and man, yet he perſwadeth with hym ſelfe ſtyll, that he hathe charitye: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſhall heare nowe a true, and playne deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of charitie, not of mens ymagination, but of the very woordes, and example of oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte. In whyche deſcription, euerye man (as it were in a glaſſe) may conſyder hym ſelfe, and ſee plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nely, without errour, whether he be in the true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye or not.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:23"/>
            <p>charitie is to loue God, with all oure harte, withall our life, with al our powers, &amp; with all our ſtrength. <hi>With all our harte,</hi> that is to ſay, that our hartes, mynde, &amp; ſtudie, be ſet to beleue his woorde, to truſte in hym, and to loue hym aboue all other thynges, whyche we doo loue beſt in heauen or in earthe. <hi>Wyth all oure lyfe,</hi> that is to ſaye, that our chief ioye, and delyte, be ſette vpon hym, and his honoure, and oure hole lyfe gyuen vnto the ſeruice of hym, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thynges: wyth hym to lyue, and wyth hym to dye, yea, and to forſake all other thynges, rather then hym. For he that loueth hys father or mother, ſonne, or doughter, houſe or la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, more then me (ſaieth Chriſt) is not worthy to haue me. <hi>Wyth all oure powers,</hi> that is to ſaye, that with our handes, and feete, wyth our eyes, and eares, oure mouthes and tongues, and wyth all other partes &amp; powers, bothe of body and of ſoule, we ſhoulde be gyuen to the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge, and fulfyllynge of hys commaundementes. This is the fyrſte, and the principal parte of charity, but it is not the whole. For charitie, is alſo to loue euery man, good, and euyll, frende, and fooe: And what ſoeuer cauſe be gyuen to the contrarye, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles, to beare good will, and harte vnto euerye man, to vſe oure ſelues wel vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſwel in woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as in all our outeward actes, and dedes. For ſo Chriſt hym ſelfe taught, and ſo alſo he perfourmed in dede. And of this loue that we ought to haue amongeſt oure ſelues, eche to other, he inſtructeth vs thus. (Mathew. v.) <hi>You haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173756:23"/> harde it taught in tymes paſte? Thou ſhalte loue thy frende, and hate thy fooe: but I tell you, loue your enemyes, ſpeake wel of them that diffame you, and doe ſpeake euil of you: doo well to them that hate you, praye for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vexe and perſecute you, that you may be the children of your father, that is in heauen. For he maketh the ſunne to ryſe bothe vpon the euyl, and good, and ſendeth rayne to the iuſte, and to the vniuſt. For if you loue them that loue you, what rewarde ſhal you haue? Doo not the publicans lykewyſe? And yf you ſpeake well onely of them, that be your brethren, and derely beloued frendes, what greate matter is that? doo not the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame alſo?</hi> Theſe be the very woordes of oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Chriſt him ſelfe, touching the loue of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. And foraſmuche as the Phariſeis (wyth theyr mooſt peſtilent traditions, falſe interpretacions, and gloſes) had corrupted, and almooſte clerelye ſtopped vp, this pure well, of Gods lyuely woorde, teaching that this loue, and charitye, pertayned onely to a mans frendes, and that it was ſufficiente for a man to loue them whyche doo loue hym, and to hate hys fooes: therefore Chriſte dyd open this well agayne, purged it, and ſcoured it, by gyuynge vnto hys god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye lawe of Charitie, a true and clere interpretation, which is this: that we ought to loue euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bothe
<pb facs="tcp:173756:24"/> frende, and fooe: addynge thereto, what commodity we ſhal haue thereby, and what in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity by doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge the contrarye. What thynge can we wyſſhe ſo good for vs, as the heauenlye father, to repute, and take vs, for hys chyldren? And this ſhall we be ſure of (ſayeth Chriſt,) yf we loue euery man, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. And yf we doo otherwyſe (ſayeth he,) we be no better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Phariſeis, Publicans, and heathen perſons, and ſhall haue oure rewarde with them: that is, to be excluded from the number of gods elect chyldren, and from hys euerlaſtyng inheritaunce in heauen. Thus of true Charitye, Chriſt taughte, that euery man is bounde to loue God aboue al thinges, and to loue euery man, frende, and fooe.</p>
            <p>And thus lykewyſe, he dyd vſe hym ſelfe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortynge hys aduerſaries, rebukynge the faultes of hys aduerſaryes, and whan he coulde not amende them, yet he prayed for theim. Fyrſte he loued God his father, aboue al thinges, ſo muche, that he ſought not hys owne glorye, and wyll, but the glorye, and wyll of hys father:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> 
               <hi>I ſeke not</hi> (ſayde he. Iohn. v.) <hi>myne owne wyll, but the wyll of hym that ſent me:</hi> Nor he refuſed not to dye, to ſatyſfye hys fathers wyll,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> ſayeng. Math. xxvi. <hi>Yf it may be, let this cuppe of death goo from me, yf not, thy wyll be doone, and not myne.</hi> He loued alſo not onely hys frendes, but alſo hys enemyes, whyche in their hartes dyd beare exceding great hatred, agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt hym, and in theyr tongues ſpake all euyll of him, and in theyr actes, and dedes, purſued hym wyth al their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173756:24"/> myght, and power, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto death. Yet al this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtandynge, he withdrewe not hys fauour from theim, but ſtyll loued them, preached vnto them, of loue rebuked theyr falſe doctryne, theyr wycked ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and dyd good vnto them, pacientlye accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge what ſoeuer they ſpake, or dyd, agaynſte him. When they gaue hym euell woordes, he gaue none euyll agayne, when they dyd ſtryke hym, he dyd not ſmyte agayne: And when he ſuffred deathe, he dyd not ſlea them, nor threaten them, but prayed for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and referred all thynges to hys fathers wyll. And as a ſhepe that is led vnto the ſhambles to be ſlayne,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. Act. 8.</note> and as a lambe that is ſhorne of hys fleſe, dyd make no noyſe, nor reſiſtence: euen ſo wente he vnto hys deathe, wythoute any repugnaunce, or openynge of hys mouthe, to ſaye anye euyll. Thus haue I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto you, what charitye is, aſwell by the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, as by the example of Chriſt hym ſelfe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo, euery man may without erroure, know hym ſelfe, what ſtate and condition he ſtandeth in: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be in charitye, (and ſo the chylde of the father in heauen) or not. For, althoughe almoſte euery man perſwadeth him ſelfe to be in Charity, yet let him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amyne none other man, but hys owne harte, his life, and conuerſation, and he ſhall not be deceyued, but truly decerne, and iudge, whether he be in perfyte charitye, or not. For he that foloweth not hys owne appetite, and wyll, but gyueth hym ſelfe earneſtly to God, to doo all hys wyll, and commaundementes, he maye be ſure, that he loueth God, aboue all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and els ſuerlye he loueth hym not, what ſo euer
<pb facs="tcp:173756:25"/> he pretende:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> As Chryſte ſayd: <hi>If ye loue me, kepe you my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. For he that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth my commaundementes, &amp; dothe kepe them, he it is</hi> (ſayeth Chriſt) <hi>that loueth me.</hi> And agayne he ſayeth: <hi>He that loueth me, wyl kepe my woorde, and my father wyll loue hym, and we wyll bothe come to hym, and dwel wyth hym. And he that loueth me not, wyll not kepe my woordes.</hi> And lykewyſe, he that beareth good harte and mynde, and vſeth well hys tongue, and dedes vnto euery man, frende, and fooe, he maye knowe thereby, that he hathe charity. And then he is ſure alſo, that almyghty God taketh hym for hys dere beloued ſonne, as Saincte Ihon ſayeth, in the thyrde Chapiter of hys fyrſte canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Epiſtle. <hi>Hereby, manifeſtlye are knowen, the chyldren of God, from the children of the deuyll. For who ſo euer dothe not loue hys brother, belongeth not vnto God.</hi> But the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe nature of man, corrupte wyth ſynne, and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Gods woorde, and grace, thinketh it againſt all reaſon, that a man ſhoulde loue hys enemye, and hathe many perſwaſions, whyche induceth hym to the contrarye. Agaynſte all whyche reaſons, we oughte aſwell to ſet the teachynge, as the lyuynge of oure ſauioure Chriſte, who louynge vs (when we were hys enemyes) dothe teache vs to loue our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. He dyd paciently take for vs many reproches,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173756:25"/> ſuffred beatynge, and mooſt cruell deathe. Therfore we be no members of hym, yf we wyll not folowe hym. For as S. Peter ſayeth,<note place="margin">i. Peter. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſte ſuffered for vs, leauynge vs an example, that we ſhould folowe him.</hi> Furthermore we muſt conſider, that to loue oure frendes, is no more but that which the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, adulterers, homicides, and all wycked perſons doo: in ſo muche that Iewes, Turkes, Infidels, and all brute beaſtes, doo loue them that bee theyr fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, of whome they haue theyr lyuynge, or any other benefytes. But to loue our enemies, is the proper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition onely of them, that be the children of God, the diſciples and folowers of Chriſt. Notwithſtanding, mans frowarde and corrupte nature, wayeth ouer depely many times, the offence and diſpleaſure done vnto hym by enemyes, and thynketh it a burden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, to be bounde to loue them, that hate him. But the burden ſhoulde be eaſye ynoughe, yf (on the other ſyde) euery man woulde conſyder, what dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure he hath done to hys enemy agayne, &amp; what pleaſure he hathe receyued of hys enemye. And yf we fynde no egall recompence, neyther in receyuing pleaſures of our enemy, nor in rendryng dyſpleaſure vnto hym agayne: then let vs ponder the diſpleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, whyche we haue done agaynſte almighty God: Howe often, and howe greuouſly, we haue offended hym. Whereof, yf we wyll haue of God forgyuenes, there is none other remedye, but to forgyue the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces done vnto vs, whyche be very ſmall in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of oure offences done agaynſte God. And yf we conſyder that be, whych hath offended vs, deſerueth
<pb facs="tcp:173756:26"/> not to be forgyuen of vs, let vs conſyder againe, that we muche leſſe deſerue to be forgyuen of God. And althoughe our enemy deſerue not to be forgyuen for hys owne ſake, yet we oughte to forgyue hym, for gods loue, conſyderynge howe great, and manyfeſt benefytes we haue receyued of hym, withoute oure deſertes, and that Chriſte hathe deſerued of vs, that for his ſake, we ſhould forgyue them their treſpaſſes, commytted agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>But here may ryſe a neceſſary queſtion, to be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued. If charity requyre to thinke, ſpeake, and doo well vnto euery man, bothe good and euyl, how can magyſtrates execute iuſtyce vpon malefactours, with charitye? Howe can they caſte euyll men into priſon, take away theyr goodes, and ſometime their lyues, accordynge to lawes: yf Charitye wyll not ſuffer them ſo to doo? Herevnto is a playne and brief anſwere, that plages and puniſhementes be not euel of themſelues, yf they be well taken of innocentes: and to an euyll man, they are bothe good and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye: and may be executed accordynge to charitie, and with charitye ſhould be executed. For declaraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, you ſhall vnderſtande, that charity hath two offices, the one contrarye to the other: and yet bothe neceſſarye to be vſed, vpon men of contrarye ſorte, and dyſpoſition. The one office of Charitye, is, to cheryſhe good, and innocent men. Not to oppreſſe them, with falſe accuſations, but to incourage them, wyth rewardes to doo well, &amp; perſeuer in well doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge: defendynge them wyth the ſworde, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr aduerſaryes. And the offyce of Byſhops, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173756:26"/> paſtours, is to laude good men, for wel doynge, that they maye perſeuer therein, and to rebuke and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, by the woorde of God, the offences, and crymes of all euyll diſpoſed perſons.</p>
            <p>The other office is, to rebuke, correcte, &amp; punyſh, vyce, without acceptation of parſons, and this is to be vſed, againſt theim onely, that be euyll men, and malefactours. And it is aſwell the offyce of charitye, to rebuke, punyſhe, and correcte them, that be euyll, as it is to cheryſhe, and rewarde them that be good, and innocent. Sainct Paule ſoo declareth, writing to the Romaynes, and ſayenge, the hyghe powers are ordeyned of GOD,<note place="margin">Roma. 13.</note> not to be dreadefull to them that doo well, but vnto malefactours, to drawe the ſwoorde, to take vengeaunce of hym that commytteth the ſynne. And ſaincte Paule byddeth Tymothye conſtantlye,<note place="margin">i. Timo. 5</note> and vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, to rebuke ſynne, by the woorde of GOD: So that bothe offyces ſhoulde be dylygently execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to impugne the kyngdom of the deuyl: the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher wyth the woorde, and the Gouernoure wyth the ſwoorde. Els they loue neyther God, nor them whome they gouerne, yf for lacke of correction, they wylfully ſuffer God to be offended, and them whom they gouerne to periſhe. For as euery louynge father correcteth his natural ſonne, when he dothe amyſſe, or els he loueth hym not: So all gouernours of Realmes, Countreys, Townes, and houſes, ſhoulde louynglye correcte them, who be offendours vnder theyr gouernaunce.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:27"/>
            <p>And cheryſhe them who doo liue innocently: yf they haue any reſpecte, eyther vnto God, and theyr office, or loue vnto them, of whome they haue gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <p>And ſuche rebukes, and punyſhementes, of them that doo offende, muſte be done in due tyme, leaſt by delaye, the offender fall headlinges into all maner of myſchiefe, and not onely bee euyll theimſelues, but alſo doo hurte vnto many men, drawynge other by theyr euyll example, to ſynne, &amp; outrage, after them. As one theef maye bothe robbe manye men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make many theues, and one ſediciouſe perſon may allure many, and noye a hole towne or countre. And ſuche euil perſons, that be ſo great offenders of god, and the common wealth, charitie requireth to be cut of, from the body of the common weale, leſt they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte other good, and honeſt perſons: like as a good ſurgeon cutteth away a putrifyed, and feſtred mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for the loue he hath to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole body, leaſt it infecte other members, adioynynge to it. Thus it is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto you, what true charitie, or chriſtian loue is, ſo plainely, that no man nede to be deceyued. Whyche loue whoſoeuer kepeth, bothe towardes God (whom he is bounde to loue aboue al thinges) and alſo towardes hys neyghboure, aſwell frende as fooe, it ſhal ſurely kepe hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all offence of God, and iuſte offence of man. Therefore beare wel away this one ſhorte leſſon, that by true chriſtian charitye, God oughte to be loued, aboue all thynges, and all men oughte to be loued, good and euyll, frende, and foo, and to al ſuche we ought (as we may) doo good: thoſe that be good, of loue we ought to encorage, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173756:27"/> cheryſh, bicauſe they be good: And thoſe that be euil, of loue, we ought to procure vnto them theyr correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and dewe punyſhement, that they may therby, either be brought to goodnes, or at the leſt, that god, and the common welthe maye be the leſſe hurte, and offended, hating alwaies, the vyce, or offence, but lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the perſon alwayes, as the creature of God, and as one who by nature is ioyned in kynred vnto vs. And yf we thus directe oure lyfe, by chriſtian loue and Charitye, then Chryſte doothe promyſe, and aſſure vs, that he loueth vs, and that we be the Chyldren of our heauenlye father, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to his fauor, being very members of Chriſt, and that after the ſhorte tyme, of this preſente and mortall lyfe, we ſhall haue with him, eternall lyfe, in his euerlaſtyng kingdome of heauen: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to hym, with the father, and the holy Ghoſt, be al honor and glorye, nowe &amp; euer Amen.</p>
            <byline>E. B.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:28"/>
            <head>¶ An Homely declaryng howe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thynge, the breache of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritye is</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Sauiour Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .v. of Mathew, ſetteth forth an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal doctrine,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> that is, a doctrine, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to al Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and there he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, how great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of lyfe, ought to be in one of vs, ſayinge in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Niſi abundauerit iuſtitia uestra plus quam Scribarum, &amp; Phariſaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, non intrabitis in regnum coelorum.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>Except your rightuouſnes excede the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes of the Scribes, &amp; the Phariſeis, ye cannot entre into the kyngedome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For the ryght vnderſtandynge of whiche wordes, it is to be noted, that rightuouſnes in this texte, doth ſignifye all kynde of vertue, and goodnes, and that by the Scribes, and Phariſeis, Chriſte doth here meane, certayne companies, whiche were amonge the Iewes, and dyd lyue accordynge to the letter of Moyſes lawe, ſo vpryghtly, in the face of the world, that they were commenly taken for parfyt men. Oecumenius,<note place="margin">Oecumenius vpon the fifte of Mathevve.</note> an auncient father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke churche, doth ſo declare the foreſayde wordes. Wherefore, when our ſauioure requireth of vs, that we, in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173756:28"/> ſhoulde paſſe the Scribes and Phariſeis, he meaneth, that we Chriſten folke ſhoulde not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outwardely, ſeme good in the ſight of the worlde, (as did the Scribes, &amp; the Phariſeis,) but inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye alſo in our hartes, ſhoulde be lykewyſe good, in the ſyght of almyghtye God, whiche they were not. And becauſe no faute is more greuouſe, then the breache of Chriſten Loue, and Charitie, therefore immediately after the foreſayde generall ſentence, he inſtructeth vs, afore all other thinges, in our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, touchinge Charitie, ſayinge: <hi>Dictum eſt antiquis, non occides, qui autem occiderit, reas erit iudicii, Ego autem dico nobis, quia omnis qui iraſcitur fratriſuo, reus erit iudicio.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>It was ſayde to them of olde tyme, Thou ſhalte not ſleye whoſoeuer doth ſley, ſhalbe in daunger of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But I ſaye vnto you, that whoſoeuer is angry with his brother, ſhalbe in daunger of iudgement.</hi> Behold, good Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, how perfit a charitie Chriſt requireth in vs. For to vs he maketh the leaſte breache of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as daungerous, as in olde tyme, was the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt breache to the Iewes. The greateſte breache of Charitie, is murdre, and the punyſhmente thereof amongeſt the Iewes, was iudgemente. The leaſte breache of Charitie, is anger, and yet the punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t appoynted for it to vs Chriſtians, by oure ſauyoure hym ſelfe, is lykewyſe iudgement. Howe greate dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of lyfe then, I pray you, muſt be betwene vs, nowe lyuynge vnder the newe lawe, and them that of olde tyme, lyued vnder the olde lawe, that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:173756:29"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of Moyſes, when as, the ſelfe ſame paine that was then preſcrybed vnto them, for the hygheſt degre of vncharitableneſſe, is nowe dewe to vs, for the loweſt degre therof? Howe is it that men flatter themſelues, wyth the pleaſaunte name of Chriſtian libertye, and thinke that, becauſe Chriſt ſaieth in the xi. of Mathew.<note place="margin">Mathe. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Iugum meum ſuaue est, et onus meum leue.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>My yoke is ſwete, and my burden lyghte,</hi> that therefore ſuche ſtreytnes of lyfe, and paynefull trauell is not requyred of vs, as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tyme of the Iewes? True it is in dede, that Chriſten men are not at thys preſente, bounde to be cyrcumcyſed, or to offer vp vnto almyghtye GOD, calues, oxen, ſhepe, and Gotes, or to goo thryſe a yeare to Ieruſalem, or to forbeare ſwynes fleſhe, or to kepe other lyke obſeruations of Moyſes lawe, but as touchynge the tenne commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and all morall Preceptes contained in the olde teſtamente, we Chriſtians are bounde to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of them, &amp; of all other thynges, belongyng to the eſtate of the new teſtamente, and ſo bounde, as that in perfourmance, and fulfyllynge of them, we muſte be muche more perfyt, and more exacte, then euer was the Iewes in obeyng Moyſes lawe. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the yoke of Chriſte called ſwete, nor his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den lyghte, for anye eaſe or remiſſion, that we maye take in oure condition, but for two other conſydera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of whiche the one is, the abundance of grace, gyuen nowe in the tyme of the newe teſtamente, farre excedynge, the meaſure of grace gyuen to the Iewes, folowynge Moyſes lawe: the other is, the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173756:29"/> greatnes of rewarde, promyſed to vs, aboue the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, as wytneſſeth amonge manye other aunciente fathers, Oecumenius alſo,<note place="margin">Oecumenius vpon the fifte of Mathevve.</note> who wrytynge vpon the v. of Mathew, ſayeth after this ſorte. <hi>Quoniam infantia in virilem iam tranſierit etatem, et copioſa hominibus data ſit gratia, et maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma propoſita ſunt premia (neque enim iam poſſeſſio terrae terrenorum, <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> bonorum, aut prolis faecunditas aut longa vita, ſeu victoria contrahoſtes promittitur, ſed regnum caeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, adoptio et victoria contra daemones) me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito magna exiguntur certamina.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as nowe, infancy is paſſed into mans age, and grace is plenteouſlye giuen to men, and mooſte greateſt rewardes are promyſed (for now nether poſſeſſion of earth, and earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye gooddes, nor longe lyfe, nor fecundite of chyldren, nor victory agaynſte oure mortall enemyes, is promiſed, but the kyngdome of heauen, adoptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God, and victory againſt deuels) therefore of good reaſon, great fygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are requyred of vs.</hi> Thus ſayth Oecumenius, concludynge that we chriſten men muſt more pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and manfully, fyght agaynſt oure ghoſtly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, then dyd the Iewes, bycauſe we receaue more grace then they receaued, and haue promiſe made to vs of greater rewardes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had made to them. For theſe two cauſes, we chriſten men muſte thynke the yoke of Chriſte, ſwete, and hys burden eaſye, be the thynges which are requyred of vs, neuer ſo hard to doo, as this is one, that we may not breake cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſo muche as in the loweſt degree that can be, that is in anger: whych woord, in the foreſaid place
<pb facs="tcp:173756:30"/> of Mathew, dothe ſygnify, a violation, or breache of charitye, not vttered or ſhewed forth by any ſygne, but onely conceaued ſecretlye in the harte, and there lyenge hyd, from knowledge of man, but open, and manyfeſt to the eye of almyghty God, who ſeyth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inwarde thoughtes of the harte: thys breache of charitye, thoughe it feme to many a ſmale faute, yet Chriſte declareth it to be a greuouſe faute, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it in the payne, equall with murder, committed of olde tyme by the Iewes. Nowe yf Chriſten men, hauynge conceyued anger in theyr hartes, do not by and by ſuppreſſe the ſame, but proceade to a fardar breache of charitie, that is, to vtter theyr anger by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſigne or token, than is this ther faut greater then the other, and the punyſhemente due for the ſame, greater alſo, accordynge to the woordes of Chriſte, who in the .v.<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> of Mathew ſaieth. <hi>Qui aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dixerit Racha, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us erit concilio,</hi> (that is to ſaye. <hi>He that ſaieth to hys brother Racha, ſhalbe in daunger of counſel.</hi> Where, by Racha, we muſte vnderſtande an oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſygne, vttered by the mouth wyth breache of charitye, and yet ſuche a ſygne as dothe ſygnifye, no expreſſe or particular reproche as, to thou our brother, or to tuſhe at hym. And by councel we muſte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a greater punyſhement, then was iudgement. After this our ſauiour procedeth to the thyrd degree of vncharitableneſſe, which is in woorde to call our neyghboure, by any euyll name, as to call hym foole. Of this thyrde degre, Chriſt ſayeth. <hi>Qui autem dixerit fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri ſuo fatue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
               <hi>reus erit gehennae ignis,</hi> that is to ſaye. <hi>He that calleth his brother foole, ſhalbe in daunger of hell fyre.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:173756:30"/>
            <p>Beholde Chryſtian people, your lyfe in thys leſſon, as in a glaſſe, and you ſhall ſee what daunger you ſtande in. Who is there almooſt emongeſt vs, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vncharitably calleth his neighbour foole, or ſom like euyl name? yea who is there in maner that doth not far paſſe thys degree of vncharitablenes? And yet our ſauiour nameth no mo degrees, partely, bicauſe the paine of this thyrde degree beinge hell fyre, no greater paine coulde be named, for ſuche as ſhoulde paſſe the ſame degree: partly, bycauſe the Chryſtyan man ſhould at the leaſt be ſoo wary, &amp; circumſpecte, in kepyng of brotherly loue, and charitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoughe he dyd, perchaunce ſo farre forgette hymſelfe, as to call his brother foole vncharitably, yet fardar than ſo, he ſhould not ſo much as thinke, throughout his whole lyfe. It is written of one Solon an infidell,<note place="margin">Cicero in his oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſext Roſcius, Amer inus.</note> but yet a very politike man, howe when he made lawes for the gouerment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous citie of Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he in all his lawes, appoynted no punyſhment for a parricide, that is for ſuch a one, as ſhoulde kyll hys father or mother: and when he was demaunded, why he prouided not for that caſe, he aunſwered, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he veryly, thought and beleued, that no one beynge broughte vp in Athens, vnder hys lawes, wolde at anye tyme attempte ſuche an heynous ſynne. Euen ſo may we ſay of our ſauiour, that he ſpeaketh but of thoſe foreſayd three degrees of vncharitablenes, for that it is not lykely, chriſten men, being traded in Chryſtes moſt parfyt religion, woulde at anye tyme procede in the violatyng of charitie, fardar then ſo. But here may be moued a queſtion whether our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:173756:31"/> hath ſo forbydden vs to be angry, to ſaye Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha, or thou foole, one to an other, that in no wiſe any man may ſo doo, but thereby he falleth in daunger of iudgement, of councell, or of hel fyre. For aunſwer to thys queſtion, it is to be noted, that our ſauiour in thys place, forbiddeth vs all kynde of vncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and nothyng els. Foraſmuch then, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third of Mathewe.<note place="margin">Math. 3,</note> S. Ihon Baptiſt calleth the ſcrybes and phariſies, adders brode, and S. Paule calleth the Galathians fooles,<note place="margin">Gala. 2.</note> and men without vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in the ſecond chapiter of his epiſtle wrytten to them:<note place="margin">Luc, 24,</note> yea Chryſt himſelfe in the .xxiiii. of Luke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his dere beloued apoſtles, fooles, and ſloo of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe, and the thyng which they dyd, cannot be iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vncharitable, therefore we muſt ſaye, that when ſuch as haue aucthoritie, vpon a good and Godlye zeale, rebuke treſpaſſours, and offenders, thereby to make them aſhamed of there euyl doynges, and the rather to leaue the ſame, that thys kynd of rebuking is laweful, and in no wiſe ment in the foreſaid talke of Chryſt. But the onely thing that is there forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is the breache of charitie, when one man mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no good at all, to an other, but for the onelye ſatiſfyeng of his vncharitable harte, wyſheth hym hurte in his harte, or vtteryng his ſecret vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mynde, doth thou hym, or tuſhe at hym, or finally ſpeaketh contumelious wordes, expreſly vnto hym, callyng him, foole, idiot or by other lyke opprobrious names: Wherefore to conclude, ſeinge you nowe know what parfytte loue and charitie, our ſauiour Chryſt doth requyre to be in vs, lette all accuſtomed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173756:31"/> rancor and malyce from henceforthe be vtterlye ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed from emongeſt vs, that we dwellyng in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, may dwel in God, and haue here in this lyfe, GOD dwell in vs, and in the worlde to come, dwell in heauen with hym for euer, which graunte vnto vs, the bleſſed trinitie, the father, the ſonne, and the holye Ghoſt, to whome be all honor and glory world without ende. Amen</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſor. Arch. London,</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:32"/>
            <head>¶ An Homelie of the church, what it is, and of the commoditie thereof.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer (good</hi> people) wyll call to hys remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ineſtimable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of almightye God, and his ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable mercye, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs nothing deſeruing the ſame: yf ther be any ſpotte of heuenly grace, in that perſon, he ſhall be aſhamed of hys owne vnthankefulnes, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediens, and be compelled to fal downe in body, and ſoule, before our Lorde, to aſke pardon for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. Of the which goodnes, and mercy of God, you haue a ſufficiente, and mooſt euident declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in theſe godly, and deuoute homelies, that are ſet fourth to you, of the creation, and redemption of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Neuertheleſſe, for your further inſtruction, &amp; ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye comforte in this behalfe, I haue thought good to lette you vnderſtande, an other hye benefyte, geuen to vs, by our ſauioure, and redemer, Ieſus Chryſte, that we, hauynge perfyt knowledge of God, maye euermore prayſe, and magnifye hym, accordynge to our mooſt bounden duetye. And this hye, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye benefyte, is the holye catholyke churche, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che our deare, and dreadfull Sauyour, both before,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173756:32"/> and after his paynefull death, dyd ordeyne, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt, to be for euer to vs, a mooſt louynge, &amp; tender mother, a perpetual preſeruation for our ſoule helth, and a pyllar of truth, in al oure doubtfull daungers. Whiche churche, forſomuche as it hath bene latelye aſſaulted, by ſundry ſectes, and hereſies, and ſo ſore ſhaken, that many (more is the pytie) hath ſeparate them ſelues from the ſame, and wylfully haue runne a ſtraye, beynge ledde, and caried with euery waue, and wynde of newe lernynge, I purpoſe, by Gods grace, to open ſhortely to you, what this churche is,<note place="margin">☜</note> what maner of churche it is, and what commoditie we haue by it.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt, the churche is a conuocation of all people throughout the whole worlde, profeſſynge one fayth of God, and one vſe of all the holy ſacramentes: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che churche, becauſe it is purchaſed, and ſanctified, by the death of oure Sauyoure Ieſus Chriſte, it is mooſt derely beloued to God the father, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in holy Scripture, by moſt hie, and excellent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as <hi>Corpus Chriſti Sponſa Christi, Regnum coelorum. &amp;c.</hi> that is to ſaye: <hi>The bodye miſticall of Chriſte, the ſpouſe of Chriſte, the kyngedome of heauen.</hi> For S. Paule, ſpeakynge of Chryſte, fayth:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>That he hath appoynted ſundry officers, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the holy ones, into the worke of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, to the edifieng of the body of Chriſt.</hi> And kynge Salomon, taught by the holy ghoſt, did forſee the dignitie, and beutye of this holye churche, and ſayde in the name of GOD therebye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vna eſt columba mea, perfecta mea.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>One is my dooue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cantic. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and my perfyt one.</hi> With many other ſuch louyng wordes: as my ſyſter, my ſpouſe &amp;c. And ſaynt Paule byddeth huſbandes to loue there wyues,<note place="margin">Epheſ, 5</note> euen as Chryſt loued the churche, Lykewyſe in the holy Goſpell, our ſauiour Chryſte, doth compare the churche, to ſondry thynges, vnder the name of the kyngdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Math. 20</note> as vnto a king, which made a maryage for his ſonne: ſometymes to tenne Vyrgynes,<note place="margin">Math. 25</note> and many ſuch other: by al which names, and callyngs, we may lerne that the churche is a high and excellent thing, and dearely beloued to almyghty God, who for hys churche ſake, dyd giue hys onely ſonne, to moſt vyle death, and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alſo he hath prepared the kyngdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Nowe, foraſmuche as we rede of an other churche in the holy ſcrypture, which is called <hi>Eccleſia malignanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 25,</note> 
               <hi>The churche of the malingnant &amp; nough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye people.</hi> And yet of late, a great number of ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall perſones, being in verye dede members of thys malygnant churche, haue vſurped to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues the name of the true churche: I intende to gyue you ſufficient inſtruction, to dyſcerne and know the true churche of Chryſt, from all hereticall and ſcyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall congregations. Fyrſt this holye and true churche of Chryſt, is called in our Crede, as it is in dede, the catholyke churche. That is to ſaye, the vniuerſal church, bycauſe it is not lurkyng in anye corner, or any one country, but is in all countryes dyſperſed: neyther is thys catholyke churche, hid
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173756:33"/> from vs, or inuiſible, or vnknowen: but we may eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dyſcerne, and know the ſame. For chriſt doth call it, <hi>Ciuitatem ſupra montem. A citie vpon an hyll.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> And in the Goſpell of Saynt Mathewe alſo, teachynge the order of brotherly reconciliation, he ſaythe. <hi>Yf thy brother treſpaſſe agaynſt the, go and tell him his faute, betwene hym, and the alone, but yf he hear not the,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 18</note> 
               <hi>yet take with the one or two: yf he heare not them, than tell the churche.</hi> Oh Lorde, howe ſhall he tell y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, yf it be not knowen, as the euyll doo contende Lykewyſe Saynt Paule ſpeaking, to the preyſtes, and elders at Epheſus,<note place="margin">Actu, 20.</note> doth warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take hede to them ſelues, and to al the flocke, amonge whome the holy ghoſt (ſayth he) hath placed you to rule the churche of God. Thus playnely the ſcrypture decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that the catholyke churche, is and oughte to be, manyfeſtly knowen, yet leſt you ſhould anye thynge doute of the vnderſtandynge of theſe ſcryptures, heare I beſech you, howe playnely, Saynt Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yne, doth wryte hereof. <hi>Sicut per uerba dei nouimus, ubi ſit pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus paradiſus: ſic per uerba Christi, ubi ſit eccleſia, didicimus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Contra Petil. lib, <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As by the woordes of God we know wher paradyſe was planted, ſo by the woordes of Chryſt, we haue learned, where the churche is.</hi> Marke here (good people) that Saynt Auſten, in thys place, doth write, agaynſt an heretike, being one of the donatyſte ſecte: who denying the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, dyd aſcrybe the fayth, of chryſt, and al
<pb facs="tcp:173756:34"/> ſaluation, to them ſelues onely, being a ſmale parte of Aphrica, lyke as all ſciſmatical congregations, in thys late tyme, haue done: ſome ſaying in germany, here is Chryſt, here is the churche: ſome in. Heluetia, here is chriſt, here is the churche: other in Bohem, here is Chriſt, here is the churche: and we in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, here is chryſt, and here is the churche. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of euery one dyſſentyng, from an other, and that in maters of great weyght, doth declare, that the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte of God, which is the ſpirite of truth, and vnitie, promyſed by Chriſt, to the catholyke churche, dothe not leade nor gouerne ſuche ſectes: neyther oughte they to mayntayne, and ſet furth, falſe doctryne, to the people, vnder the name of the churche, yet ſainte Auſten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place, addyth hys, or rather gods threatnyng,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> ſaying, <hi>Ab isto uniuerſo, ad partem, quamlibet, quis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſeparat hominem, ille diaboli filius, &amp; homicida conuincitur. Whoſoeuer doth ſeperate one man, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys whole, to anye parte: he is proued to be the ſonne of the deuyl, and a very manqueller.</hi> Alas than in what heauy caſe, are thoſe, that haue ſeparate from the catholyke churche, not one man onely, but many thouſandes? ſurelye in heauye and miſerable caſe: vnleſſe, they doo ſpeadelye and in due tyme repent, and doo penance. Moreouer to knowe more manyfeſtly, the catholyke churche, of Chryſt, we ought to conſider what Saynte Paule wryteth, of the foundation thereof. For al ſciſmaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call congregations, though they grounde them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, apparantly, vpon the holye ſcrypture, yet haue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173756:34"/> they there profeſſion, ſeuerally, taken, of ſome noug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hty man, as ſaynt Auguſtyne ſayth <hi>They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led euery one by proper names,</hi>
               <note place="margin">August de. ui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tilitate. cred. Cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whiche they dare not denye.</hi> But the catholyke churche thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh heretykes haue named it papyſticall, yet recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it neuer any other name, but catholyke, and chryſtian: but al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that rede, may ſe how gloriouſly, ſome haue vſyd the name of <hi>Marchion. Ebion, Arrianus, Manicheus. Pelagius. Donatus.</hi> and in our tyme lykewyſe the name of Luther, Zwinglius, Carolſtadius, wyth thouſandes ſuch other: which hereticall faſhion S. Paule doth rebuke, in hys epyſtle to the Corinthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who were euen in lyke caſe: and boſtyng vpon men ſayd, <hi>Ego Pauli, Ego apollo. I hold of Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>and I of Apollo.</hi> But the holy apoſtle rebuketh them ſaying. <hi>As longe as there is amonge you, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying and ſtryfe, or ſectes, are you not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall?</hi> So that euerye chryſten man, and woman, may playnely ſe by the ſcrypture, that theſe hauynge ſuche diuiſion, and ſundrye ſectes amonge them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, are by S. Paule, accompted altogether carnal, and farre vnworthy to vſe the name of the churche, whiche is the onely, and chaſte ſpouſe, of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2</note> But of the catholyke churche, ſaynt Paule ſayth: <hi>Now therfore, ye are not ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, and foreyners: but you are citiſens with the ſaynctes, and of the houſholde of God, and are buylded vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles, &amp; prophetes,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:35"/> Ieſus Chryſt hym ſelfe being the heade cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone.</hi> And further, bycauſe ſaynt Paule thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughe the holy Ghoſt in him, dyd forſee, that all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retykes would callenge to them ſelfes the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Apoſtles, &amp; prophetes, and that they wold with out authoritie or knowlege, wraſte theyr wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, euery one to there owne ſenſe: therefore this holy apoſtle,<note place="margin">Epheſ, 4</note> in the ſame epyſtle, tellyth vs the order whych Chryſt hath apoynted to be obſerued in hys church: for he ſayth, that Chryſt aſcending into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, dyd gyue gyftes to men, and that he made ſome apoſtles, ſome prophetes, ſome Euangelyſtes, ſome ſhepardes, and teachers, declarynge thereby, that in the catholyke churche, there are orders, and offycers, ſome hyer, ſome lower, whom the reſt ought both diligently to heare, and humbly to obey. So dyd the ſame S. Paul,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Timot</hi> 4 <hi>Tit.</hi> 1</note> before hys death, apoint Timothe, to the offyce of a Byſhoppe, and alſo Tite he dyd leaue in Creta, that he ſhoulde ordeyne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes in euery citie, whiche preiſtes, and Byſhoppes ſhould not be dyſdained, or litle regarded (as in this tyme of manye they are) but they ſhoulde (dooyng there duetie) haue double honoure, and faythfully gouerne the church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actuo,</hi> 20 <hi>Tit.</hi> 2</note> as ſaint Paule ſayeth. And wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to Tite, he byddeth him exhort, and rebuke, with al feruentnes of commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng, by theſe places of the holy ſcrypture, you may eaſely ſee, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: that in the catholyke churche, there are and ought to be degres and orders, and that whoſoeuer doth breake, contemne, or deny the ſame, he denieth and forſaketh the verye truth, and ordinaunce of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173756:35"/> Chryſte, and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Nowe further, we oughte to conſider, that as S. Paule dyd ordeyne Timothe, and Tyte, yea and other byſhoppes, and Preiſtes, in his tyme, ſo they by his commaundement, dyd in theyr tyme, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne other, delyueringe alſo to them, the doctryne whiche they haue receaued of Paule, and by conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall diſcurſe of tyme, euerye one hath deliuered the fayth, that they from the Apoſtles haue receaued, and ſo euen from Chryſte, to this preſente daye, one fayth hath euer ſtande ſtedfaſte. Whiche thoughe it hath ſundry tymes bene aſſayde, and ſore pynched, yet euer hath it preuailed at the laſt, and had the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hande, accordynge to Chriſtes promyſe,<note place="margin">Math. 16</note> neyther ought anye man leſſe to credyt the catholike church, becauſe there are in the ſame, dyuers euyll, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſynners. For Chriſt hym ſelfe,<note place="margin">Math 13</note> doth compare the churche to a nette, caſte into the ſea, whiche taketh both good and bad fyſhes, but at the ende, the good ſhalbe reſerued, and the euyll caſt awaye. Was not twelue choſen by Chriſte, yet one of them, he calleth a deuyll? Doth not Chriſte alſo ſaye,<note place="margin">Math 23.</note> that Scribes and Phariſeis, doo ſyt in Moyſes chayre, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, he woulde the people ſhould obey theyr leſſons? Euen ſo, thoughe ſome members of Chriſtes catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, doo not lyue accordynge to theyr vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catyon, yet oughte no man therefore the leſſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde the fayth and doctryne of the ſame churche. Theſe thynges, good people, thoughe they are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente, to declare the holye Churche, what it is,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:36"/> and howe it may be knowen, yet I beſech you moſt diligently, to note, and carye awaye one rule, which ſhall neuer deceaue you, but is a ſure tryall of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke churche, and the fayth thereof. This rule is not myne, but taken out of a learned, auncient, and ryghte godlye father in Chriſtes Churche. He ſayth <hi>There are thre meanes to trye a churche,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincentius Lirenenſis.</note> 
               <hi>or doctryne, the fyrſt is antiquitie, the ſecond, is vniuerſalitie, the thyrde, is vnitie.</hi> By the fyrſt, we are taught, that a true doctrine muſt be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by that it is not lately ſpronge vp, or ryſen, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from Chriſt, and his apoſtles, and hath conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſtyll in the churche. By the ſeconde, we maye vnderſtande, that a true fayth, or doctryne of the churche is that onelye, whiche vnyuerſallye, in all countreys hath ben taught, &amp; beleued. By the thirde we ought to learne, that a true doctryne, or fayth of the church, doth alwayes agre, and is alwayes one. Nowe thoſe three thinges well noted, may inſtruct and teache any Chriſten man, to knowe the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, whiche euer ſynce the Apoſtles tyme, and in all countreys, with one conſent (in al thinges concernyng our fayth) hath ſhewed her ſelf the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſpouſe of Chryſt. Contrary wyſe, falſe doctryne, and hereſye, euer hath doone, and ſhall doo to the worldes ende, <hi>lately ariſe, &amp; lurke in priuat cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, &amp; neuer agre with itſelfe.</hi> Which thyngs I myght eaſelye at large proue, and open to you, by playne and manifeſt demonſtration. But becauſe in the nexte homelie, I intende to ſpeake of the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173756:36"/> of the churche, and alſo of the commoditie, and profite that we haue by the ſame, here I wyll make an ende,<note place="margin">Roma. 12</note> beſechyng all you (good and godly people) to geue your bodyes, and ſoules, an humble and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacryfyce to almyghtye God, prayinge euermore, that we may be altogether lyuelye membres, of oure ſauyoure Ieſus Chryſt, and of his catholyke churche here vpon earth, and after this lyfe, partakers of the ioyfull kyngedome of heauen, through the ſame our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, to whom with the father, and the holy ghoſte, be all honoure and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
            <byline>H. Pendilton ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:37"/>
            <head>¶ An Homely, of the aucthoritie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, declarynge what commoditie and profit we haue thereby.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ykewyſe, as in</hi> the laſte homelye, it was declared to you (good chryſten people) what the churche is, and how it maye be knowen: ſoo nowe ye ſhall learne, the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſame ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke church, and the commoditie, or profyt that enſueth to vs all, beynge members of the ſame churche. Fyrſte, whan oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt, dyd ſend forth the twelue apoſtles to preach, who were, and are, the cheife, and pryncipall pyllers of this catholyke churche, he dyd geue to them great power, and aucthoritie, as ſaynt Mathewe beareth wytnes,<note place="margin">Math. 10</note> ſayinge: <hi>Ieſus dyd call together the twelue diſciples, and gaue to them power ouer vncleane ſpirites, that they ſhoulde caſt them out, and ſhoulde heale all maner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and infirmities.</hi> And ſondrye tymes we do rede in the holy Goſpell, that our Sauiour Chryſte doth ſpeake to his Apoſtles, after this maner. <hi>Qui uos audit, me audit, &amp; qui uos ſpernit, me ſpernit.</hi> That is to ſaye:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173756:37"/> 
               <hi>He that heareth you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mathe. 10.</note> 
               <hi>heareth me and he that diſpiſeth you, doth diſpiſe me.</hi> Meanynge,<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> and wyllynge thereby, that all the worlde ſhoulde know and confeſſe, the aucthoritie of the catholyke church, whiche Chriſt him ſelfe dyd buyld in, and vpon theſe hys holye Apoſtles. And to the ſame purpoſe he ſayd to them, <hi>Iam non dicam uos ſeruos, ſed amicos &amp;c</hi> That is to ſay <hi>Nowe I wyll no more call you ſeruauntes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 15</note> 
               <hi>but frendes: for al thinges that I haue herde of my father, I haue declared to you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 20</note> And agayne he ſayth: <hi>As my father ſente me, euen ſo I ſende you.</hi> By theſe, and many ſuch other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we maye ſee, that our louynge ſauiour, dyd giue greate aucthoritie to his Apoſtles. But nowe it is expediente, and nedefull, to declare, in what ſpecyall poyntes this aucthorytie doth conſyſte, and that the ſame aucthorytie was not onely geuen to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſte, but alſo to theyr ſucceſſours, in the catholyke churche, euer to endure. Whiche auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, thoughe it be greate, and manyfolde, yet theſe are the chefeſt partes thereof, that hereafter doo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe. Fyrſte, almyghtye God, hath geuen power,<note place="margin">The churche hath the true ſence of the ſcripture, and is iudge therof.</note> and aucthoritie, to the catholike churche, to haue the true ſenſe, and vnderſtandynge, of the holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yea, and to approue alſo, or reproue al wryting, as Scripture, or no Scripture. Whiche thynge, good chriſten people, you may well vnderſtande to be mooſt true, yf ye cal to remembraunce, who is the guyde, and gouernour of the churche, that is to wit, the holy Ghoſt: as Chriſte dyd promyſe, ſayinge.
<pb facs="tcp:173756:38"/> 
               <hi>Ego rogabo patrem et alium paracletum dabit vobis, vt maneat vobiſcum ineternum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> that is to ſaye, <hi>I wyll aſke my father, and he wyll giue to you an other comforter, that he maye abyde wyth you for euer.</hi> And after that our Lord and ſauiour had ryſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, he dyd breathe vpon hys Apoſtles, and ſayde <hi>Accipite ſpiritum ſanctum Take you the holy ghoſt</hi> and alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 20.</note> after hys aſcenſion into heauen, accordynge to his merciful promiſe, he did ſende downe the holy Ghoſt vpon his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Act. ii.</note> as ſaincte Luke writeth. Nowe that the holy ghoſte was not gyuen to the Apoſtles onely, but alſo to the catholyke churche, to the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende, it is manyfeſt: foraſmuche as Chryſte dyd promyſe the conforter, <hi>vt maneat vobiſcum inaeternum. That he ſhould abyde</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>wyth you for euer.</hi> Nowe we are mooſte certayne,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14</note> that the Apoſtles of Chriſte dyd ſuffer deathe, for the faythe of Chryſte, and that within fewe yeres, after they thus had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued the holy ghoſte. Neuertheles, Chriſt ſending furthe hys Apoſtles to preache, and baptyze, ſayd to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce ego vobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſum omnibus diebus vſque ad conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mationê ſeculi.</hi> That is, <hi>Behold, I am with you at al tymes, euen to the ende of the worlde.</hi> Wherefore we maye playnly ſee, that the holy ghoſte beynge promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Apoſtles, to abyde for euer, and to the very ende of the world, was promiſed and giuen to them, and to their ſucceſſours in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, where he doth, and ſhall abide for euer. Now foraſmuche, as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſte is the gouernour and ruler of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, we ought there onely, and in no other
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173756:38"/> corner, to ſerche the true vnderſtandynge, and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge of the ſcryptures. And for this cauſe, the aucient fathers (were they neuer ſo godly, and ſo wel learned) yet woulde they neuer preſume vpon theyr owne iudgementes, but euer referred them ſelues, to the vnderſtandyng, and interpretacion of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche before them. Therfore the godly lerned, and ancient father <hi>Ireneus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ireneus li. <hi>3</hi> capi. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> wryting agaynſte ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall hereſyes, ſayeth thus. <hi>Quid enim ſi qui de aliqua modica, questione diſceptatio eſſet, nonne oporteret, in antiquiſſimas recurrere, Eccleſias.</hi> &amp;c. that is to ſaye, <hi>but what and yf there were contencion concerning ſome ſmal que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, were it not neceſſarye to returne to the mooſte auncient churches,</hi> and immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he ſayeth: <hi>Quid autem ſi ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> apostoli quidem ſcripturas reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſſent nobis, nonne oportebat ordinem ſequi traditionis, quam tradide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt hijs, quibus committebant Eccleſias? What</hi> (ſayeth this holye father) <hi>yf the Apoſtles had lefte to vs no ſcripture at all, had it not bene neceſſarye to folowe the order of that tradition, whyche they delyuered to thoſe, to whome they dyd bequethe the churche?</hi> Alas (good people) howe farre are manye in theſe dayes gone from this olde, and auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rule? this bleſſed martir, here exhorteth, or, rather commaundeth, that yf any ſmall dyſcorde, (thoughe it be in a matter of lytle importaunce) doo chaunce, that we woulde not, accordyng to our fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſy, iudge therein, but though we haue no ſcripture for the ſame, yet (ſayeth he) we ought to folowe, kepe,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:39"/> and obſerue the tradition of the aunciente churches. Where as in theſe late dayes, the impudente proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, haue taughte the zely people, that euery man ſhoulde, and may be a iudge of controuerſyes, and that we oughte to obſerue no tradition, nor ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, other than we fynde in the holy ſcrypture. Of ſuche, the ſame holy Ireneus dooeth ſpeake thus, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many other notable leſſons to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Omnes autem hij decidunt a veritate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ireneus li. 4 Cap. 43.</note> 
               <hi>et heritici quidem alienum ignem afferentes ad altare dei, id eſt, alienas doctrinas, a celeſti igne conburen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. &amp;c. All theſe</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>doo fal from the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and the heretykes truely, bryngynge ſtraunge fyre to the aulter of God, that is to ſaye, ſtraunge doctrine, ſhalbe brent with the heuenly fyre.</hi> With ſuche lyke threatnynges in the ſame place, to thoſe that diſobey the authoritie of the churche. Lykewyſe ſainct Auguſtyne ſpeakynge of the baptyſme of chyldren, and howe that ſacrament, can profyte them, ſeynge many die before they know the effecte of the ſame: affyrmeth, that the faythe of thoſe that brynge the chylde to chriſtenynge, ſhall profyte the childe that is broughte: but for his proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de. li. arb. lib. 3. Cap. 23.</note> he bryngeth thys. <hi>Hoc commendat eccleſie ſaluberrima au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas. This thynge the mooſte holſome auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritye of the churche doethe commende.</hi> And euen wyth lyke reuerence, the ſame ſaincte Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne, dooth many tymes ſubmytte all hys iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 7. In proemio Li. 3. De. Tri.</note> and woorkes to the catholyke churche. And fynally to declare hys iudgemente, concernynge the aucthoritye of the catholyke churche. He ſaieth thus.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173756:39"/> 
               <hi>Ego vero Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelio no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crederem niſi me catholicae Eccleſiae commoueret authoritas,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, <hi>Truely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. contra epiſt. Manich. Capi. 3</note> 
               <hi>I would not beleue the Goſpell, onles that the aucthoritye of the catholyke churche dyd moue me thereto.</hi> And we ought here to conſyder, that after the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſauioure Chriſte, for the ſpace of certayne yeares, there was no goſpell at all wrytten: but all thynges, concernynge the faythfull chriſtians, were ruled, and gouerned by the dyſcyples of Chriſt, beyng than, the heades of the church. Afterwarde, we rede that dyuers of the dyſcyples of Chriſte, dyd wryte Goſpelles: as ſainct Bartylmew, Nicodemus, and an other Goſpel was called <hi>Euangelium Nazareorum.</hi> But the authorite of the churche, dyd onely admitte thoſe fower euangeliſtes: which nowe the whole churche dooth retayne. Whyche thing might well ſeme mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous, ſeynge that bothe ſaincte Bartylmew, and Nicodemus, were preſent, and dyd ſee the woorkes of Chriſt, and alſo dyd here hys doctryne, where as ſainct Luke dyd learne hys goſpell of ſaincte Paule, and other, and ſo lykewyſe dyd S. marke but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it dooeth mooſt playnly appere, that the catholike churche onely, hathe this hye aucthorite, to dyſcerne ſcriptures, and that ſcriptures allowed by the church ſhoulde not be refuſed of anye particulare perſons. Nowe therefore, ſeynge that the catholyke churche, bothe hathe delyuered, to vs the ſcripture, and in all ages and tymes, hath bene taken of all Godly lerned men, for the true iudge thereof. I exhort, and beſeche all you (good chriſten people), that in all doutes, opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and controuerſies, ye would reſort to the holy
<pb facs="tcp:173756:40"/> churche, and there learne what the ſame catholyke church hath beleued, and taught, from time to time, concernynge doutes, or controuerſies, and yf wyth lowly and meke hartes ye wyll ſo doo, ſurely the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſte wyll inſtructe you, he wyll comforte you, and he wyl leade you, into al trueth. But yf in ſuche caſe, ye wil fly from the catholike church, &amp; aſke cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of your ſelues, or of any that dooth ſwarue from the ſayd churche, than for ſo muche as the holy ghoſt is not your guyde, you ſhall fall from ignoraunce to errour, and from doutyng, and dyſputyng, to playne hereſy, and ſo from one, to another, to the vtter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,<note place="margin">An other auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriti of the churche.</note> of bothe body and ſoule. Yet beſide this great authoritie of the churche, whereof you haue hearde, there is an other gyuen by God, of mooſte hye excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencye, that is, power to forgyue, and pardon, the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſynner, and to puniſhe, and correcte, the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or frowarde ſynner: which power and auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,<note place="margin">Leuit. 13.</note> as it was fygured in the preeſthood of the olde lawe, as in Iudgynge of leproſe perſons, and in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhynge to death, thoſe that did not obey the prieſt: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo is it giuen by our ſauiour Chriſt in very dede,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> in the goſpel, to his Apoſtles, and to all theyr ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours. For after that our ſauioure hadde ryſen from deathe: he came amonges hys Apoſtles, and brethed vpon them, and ſayde <hi>Accipite ſpiritum ſanctum, quorum dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeritis peccata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> 
               <hi>dimittuntur eis, et quorum retinueritis, retenta ſunt.</hi> (That is,) <hi>take you the holy ghoſt, whoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes you ſhall forgyue, they are forgyuen to them, and whoſe ſynnes you doo retayne,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173756:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> they are retayned.</hi> Whyche aucthorite, by playne woordes gyuen by Chriſt, though ſome hath, or doo, contemne, and ſet at noughte,<note place="margin">Ciril in Iohn Lib. 12. capi. 20.</note> yet ſaincte Cyrill byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them ceaſe to merueyle, that Chriſt ſhould giue, ſuche power, for he ſayeth, <hi>Certe abſurdum non eſt, peccata re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti poſſe ab illis, qui ſpiritum ſanctum in ſeipſis habeant. Surelye,</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>it is no abſurdyte,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>ſynnes are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>holy ghoſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Nowe yf you wyll marke, that not the preeſt onely, but alſo the holy Ghoſt dothe woorke, in remitting, and pardonyng ſynnes, than I truſt you wyll ſee, &amp; graunte, this aucthoritie of Chriſtes catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, which thyng euery chryſten man dothe confeſſe dayly in his crede, ſaying, not onely I beleue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly catholyke churche, the communion of ſaynctes, but addyth alſo, the remyſſion of ſynnes, to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame catholike churche.<note place="margin">i. Timo. 1.</note> Doo not we rede that ſaynt Paule dyd vſe this aucthoritie, whan he did excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate Hymeneus and Alexander? dyd not the holye Byſhoppe ſaynt Ambroſe, vſe this aucthoritie in euery poynt, vpon the emperoure Theodoſius?<note place="margin">Theodorit Lib. 5. hist. Eccle. ca. 18</note> Which holy byſhoppe perceyuynge the emperoure had greuouſlye offended, dyd not ſpare to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate hym: yea and though he offered him ſelfe obedientlye to be receyued, yet was it after longe penaunce, that he was abſolued, this holy byſhoppe dyd vſe the authoritie giuen to him by God, &amp; thys chriſten emperoure, knowing, the ſame, dyd with al humilitie obey. Yf the biſhopes and preiſtes in time paſt, and alſo the layitee, had lerned and practſied
<pb facs="tcp:173756:41"/> there duetyes and vocations, by this example, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the churche of Chryſte ſhoulde not haue come to ſuch great diſordre as we ſee, neyther ſhoulde vyce and wyckednes, ſo frely haue bene vſyd: but bicauſe this mater, is largely and lernedly, ſet fourth in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of penance, I wil ceaſe to ſpeake any more hereof, and nowe it remayneth to declare, what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and profytte we haue by thys catholyke church, our lorde and mayſter chryſte in the goſpell, of ſaincte Iohn,<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> doeth compare hym ſelfe to the vyne tree, and all vs to the braunches: and ſayeth. <hi>Manete in me, et ego in vobis. Abyde you in me,</hi> (that is to ſaye, in the faythe of my churche.) <hi>And I wyll abyde in you.</hi> Oh mercyful Lord, what comfort, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditye is this, for a chriſten man, to haue Chriſte to abyde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym? And farther he ſayeth. <hi>Yf you abide in me, &amp; my wordes abide in you, aſke what you wyl, &amp; it ſhalbe graunted to you.</hi> Here are we ſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if we abyde in chriſtes catholike churche, &amp; embrace the faythe, and doctryne therof, both Chriſt hym ſelfe by grace, wyll abyde in vs, and alſo oure prayers, ſhal euermore be hearde. And wythoute all doute, there is no abiding in Chriſte, vnles we abide in the vnyte of hys catholyke churche. For as ſaynct Cipriane ſayeth:<note place="margin">Ciprianus de ſimpli. prelat.</note> 
               <hi>Non poteſt habere deum patrem qui non nouit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam matrem: He cannot haue God hys father,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>knoweth not the churche to be his mother:</hi> But a child of God, knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche to be his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; lyinge in the boſome thereof, may be ſure that Chriſt the ſpouſe of the churche,<note place="margin">Gene. 7.8.</note> wyll neuer forgette
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173756:41"/> hys nedefull requeſtes. And as no lyuely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was ſaued from death, but ſuche onely as were in the arcke of Noe,<note place="margin">Gen. 7, 8.</note> ſo is there none ſaued from dampnation, but thoſe that are in the vnyte of Chriſtes churche. And therefore, to gyue vs warnynge, the holye doctoure Saincte Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne, ſpeaketh in thys maner mooſte playnlye. <hi>Quisquis ergo ab hac catholica eccleſia fuerit ſeperatus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libet lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter ſe uiuere exiſtimet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">August. epiſt 152.</note> 
               <hi>hoc folo ſcelere quod a Christi Vnitate diſiunctus eſt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habebit uitam, ſedir a dei manet ſuper cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> That is in englyſh, <hi>Whoſoeuer therfore ſhal be ſeperatid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this catholike church, although he think himſelf to liue neuer ſo worthely, yet for this onelye crime</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>he is ſeparated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitie of Chriſt, he ſhal not haue life, but</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>wrath of god abideth, vpon hym.</hi> But what nede is it, to allege ſaincte Auguſtine, or any other auncient father herein, ſeing almyghty God by hys prophet Eſay, hath ſet furthe to vs a lytle picture of hys churche,<note place="margin">Eſai. 5.</note> vnder the name of a vyneyarde, and the houſe of Iſraell? There maye we ſee, that thynge that we by experience doo knowe. For almyghty God, in that parable decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by hys Prophete, howe muche he had doone for the houſe of Iſraell, a fygure of Chriſtes churche, in that he had planted them in a batſome, and frutefull countrey, and had gyuen to them good gouernours, and orders, wherein they myghte haue lyued, and pleaſed hym, but foraſmuche as they dyd wylfullye breake the lawes of God, &amp; hys ordinance, he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them ſaying: <hi>Auferam ſepem eius, et erit in direptionem. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:173756:42"/> 
               <hi>I wyll</hi> (ſayeth oure Lorde) <hi>take awaye the hedge of my vyneyarde, that it may peryſhe.</hi> Euen ſo hathe our ſauioure Chriſte dealed wyth vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of his churche. For where as by his preciouſe deathe and paſſion, he dyd purchaſe vs, and lefte vs in the cuſtodye of his catholyke church, as is before ſayde, leauynge alſo to vs, lawes to obſerue, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, wherewith we ſhould be preſerued. And we naughty people, haue dyſpyſed al his mooſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and holſome decrees, and ordinances, he hathe of his iuſtyce, and accordynge to hys promyſe, euen in oure tyme puniſhed vs: and hath ſuffred the wicked, to plucke downe the pale or hedge of his vineyarde: I meane all good order, as well in the churche, as in the common wealthe, and that for the ſpace of many yeares paſte. Nowe here chriſten people, thoughe you doo not conſyder the plage of ſundrye ſynnes, that hathe in this late ſcyſme, poſſeſſed manye mens ſoules, yet doo not dyſſemble, nor forgette the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye, that we all haue ſuffered outewardelye, ſynce we were ſeparate from the churche of Chriſte: alas, what Chriſten bloude wythin this Realme, euen by oure owne countreimen, hath bene ſhed? Oh Lord, how many poore wydowes without comforte haue bene lefte? Howe many fatherleſſe children without ſoccoure? I leaue here to ſpeake, of the vnſhameles breakynge of the deade mennes teſtamentes, and theyr mooſte godly intentes, &amp; ordinances: Abbais, are poulled downe: Collegis, and Chantrees are ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: churches are robbed, and poore Chriſt, (that is to ſaye,) the hungry, and nedefull people, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſhe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173756:42"/> and crye oute therefore. All theſe ſurely, wyth many mo, haue come vpon vs, bicauſe we haue bene oute of the houſe of God. Wherefore, in the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, let vs all togyther lament, and be ſory for oure goynge aſtraye, let vs come, and fal downe before God oure father, and confeſſe oure tranſgreſſion, and humblye deſyre,<note place="margin">Luce. 15.</note> that we maye be receyued into hys houſe, whyche is the churche, thoughe we ſhoulde all the dayes of oure lyues, be but hyrelynges. <hi>Quia melior eſt dies vnus in atrijs tuis ſuper milia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 83.</note> 
               <hi>One daye</hi> (Oh Lorde) <hi>is better ſpente in thy houſe than a thouſande otherwyſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fynallye yf we contynew obedyente chyldren, in the boſome of our mother, the holye churche: we ſhall be fedde wyth lyuely faythe, oute of whyche wyll ſprynge in vs, muche holyneſſe of lyfe, and quietnes of conſcience: and yf at any tyme throughe our frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, we happen to fall, we haue readye, to rayſe vs vp agayne, the holye Sacramentes: throughe the comfortable helpe whereof, we be made ſtronge: and ſo daye by daye more able to procede in al kynde of vertue: and thus hauynge vpon earthe oure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the holye churche, whiche is the ſpouſe of Ieſus Chriſte the Sonne of God, we maye be bolde to call vpon GOD our father: and be aſſured, that he wyll heare vs, as hys dearebeloued chyldren, and gyue vs the inheritaunce of heauen, whyche is prepared for vs, through our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e wyth the father, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, be honour, prayſe and glory, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <byline>H. Pendilton ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:43"/>
            <head>¶ An Homelye of the Primacy, or ſupreame power, of the higheſt gouernor of the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Churche.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in euery natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> and polytyke body, ſo in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, (which is a miſticall body) ſuperioritie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority, muſt nedes be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, or ells it cannot endure. And for thys cauſe ſpeciallye, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chryſte, when he was here conuerſaunte, on the Earth, dyd, hymſelfe, appoynte his Apoſtles, &amp; Diſciples, and there ſucceſſours, to haue the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyght, cure, and high gouernement of his church, to the worldes ende. And to the intente, that no man ſhould contempne theyr aucthoritie, he doth ſaye in the thyrtenth of Saynt Ihon, <hi>Amen, Amen, Dico vobis, qui accipit ſi quem miſero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 13</note> 
               <hi>me accipit. Qui autem me accipit, accipit eum qui me miſit</hi> That is to ſay: <hi>Veryly Veryly, I ſaye vnto you, who that receyueth him whome I ſende, receyueth me And he that receiueth me, receyueth hym that ſent me.</hi> And in the tenth of Luke he ſayth, <hi>Qui uos audit me audit, &amp; qui uos ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, me ſpernit. Qui autem me ſpernit, ſpernit eum qui miſit me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luce. 10.</note>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:173756:43"/> That is to ſaye: <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me, and he that diſpiſeth you diſpiſeth me, and he that diſpiſeth me, diſpiſeth hym that ſent me.</hi> Of the Apoſtles alſo and theyr ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and of theyr charge ouer Chriſtes flocke, doth Saynt Paule ſpeake, in the fourthe chapiter to the Epheſyans, ſaying.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ipſe dedit quoſdam quidem Apostolos, quoſdam autem Prophetas, alios uero Euangelistas, alios autem pastores, et doctores, ad conſummationem ſanctorum, in opus ministerii, in edificationem Corporis Christi, donec oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curramus omnes in unitatem fidei, &amp; agnitionis filii dei, in uirum perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, in menſuram etatis plenitudinis Christi, ut iam non ſimus paruuli fluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuantes, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> circuferamur omniuento doctrine, in nequitia hominum, in aſtutia ad circumuentionem erroris.</hi> That is to ſaye:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He (meanyng Chryſte) hath giuen or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome, Prophets ſome Euangeliſtes, ſome paſtores, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, to the perfytynge, or conſummating, of the holyons, to doo the worke of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, to edyfye the body of Chryſt, vntyll we all come together, in one vnitie of fayth, and knowledge of the ſonne of God, vnto the eſtate of a perfecte man, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſure of the age of the fulnes of Chryſt, that from henceforth, we ſhould not be as babes, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryng, neyther ſhould we be caryed aboute with euery blaſte of doctryne, in the wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of men, in the wylynes of them, who go
<pb facs="tcp:173756:44"/> aboute to deceyue vs</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This place of Saynt Paule moſt playnelye ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before our eyes, the authoritie, and gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which our ſauiour hath appoynted, to contynue to the ende of the worlde, in his churche, and howe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, Prophetes, Euangeliſtes, Preachers, and teachers, are giuen of Chryſt, to his people, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne them. And therewith al Saynt Paule, in the ſayde place, ſheweth to what ende, ſuche gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and authoritie is inſtituted, it is to wytte, for the ſpiritual edifieng of the hole body, in the fayth, &amp; for the defenſe of the hole bodye, from the poyſon of hereſye. And in dede no one thing can ſo muche ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe hereſye, as yf the Authoritie, and gouernment Eccleſiaſticall, be accordingly therevnto eſtemed, &amp; obeyed, as witneſſeth Saynte Ciprian, the bleſſed Martyr, in hys fyrſt boke, and third Epyſtle ſaieng. <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliunde hereſes obortae ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ciprian. Lib. i. epistle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>aut nata ſunt ſciſmata, <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> inde, quod ſacer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doti dei non obtemperatur. Nec unus in eccleſia ad tempus ſacerdos, &amp; ad tempus iudex, uice Christi cogitatur, cui ſi ſecundum magisteria diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, obtemperaret fraternitas uniuerſa, nemo aduerſus ſacerdotum colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia quic<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> moueret.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>Neyther other where, or by other meanes, are hereſyes ſprong vp, and ſciſmes ryſen, than hereof, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> obedience is not gyuen to the preiſt of God. Nor one is conſidered, or thought, to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, for the tyme, the preiſt, and for the time the iudge, in Chriſtes ſtede, vntowhich one, yf the hole fraternitie dyd (according to the heauenly commaundements) obeye, no
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173756:44"/> man woulde ſtirre, or moue anye thinge againſt the Colleges or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies of preiſtes.</hi> Hereby you may perceyue, that ſaynt Cypryans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, or iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is, that the gouernment Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, and eſpecially of one, to be taken, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as Chriſtes vicar, is the beſt meane, to let and ſuppreſſe hereſies, and that ſuch one gouernor, is to be obeyed, of all chryſten people, which thinge maye be proued very playnely, and euidently, by the holy ſcryptures themſelues. For the ſcryptures doo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that our ſauiour appoynted S. Peter, to thys high rowme, and charge, ouer his hole flocke, and no one of the Apoſtles els. In the .xxi.<note place="margin">Ioan. 21</note> of S. Iohn it is wrytten, howe, our ſauiour, after his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, appearing at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea of Tiberias, to certen of his Apoſtles, amongeſt whome was Peter, dyd fyrſte take breade, and fyſhe, and gaue vnto them, And when they had refreſſhed them ſelues, he ſayde vnto Peter. <hi>Simon Ioannis diligis me plus hiis? Dicit ei, Etiam domine tis ſcis, quia amo te. Dicit ei. Paſce agnos meos. Dicit ei iterum, Simon Ioannis diligis me? Ait illi. Etiam domine tu ſcis quia amo te Dicit ei Paſce agnos meos Dicit ei tertio. Simon Ioannis amas me? Contristatus eſt Petrus, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a dixit ei tertio, amas me? &amp; dixit ei. Domine tu omnia nosti, tu ſcis, quia amo te. Dicitei, Paſce oues meas.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>Symon the ſonne of Ioannes, doeſte thou loue me more then theſe doo? He anſwered vnto him: Yea Lorde, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. He ſayde vnto him: Fede my lambes. Then he ſpake to him agayne, and ſayde: Symon the ſonne of Ioannes, doeſte thou loue me?
<pb facs="tcp:173756:45"/> He aunſwered: yea Lorde, thou knoweſte that I loue thee. He ſayd vnto hym againe: Feede my lambes. Then ſpake he vnto him the third tyme, and ſayde: Symon the ſonne of Ioannes, doeſt thou loue me? Peter was ſorie, becauſe Chriſt ſayde vnto him now the thyrde time, doeſt thou loue me, and he aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſayde: Lorde thou knoweſte all thinges, thou knoweſt that I loue thee. He ſayde vnto him feede my ſhepe.</hi> This proceſſe of Scripture, hath in it, many circumſtaunces to be noted. The fyrſt is, that (other Apoſtles beynge than preſent, and amongeſt them, euen he of whom Chriſt did euer make very much of, that is to ſay, S. Iohn) yet our Sauiour Chriſt, dyd dyrecte his ſpeach, and talke, but to Peter onelye, ſignifienge the matter, wherof he dyd ſpeake, to appertayne to Peter chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and pryncipallye, and not in ſo ſpeciall a ſorte, to anye one of the apoſtles els. Another, and ſeconde circumſtaunce to be here conſidered, is that oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure, dyd aſke Peter mooſt earneſtly, whether he loued him, more than did the other apoſtles. And the thyrde cyrcumſtaunce is, in that Chriſte dyd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte both his lambes, and his ſhepe, vnto hym. Theſe cyrcumſtaunces (I ſaye) and other ſuche like, well conſidered, doo conuince, and clearelye proue, that the hyghe charge, ouer all the churche militant, was eſpecially committed, to Peter.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:173756:45"/>
            <p>And to this purpoſe, maketh, and ſerueth, an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther talke, of our ſauiour, vnto S. Peter, written in the .xvi. of Mathew, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> texte is in this maner. <hi>Venit autem Ieſus in partes, Caeſareae Philippi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; interrogabat diſcipulos ſuos dicens. Quem dicunt homines eſſe filium hominis? At illi dixeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Alij Ioannem Baptiſtam, alij autem Heliam, alij uero Hieremiam, aut unum ex prophetis. Dicit illis Ieſus, uos autem quem me eſſe dicitis? Reſpondens Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Petrus dixit. Tu es Chrictus filius Dei uiui. Reſpondens autem Ieſus dixit ei. Beatus es Simon Bariona, quia caro &amp; ſanguis non reuelauit tibi, ſed pater meus qui in coelis eſt. Et ego dico tibi, quia tu es Petrus, &amp; ſuper hanc petram aedificabo Eccleſiam meam, &amp; portae inferi non praeualebunt aduerſus eam. Et tibi dabo claues regni coelorum. Et quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ligaueris ſuper terram, erit ligatum &amp; in coelis, &amp; quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolueris ſuper terram erit ſolutum &amp; in coelis.</hi> That is to ſaye: <hi>Ieſus came into the coaſtes of Ceſarea Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi, and he aſked his diſciples, ſayinge: Whom doo men ſay the ſonne of man to be? And they aunſwered, ſome Iohn Baptiſte, ſome Helias, ſome Hieremias, or one of the prophetes. Ieſus ſayd vnto them. But who ſaye you that I am? Then Simon Peter made aunſwer, and ſayde: Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuinge God. And Ieſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſayd: Bleſſed art thou Simon, the ſonne of Ioanna, for fleſhe and bloude hath not this reueiled, and opened vnto the, but my father whiche is in heauen. And I ſaye vnto the, that thou arte Peter, or a rock, and on this rocke I wyll buylde my church,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:46"/> &amp; hell gates ſhal not preuayle agaynſt it. And I wyl gyue vnto thee, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; whatſoeuer thou ſhalte bynde vpon earth, ſhalbe bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; whatſoeuer thou ſhalt loſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, ſhal be looſed alſo in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Theſe wordes of Chriſt were ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longe before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte gaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Peter, to feede hys flocke, and that thynge, whyche is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed in the other woordes, is here promyſed, in theſe woordes. In the other woordes oure ſauioure dothe preſently, put him in authoritie, ſaying. <hi>Feede my Lambes, feede my ſhepe.</hi> In theſe woordes, he dooeth but promyſe the ſayde authority vnto him, ſayenge. <hi>Vnto thee wyll I gyue the keyes of the kyngedome of heauen, and what ſo euer thou looſeſt, or byndeſt in earth, ſhal be looſed or bounde in heauen.</hi> The lyke of this, did our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour neuer ſpeake to any one of the Apoſtles els, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally, but onely generally. For generally to Peter, and to the reſte, being al together, (ſauing Thomas, who was abſent,) Chriſt ſayed the woordes whyche are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the .xx.<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> of Iohn, it is to witte, <hi>Receyue you the holy ghoſte, whoſe ſynnes ye remyt, they are remytted, and whoſe ſynnes ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> 
               <hi>they are retained.</hi> And in the .xviii. of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Chriſt ſayeth vnto the twelue. <hi>What ſo euer thynges you ſhal bynde vpon the earthe, ſhal be bounde alſo in heauen, &amp; whatſoeuer you ſhal loſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, ſhalbe loſed alſo in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:173756:46"/> Yf our ſauiour Chriſt had not intended to gyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peter a ſpeciall authoritie, aboue the reſt, what nede was there to ſpeake this, ſeuerallye, vnto Peter, ſeing he had ſpoken it generally to them all before? And what thing ment he els, when, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of al the twelue, he promiſed to gyue vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the keyes of the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſauing a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall priuilige, or prerogatyue to Peter? Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our through his heauenly wyſedome, perceyuynge, that it is moſt neceſſarye, one to be ouer a hole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, ſpecially being a multytude congregated of ſo infinite a number of people, and of ſo ſondry nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as is the catholyke churche, did appoynte S. Peter, to that offyce, and Peter hauinge receyued ſuch charge at Chriſtes handes, did incontinentely practyſe and exerciſe the ſame: and all the reſt of the Apoſtles dyd gyue place vnto him.<note place="margin">Act. i.</note> And therefore in the firſt of the Actes it is written, howe that after Chriſtes aſcenſion, incontinently S. Peter roſe vp in the myddeſt of the faythfull, and moued them to goo to the election of one, that ſhould ſuccede in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das rowme, which offyce he vndoubtedly woulde not haue taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but that our ſauiour Chriſt had Authoriſed him in ſuch ſorte, as is before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. In the .ii.<note place="margin">Actes. 2.</note> of the Actes it is wrytten howe that in the preſence of all the Apoſtles, S. Peter tooke vpon him to ſpeake in all their names to the people on whitſonday in the morning, ſtreighte after that they had receyued the holye Ghoſte, in the likenes of cloue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tunges. In the third of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes, it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Actes. 3.</note> how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> S. Peter healed a lame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was lame from
<pb facs="tcp:173756:47"/> his mothers wombe, and that when the people won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at ſo ſtraunge a myracle, the ſayd Peter made an oration vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.5.6.</note>In the fourthe of the Actes, and in the fyfte, and ſyxt there is the lyke, and in manye other places of the ſame booke. All whyche places of ſcrypture oughte to perſwade euery godlye harte, to thynke that oure ſauiour dyd gyue vnto ſainct Peter, that authoritie, aboue all the reſte of the Apoſtles, vpon hys hoole churche, for an vnytye, and good order, to be kepte in the ſame. And yet for your better contentation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you ſhal here the authorities of the Aunciente fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>Origene,<note place="margin">Origenes</note> a greeke wryter, whyche was wythin two hundred yeares after Chriſte, in hys expoſition, made vpon the .vi. Chapiter of S. Paules Epiſtle, to the Romaynes, wryteth thus. <hi>Petro cum ſumma rerum de paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendis ouibus traderetur, et ſuper ipſum tan<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> ſuper terram fundaretur ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, nullius confeſſio uirtutis alterius, niſi charitatis exigitur.</hi> (That is to ſaye,) <hi>when the hygheſt authoritie, or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of chriſtes ſheepe, was committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peter, and the churche was builded vpon hym, as vpon a ſure grounde, there was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred, or exacted of hym, the profeſſion of none other vertue ſaue onely of charitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ciprianus.</note>The bleſſed martyr, ſainct Cipriane, in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, affyrmeth the ſame, and amongeſt other, in hys Epiſtle written. <hi>Ad Iubatanum.</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Manifeſtum eſt, vbi, et per quos, remiſſio peccatorum dari poſſit: Nam dominus primum Petro, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quem edificauit eccleſia ſuam, et vnde vnitatis originem inſtituit, et
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173756:47"/> oſtendit, potestatem istam dedit:</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt where, and by whome, remiſſion of ſynnes maye be gyuen, for oure Lorde fyrſte vnto Peter (vpon whome he buylded hys churche, and from whome he dyd ordeyne, and ſhewe, the begynnynge of the vnitye, to procede) dyd gyue that power, or authoritie.</hi> And in the ſame Epiſtle, (within a whyle after) he ſayeth. <hi>Eccleſiam, que vna eſt, fundauit ſuper vnum,</hi> that is to ſaye, <hi>He dyd founde his churche, which is but one, vpon one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sainct Baſyll,<note place="margin">Baſilius.</note> in hys booke againſt <hi>Tauonius</hi> writeth thus <hi>Per hanc vocem intelligimus Ionae filium, qui fuit ex Bethſaida, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreae fratrem, qui ex piſcatore, in Apoſtolatus ministerium vocatus est Qui quoniam fide praestabat, eccleſiae in ſe aedificationem ſuſcepit.</hi> That is to ſaye, <hi>by this voice, we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſonne of Ionas, which was of Bethſaida, the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Andrewe, which ſonne of Ionas was called from a fyſher, to the miniſterye of the Apoſtleſhyp and bycauſe he excelled in faith, he had the churche buylded vpon hym.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sainct Ambroſe in hys fourthe ſermon ſayeth.<note place="margin">Ambroſius</note> 
               <hi>Petrus deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pro ſoliditate deuotionis, eccleſiarum petra dicitur, ſicut ait dominus. Tu es petrus, et ſuper hanc petram aedificabo eccleſiam meam. Petra enim dicitur, quod primus in nationibus fidei fundamenta poſuerit, et tanquam ſaxum immobile, totius operis Christiani compagem molem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineat</hi> (That is to ſaye,) <hi>Fynally, or for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Peter, for the ſoundenes, or ſubſtancial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:173756:48"/> of his deuotion, is called the rocke of the churches, as oure Lorde ſayeth Thou arte Peter, or of a rocke, and vpon this rocke wil I buylde my churche. In dede he is called a rocke, bicauſe he was the fyrſte that did laye the foundation of faythe amongeſt the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, &amp; as a ſtone, or a rocke, that cannot be moued, he doeth conteine or kepe, the frame, and weight of the hole chriſten woorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtinus</note>S. Auguſtine hath the lyke in his ſyxe and twenty ſermon, <hi>de ſanctis,</hi> and in his .xvi. ſermon <hi>de tempore,</hi> but mooſt notably in hys .124. ſermon <hi>de tempore,</hi> where he maketh a large proceſſe of ſainct Peter, and emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt other thinges, ſpeakyng of Peters denial of his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, he wryteth thus of hym. <hi>Totius corporis morbum in ipſo capite curat eccleſie, et in ipſo vertice componit membrorum omnium ſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem,</hi> That is to ſaye, <hi>He</hi> (meanyng Chriſt) <hi>doeth cure in the very heade of the churche</hi> (meaning Peter) <hi>the dyſeaſe, of the hole body, and in the very crowne, or toppe of the head, he frameth the healthe of all the members.</hi> Here ommyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge infynite, other authorities of the aunciente fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, touchynge the primacye, or hygheſt authoritie eccleſiaſticall, to haue bene gyuen vnto ſainct Peter of our ſauiour Chriſt hym ſelfe, I exhorte you in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, partely of theſe teſtimonyes, ſome wherof are taken out of the very ſcripture, ſomme out of the aunciente and famous doctours of the churche, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173756:48"/> partly, and mooſte eſpecially, in conſyderation of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the hole catholike church herein, nothing to doute in this matter, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy Apoſtle S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was Chriſtes vicar on earthe, and had hygher, and more authoritye generall, then anye one of the Apoſtles els, and that the ſpeciall purpoſe, why that Chriſt woulde haue ſuche authoritie to be in one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was, &amp; is, for the preſeruation of vnitie in his church, whyche churche, is but one, and thus muche for thys tyme, ſhall nowe ſuffice you. In the nexte homely, you ſhall heare fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this matter.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris. et Archidiaconi London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:49"/>
            <head>¶ An other Homelye of the Pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macye.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is wrytten in</hi> the .viii. chapiter of the actes, how Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus, dyd offer vnto Saynte Petermony, to giue him power, that on whome ſoeuer he ſhoulde laye hys handes, the ſame parſon might ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, receiue the holy Ghoſt. But being for this his moſt wicked requeſt, greuouſly reproued, and fearyng withal, to conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, in thoſe parties, that is to ſay, in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, ſo nighe thappoſtles, he, the ſayde Symon Magus fled to Rome, and there by his enchaunte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,<note place="margin">Iuſtinus Martir.</note> dyd greately delude the people, as Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus the Martyr, a very auncient writer, in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde Apologie, directed, or ſent, to the Emperoure Antonius, doth playnelye teſtifie: Ireneus<note place="margin">Ireneus.</note> alſo in his firſt boke <hi>Contra hereſes.</hi> doth recorde the ſame. And the ſaid Simon Magus, dyd ſo delude &amp; blind the people, that they dyd eſteme him for a God, and dyd ſet vp his image, in the Citye, with this inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Simoni deo ſancto</hi> That is to ſay <hi>To Simon the holye God.</hi> But it was not longe, after thoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173756:49"/> prankes, played by Simon Magus, thus ſeducyng the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ther, but God ſent his great Apoſtle ſaynct Peter thyther, (that is to ſaye, to Rome) who bothe did confounde the ſayde Simon Magus, and dyd alſo conuert a great number of the people there, vnto the faythe of Chryſte, as is at large, ſet fourthe in the .xiiii. chapiter, and ſeconde booke of Euſebius,<note place="margin">Hiſtoria Eccleſiastica Euſebij</note> Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorye. Nowe this Apoſtle ſayncte Peter, by the wyll, and prouidence of God, beynge brought to Rome, dyd there continue, byſhop of that Sea .xxv. yeares, and there alſo dyd ſuffer a glorious martyrdome, in the laſt yeare of the reygne of cruell Nero Themperoure, whyche thynges Sayncte Hierom in the verye begynnynge of hys woorke,<note place="margin">Hieronimus</note> 
               <hi>De Eccleſiasticis ſcriptoribus</hi> dothe wytnes in this maner. <hi>Simon Peter, the ſonne of Ioannes, of the prouince of Galile, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne of Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaida, the brother of Andrewe the Apoſtle, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his byſhopricke in Antioche and after his preaching in Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus, Galatia, Cappadotia, Aſia, and Bithinia, to the Iewes whiche were dyſperſed abrode in ſondrye contries, came to Rome, to ouer throwe Simon Magus, and there dyd kepe his ſea, fyue and twenty yeres, vntyl the laſt yere, (it is to wyt the .xiiij. yere) of the reigne of Nero, by whome he was crucifyed, and ſo crowned with a crowne of martyrdome, his heade beynge turned downe to the grounde,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:50"/> and his feete vpwarde, bycauſe he ſayde, or accompted hym ſelfe vnworthy, to be crucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in ſuche forme, and maner, as hys may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſius</note>S. Ambroſe in hys .lxx. ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeakyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of ſainct Peter, and ſaint Paule, at Rome, ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus. <hi>I thinke it not done without a great cauſe, that in one day, in one place, and vnder on perſecutoure, they bothe dyd ſuffer. In one daye, for that they ſhould come to Chriſt together. In one place, that neither of theym bothe, ſhoulde be deſtitute of Rome, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one perſecutoure, that lyke cruelty ſhould ſlaye them bothe. The day was for their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, the place for theyr glory, the perſecutour, for theyr vertue. And in what place I praye you dyd they ſuffer martyrdome? Euen in Rome, whiche is the heade, and chyefe citye, of the worlde, to the intente that where the head of ſuperſtition was, there ſhould reſt the heade of holynes, and where the prynces of the heathen did dwel, there the princes of the churche ſhoulde lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſayeth ſaint Ambroſe, wherevnto agreeth <hi>Egeſippus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Egeſippus</note> an auncyent wryter, in his thyrde booke, of the diſtruction of Hieruſalem, and lykewyſe, <hi>Dioniſius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dioniſius</note> the byſhop of Corinthe,<note place="margin">Corinth.</note> and Caius alſo whiche lyued
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173756:50"/> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of <hi>zepherinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sepherinus</note> the Byſhop of Rome, as more at large appeareth, in the .xxv. Chapiter, of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde ſeconde booke of Euſebius,<note place="margin">Euſebius</note> Eccleſiaſticall hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory. Nowe that we haue in the homely, goyng next before this, declared, that our ſauioure dyd appoynt Saincte Peter to a greater, and hygher offyce, then he dyd any other of hys Apoſtles, and haue in this homely intreated, of the abode of ſaincte Peter, and martyrdome at Rome, we wyll conſequentlye proue, that the Byſhoppes of Rome, haue alwayes, in the catholyke churche, bene eſtemed, iudged, and taken, for ſainct Peters ſucceſſours, euen in that hys ſpecial, and hygheſt offyce, and that to hym, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the wyll of God, doeth appertayne the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtes hole flocke, on earthe. And fyrſte I wyll begynne wyth the aunciente Authour, <hi>Ireneus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ireneus 3. Lib. aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hereſes.</note> who in the thyrde Chapiter of hys thyrde booke, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hereſyes, doeth ſay, that the church of Rome, is the greateſt, the eldeſt, and the beſt knowen, of all churches, and that it was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, by the mooſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Apoſtles, Peter, and Paule, and that through the ſucceſſion of the byſhops of Rome, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſainct Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vntyll hys tyme, the trueth was deryued, from hande to hande, &amp; that it might there eaſely be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and had. And herevpon he ſayeth further theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>Ad hanc enim eccleſiam propter potentiorem principalitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neceſſe est omnem conuenire eccleſiam, hoc eſt eos qui ſunt vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fideles.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>For vnto this churche</hi> (meanyng, and poyntynge the ſea of Rome) <hi>for the more mighty principalty of it, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole churche of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173756:51"/> is to ſaye, all the faythfull, where ſoeuer they be, muſte aſſemble, or repayre vnto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Augustinus</note>And ſainct Auguſtyne, agreably herevnto, doth, in his .162. Epiſtle, ſaye: that in the churche of Rome, the primacy of the Apoſtolike Sea, did euer floriſhe. And the ſame ſainct Auguſtyne, wrytinge agaynſte one Petilianus, whyche dyd blaſpheme the ſea of Rome (as heretykes doo nowe a dayes) doeth more ouer write in this maner. <hi>Yf all the byſhoppes of the worlde, were ſuche men, as thou dooeſt mooſt falſely reporte theim to be, what hath the ſea of Rome hurted the, where Peter dyd ſyt, and nowe Anaſtaſius ſytteth? or what hath the ſea of Hieruſalem hurted the, where Iames did ſit, and now at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dothe ſit, with whome we are in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike vnitie ioyned, and from whome ye haue deuyded your ſelues, in youre wycked rage, or fury, why doeſt thou cal the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſea, the ſea of peſtilence? If thou doo it for the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou thinkeſt to preache the lawe, and not to fulfyll the lawe, dyd our ſauiour I praye the, any ſuche iniury to the ſea or chaire of the ſcribes, and Phariſeis, of whome he ſayeth.</hi> They ſay, but they doo not? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the holye Martyr, ſainct Cipriane in the thyrde Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Ciprianus.</note> of hys fyrſte booke, ſpeakynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:173756:51"/> certayne, whyche dyd diſobey, &amp; contempne, Cornelius, the byſhoppe of Rome, writeth in this maner. <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim aliunde hereſes oborte ſunt, aut nata ſunt ſciſmata, <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> inde quod ſacerdoti dei no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obtemperatur, nec vnus in eccleſia ad te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos, et ad tempus iudex, vice Chriſti iudicatur: Cui ſi ſecundum magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria diuina obtemperaret fraternitas vniuerſa, nemo aduerſus ſacerdotum collegium, quic<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>quam</ex>
                  </expan> moueret.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>Of none other cauſe are hereſyes ſpronge vp, or ſciſmes ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, than of this, that the prieſt of GOD</hi> (meanynge Cornelius; the byſhoppe of Rome,) <hi>is not obeyed, and one is not taken in the churche, to be the hyghe prieſt for the tyme, and for the tyme in Chriſtes ſtede a iudge, or Chriſtes vicar, vnto whome yf the hole fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitye were, accordynge to Goddes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, obediente, no man woulde any thing moue, or ſtyrre agaynſt the colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, or companye of prieſtes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sainct Auguſtyne alſo wrytynge agaynſte the Epiſtle of a Maniche, whyche Epiſtle is intituled,<note place="margin">Augustinus.</note> or called, <hi>Fundamentum,</hi> giueth to the ſea of Rome, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous prerogatyue, and dothe buylde hys faythe, amongeſt other thinges, vpon the ſucceſſion, of the Byſhoppes of Rome, who after ſainct Peter dyd fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe orderly, euen to hys tyme, whych was .300. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res after Chriſte. And he wryteth in this maner. <hi>Multa ſunt, que me in eccleſie gremio iuſtiſſime tenent: Tenet me conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio populoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tenet authoritas miraculis inchoata, ſpe nutrita, charitate aucta, vetustate firmata, tenet ab ipſa ſede petri Apostoli, cui paſcendas oues ſuas poſt reſurrectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuam dominus commendauit, vſque
<pb facs="tcp:173756:52"/> ad preſentem epiſcopatum, ſucceſſio ſacerdotum.</hi> That is to ſaye, <hi>there are many thinges, which of very good reaſon, doo kepe me, in the lawes of the catholyke churche. The conſent of ſo manye people, and nations, or cuntries, dothe kepe me: the authoritie of the churche, begon with myracles, nouryſſhed with hope, encreaſed with charitye, and confyrmed with antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, doeth kepe me: the ſucceſſion alſo of byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes, from ſainct Peter the Apoſtles ſeat, or tyme (to whome oure Lorde dyd after his reſurrection, commyt hys ſhepe to be fedde) vnto this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Biſhopricke</hi> (meanyng Rome) <hi>doeth kepe me in the catholyke churche.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sainct Hierom alſo in his Epiſtle to Damaſus, doeth ſet fourthe very notably,<note place="margin">Hieronimus.</note> the primacye, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premitye, of the byſhoppe of Rome, as beyng ſainct Peters ſucceſſours, and amongeſt other thynges, he ſayeth thus. <hi>Si quis cathedrae Petri iungitur meus eſt.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>Yf any man be ioyned to Peters chayre, or hold of Peters ſeat</hi> (meaning the ſea of Rome) <hi>he is myne, and I receyue and ioyne wyth hym.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſius</note>Sainct Ambroſe alſo in his thyrd booke, of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and in the fyrſt Chapiter, doth ſay thus. <hi>Eccleſia Romana hanc conſuetudinem non habet, cuius tipum in omnibus ſequimur.</hi> That is to ſaye, <hi>the churche of Rome (whoſe forme, or trade, we doo folowe in all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173756:52"/> poyntes) hath no ſuche cuſtome</hi> Other lyke autorities of the auncient fathers, for the primacye, and ſupremacy of the Sea of Rome, there are, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infinite: But what nede many autorities, eyther of ſcripture, or of the fathers, in this behalfe, ſeyng very experience, hath this thouſande yeres, proued, that ſuche, as dyſobeyed the ſea of Rome, did fal ſone after into abhomynable hereſy, and therevpon into deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion amongeſt them ſelues, and conſequently, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or els, in proceſſe of time, were gladde, and faine, to returne to their dewe obedience againe. Yf you be deſyrouſe to haue exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in this matter, looke but on thoſe countryes, and thoſe parſons, that now be in captiuitie vnder the great Turke, who in tyme paſte, agreeing with the ſea of Rome, did floryſhe in chriſten religion, &amp; all welthe, looke alſo vpon Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, and take example therby, how they proſpered amonges theym ſelues, ſynce they declyned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the obedyence of the ſea of Rome. And it is a worlde, to ſee howe thoſe, whome they tooke for theyr greateſt doctours, haue abuſed, ſeduced, and mocked theym, euen in this matter of the primacye, for where as Luther, eſpeciallye, and aboue all other,<note place="margin">Lutherus.</note> was theyr ryngleader in this matter: yet when he was emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt lerned men, and ſhoulde talke of this matter, wyth theim, he was ſo driuen to the wal, that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in wrytynge, to be ſhewed at this daye, he dyd in a booke of hys, intituled. <hi>Reſolutio Lutheriana ſuper propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitione ſua. 13. de poteſtate Papae,</hi> confeſſe and ſaye playnlye, as hereafter doeth folowe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:53"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Primum, quod me mouet Ro. pontificem eſſe alijs omnibus, quos ſaltem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerimus ſe pontifices gerere, ſuperiorem, est ipſa voluntas dei, quam in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo facto uidemus. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim ſine voluntate dei, in hanc monarchiam unqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venire potuiſſet Ro. pontifex. At voluntas dei, quo quo modo rota fuerit, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuerentia ſuſcipienda eſt, Ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non licet temere. Ro. pontifici in ſuo pris matu reſistere. Hec autem ratio tanta est, vt ſi etiam nulla ſcriptura, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la alla cauſa eſſet, haec tamen ſatis eſſet ad compeſcendam temeritatem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistentium, et hac ſola ratione glorioſiſſimus martir Ciprianus, per multas epistolas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidentiſſime gloriatur contra omnes epiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſarios, ſicut.</hi> 3. <hi>Re legimus, quod dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tribus Iſrael diſceſſeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a Roboa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, filio Salomonis, et tamen quia voluntate dei, ſine autoritate factum eſt, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum apud deum fuit. Nam et apud theologos omnes, voluntas ſigni, quam vocant operationem dei, non minus quam alia figna voluntatis dei, vt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta, prohibit. &amp;c. metuenda est. Ideo non uideo, quomodo ſint excuſati aſciſmatis reatu, qui huic voluntati contrauenientes, ſeſe a Ro. pontificis autoritate ſubtrahunt. Ecce hec eſt una prima mihi inſuperabilis ratio, quae me ſubijcit Ro. pontifici et primatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiteri cogit.</hi> That is to ſay <hi>The firſt thing, which moueth me to think, or beleue, the Romayne Byſſhoppe to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to all other, whom at the leaſte wyſe we doo know to accompte them ſelues for Byſſhoppes, is the very wyll of God, which we doo ſee, euen in the very facte, or matter. For in dede without the wyll of God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne Byſſhoppe, coulde not at any tyme haue commen to this monarchy, or ſupreme rule, and the wyll of God, by what meane ſo euer it be knowen, is to be receyued, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with reuerence, and therefore it is not lawefull, folyſhly, or hedely to make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173756:53"/> vnto the ſayd Romayne Byſſhope, in his Byſſhoppryke. And this reaſon is ſoo great, or of ſuche force, that althoughe noo ſcrypture, nor no other cauſe were, yet thys were ſufficient ynoughe to brydle, or kepe vnder, the temeritie, or madnes, of them,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>make reſiſtance. And by this reaſon alone, the moſt glorious Martyr Cyprian, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Epyſtles doth moſt boldely glory, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſe, agaynſt all the aduerſaries of anye of the Byſſhoppes, accordyng as we do reade in the third boke of the kynges. Where all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the x. tribes of Iſraell, dyd departe from Roboam, the ſonne of Salomon, yet bycauſe it was done by the wyll of God, it was without other authoritie firme, &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For alſo emongeſt all the deuynes, the wyll of the ſigne, whiche they doo call the workyng of God, is to be feared no leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other ſignes of the will of God, as precepts and thinges forbydden &amp;c. And therefore I doo not ſe howe they be excuſed from the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or ſynne, of ſcyſme, who doing, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minge agaynſt this will, doo withdrawe, or pull them ſelues, from the Authoritie of the Romaine Byſſhoppe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:54"/>
            <p>Thus much ſayth Luther himſelfe, and ſoo ſhall you fynd it, if ye reade his ſayde worke, in the place aforeſayd: and the thing ſo being, you may ſe, what a holy father that marchant was, to deceyue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as he dyd, and to bryng them to that wonderfull calamitie, that the thirde or fourth generation (if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſo longe doo contynue) ſhall feele, and ſmarte for it, as other alſo ſhall, that be in the ſame caſe. And now to retourne to our owne country of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, this may be truly ſpoken, that of all realmes chriſten, there is none that hath (beſides the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral dutie) ſo ſpecial cauſe to fauour that ſee of Rome, as England hath. For from that ſee, came the fayth into this Iland,<note place="margin">Beda. Eccleſ. hist. Angl li. i,</note> in the daies of kyng Lucius, about an hundreth and fyftye yeares after Chryſte. And vi. C. yere after Chriſt, whan the Saxons wer ſpred ouer the hole realme, and were infidells, there were ſent moſt notable, and godly preachers, hither into England: who conuerted and tourned many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes, to the fayth. And what benefites we haue in our dayes receyued of that ſee of Rome, all men doo perceyue, and feale in them ſelues, &amp; do thanke god therefore, or ells the deuyll hath wonderfullye blynded and ſeduced them. Nowe on the other ſide, what miſeries haue be faine emongeſt vs, ſynce our diſobedience agaynſt the ſee of Rome, and ſynce the tyme, that temporall princes dyd take vpon them, that offyce, which is ſpirituall, and not belongyng to the regall power, but greatly diſtant, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the ſame, I nede not in words to declare, foraſmuch as you haue felt the ſmart therof in dede,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173756:54"/> and to this day are not quyte of Gods plage for the ſame. Wherfore to conclude in this matter, this ſhal be to exhort you, and in Gods name to requyre you, to eſteme the primacy, and ſupremitie of the ſea of Rome, as an authoritie inſtituted by Chryſt, for the quyetnes of the chriſten people, and for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of chryſtendome, in one catholyke, true fayth, &amp; for the defence of it, agaynſt all hereſie, and wherby quyeting your ſelues, to ſerue God, in the catholike truth, you ſhall ſoneſt appeaſe his wrath, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his fauour, and grace, in this lyfe, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obteyne the euerlaſtyng lyfe, whyche ſende vnto you all, the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt, to whome be al honor, and glorye, worlde wythout ende Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris, et Archidiaconi London,</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:55"/>
            <head>¶ An homely declarynge that in the bleſſed Sacrament of the aultare, is the very body, and bloude of oure Sauioure Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that men are once graft in Chriſt, and be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his death, &amp; paſſion, amonge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theyr dueties, one of the cheife is, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to prepare them ſelues to the worthy receauynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aultare, wherevnto are two thynges on our partes requiſit (as ſayeth ſaynt Baſell,<note place="margin">Baſill in his rules.</note> &amp; good reaſon confirmeth) the one, feare, the other, fayth. The feare whiche men muſt haue, when they prepare them ſelues to come to this ſacrament, ought to be grounded vpon that terrible ſayinge of ſaynt Paule, in the .xi. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians, where he ſayth:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> that <hi>whoſoeuer doth participate therof vnworthely, doth eate and drinke his owne dampnation.</hi> The fayth, whiche we muſt haue in oure hartes, when we come to Gods borde, is to be buylded lykewiſe, vpon the vndoubted aucthorities of ſcripture, whiche declare mooſt playnly vnto vs, what meate it is, that we there eate. For the parfyt vnderſtandyng wherof, let vs conſider, that our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173756:55"/> Chriſte, beynge here on earth, dyd fyrſt make a ſolempne promyſe of a meate, whiche hym ſelfe woulde geue vnto vs, and afterwarde in dede, he dyd geue the ſame, accordynge to his promyſe. In the promyſe makynge he ſayde (as it is wrytten in the .vi. chapter of S. Iohns Goſpel.) <hi>The breade,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> 
               <hi>or foode that I wyll geue vnto you, is my fleſhe, whiche fleſhe I wyll geue for the lyfe of the world:</hi> and in the ſame chapter he alſo ſaith. <hi>My fleſh is verily meat, and my bloud is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely drincke.</hi> And as he then promiſed, ſo he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde perfourmed, euen the very laſte nyghte that euer he companyed with his Apoſtles, before his death, at whiche tyme, he toke breade into his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and gaue thankes, and brake it, and gaue it to his diſciples, and ſayde: <hi>Take eate, this is my body, whiche ſhalbe geuen for you.</hi> Yf we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the wordes ſpoken by Chryſte, when he made the promyſe of a meat, to be by him geuen vnto vs, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe other wordes, whiche he vttered in geuyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, we nede not doubt of the thynges which he gaue. In the promyſſe makynge, he ſayde: that he woulde geue vs his fleſſhe, in the perfourmynge of the promiſe, he geueth the ſame, ſayinge, <hi>take eate, this is my bodie.</hi> Agayne, in the promiſe making, he affyrmeth, that the fleſhe, whiche he would geue vs to fede on, ſhould be the ſelfſame fleſh, that ſholde be geuen for the lyfe of the world, and in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunce of his promyſe, he ſaid, that the thing which he
<pb facs="tcp:173756:56"/> gaue, was his bodye, whiche ſhoulde be geuen to death for vs. Nowe the circumſtaunces beyng wel conſydered, which our ſauiour vſed in the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this moſt bleſſed Sacrament, ſhal greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme al godly hartes, in the true belefe of the ſame. The tyme was the night before he ſuffered deathe, to ſignifie vnto vs, that this meate, being differred to the laſt day, that euer our Sauiour was conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt with his Apoſtles, muſt nedes be his very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and bloude in dede, and ſuch a meate as no other can be in any wyſe comparable vnto it. Agayne, in that our ſauiour dyd eate of the paſchal lambe with his Apoſtles, immediatly before he did inſtitute this ſacrament, it moſt playnely declareth vnto vs, that this ſacrament is a marueylous worthye myſterye, and that very thing, which the eatyng of the paſchal lambe, in the olde lawe did prefigurate, for whiche cauſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this was inſtituted, that was abrogated Nether is it with out a meruelouſe conſideration, that Chryſt at that heauenly banket, would of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, nother haue the bleſſed Vyrgyn Mary his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, preſente with him, nor anye other of his dyſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſaue onely the .xii. Apoſtles, whome he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the heade miniſters of al his miſteries here on the earth, and ſpecially to be the miniſters of this moſt bleſſed ſacrament, and the inſtructours of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, touching the ſame. Now what meneth it, that our Sauiour was not content to offer them this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament onely, but with the offeryng therof, he ſaid alſo vnto them. Take eate, take and drinke? Do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſe, to offer to other, meate and drinke, for anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173756:56"/> purpoſe, but onelye that they ſhoulde eate and drynke thereof? but bycauſe it was his bodye, and hys bloude, therefore he fyrſte byddeth them take, and not feare to eate and drynke the ſame.</p>
            <p>Beſydes this, it is to be well noted, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> three Euangeliſtes, Mathew, Marke, and Luke, doo all three agree in the maner of the inſtitution of thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they wrytyng all thre their goſpeles at ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry tymes,<note place="margin">Chriſosto. and Theophilact.</note> as Mathew eyght yere after the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of our ſauiour Chriſt. Marke .x. yeares. Luke xv. yeares. And where in doubtefull ſpeaches of our ſauiour Chriſt, ſome one or other of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſtes, euermore openeth plainely the very meaning of the ſpeches, yet touching theſe words, this is my body, no one of them, maketh any declaration vpon the ſame, but they all leue them to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vs, as they ſound, and (as of moſt plaine wordes) they make no expoſition or interpretation of them at al. Whyche poynte muſt be well conſydered. And therfore note, that where Chryſt ſayde. <hi>It is impoſſible for a rych man to entre into the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> (bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of theſe wordes may be diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly taken,<note place="margin">Marke. 10.</note> thereof) S. Marke in his tenth chapyter declareth the very meanyng of them, ſaying: <hi>It is harde for them that truſt in there ſubſtaunce to be ſaued.</hi> Agayne Chriſt at another tyme ſayde to the Iewes, <hi>looſe you this temple, &amp; in three dayes ſhal I buyld it agayne.</hi> And for that the ſenſe of theſe wordes is doughtfull S. Iohn there expoundeth them and ſayeth, that Chryſt by the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement
<pb facs="tcp:173756:57"/> his body, whiche ſhould be by the Iewes put to death, and by him the thirde daye ſhoulde be rayſed from death to lyfe. In the .vii. of Ihon,<note place="margin">Iohn 7.</note> oure ſauiour ſayeth: <hi>He that beleueth in me, as the ſcripture ſayeth, there ſhall, ryuers of quicke water flowe out of him.</hi> And bicauſe this ſaing is obſcure, S. Iohn to make it open, ſayeth, that he ſpake thoſe wordes, of the ſpirit, which they that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued in him ſhould receyue. In the .xii. chapyter of S. Ihon, our ſauiour ſaieth in this maner. <hi>If I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyfte vp from the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> 
               <hi>I wyl drawe al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges vnto my ſelfe.</hi> And S. Iohn by and by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs the expoſition, ſaying, that hereby he ſigny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, what kynde of death he ſhould ſuffer. Manye other lyke places are there in the newe teſtamente, the matter of which places, is not ſo highe, nor ſoo nedefull to be ryghtly vnderſtanded, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of theſe wordes, <hi>this is my body,</hi> and yet of theſe wordes, no one Euangeliſt maketh any expoſition, bycauſe the wordes are playnely, and ſymply to be taken as they were ſpoken. Beſids al this, we haue in S. Paule in the .xi Chapiter of his firſt Epyſtle, to the Corinthians, a goodly, and a large proceſſe touchyng this Sacrament, and yet in that whole proceſſe, no matter to inſtructe vs otherwyſe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue of it, than that there is in it the very bodye and bloude of our ſauiour Chryſt. For fyrſte he vttereth the wordes of our ſauiour euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſtes do, as that he ſayd <hi>this is my body,</hi> and he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no declaration vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Secondly where
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173756:57"/> none of the Euangeliſts make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of any paine due to the vnworthy receauer. S Paule affirmeth that the vnworthy receyuing of this Sacrament bryngeth iudgement, and dampnation. Thirdly, he telleth, that for the vnworthy receauing herof, God plageth cities, and countryes, with ſondry greuous plages, as with infirmity, with ſyckenes, and with death alſo. Forthely, he geueth vs counſell diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to examine and trye our ſelfes, before we come to gods borde. If the very body and bloude of oure ſauiour Chriſt, be nat in dede in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aultare, why ſhold our ſauiour ſo ſpeake as he ſpake in the promyſſe made thereof? why dyd he, as he did in the inſtituting therof? why dyd none of the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts ſo declare chriſtes wordes? why dyd ſayncte Paule ſo terribly pronounce of the vnworthy recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of it, and ſo erneſtly warne vs, of due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be made therefore? It is then moſt vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly to be of all chriſten people beleued, that in the Sacrament of the aultare, there is the verye body and bloude, of our ſauiour Chryſt, worthy of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, the ſelfe ſame in ſubſtaunce, that is in heauen: which thing for Chryſt to bryng to paſſe, is a thing moſt eaſye, he being God almighty, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth: and for him to do, is mooſt ſemely, that as he gaue that bodye, to deathe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme vs, ſo he ſhould giue the ſame in this heauenly bankitte, to fede vs, that he mighte be all in all. The body of our ſauiour Chriſt to be in very dede in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in the viſible fourme of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aultare, inuiſibly vnder the viſible four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb facs="tcp:173756:58"/> of breade and wyne, nether is impoſſible to hys power, that made all thinges of noughte, nether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemely for his exceadyng great loue towardes vs, who ſo loued vs, that for vs, he did not refuſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death, and that the death of the croſſe: neyther yet is it agaynſt his wyll, who of his onely mercye, ſo promyſed, and wyth hys omnipotent word, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted it, nother is it fynally vnfytte for his wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſeyng he hath ſo ordeyned, that euery natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall mother, nouryſheth her children, wyth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of her owne body. And why then ſhold chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men refuſe to beleue it? why do we not rather embrace it, and gyue God moſt hartye thankes for it, being the greateſt iewel, that euer was amonge mortal men: why do we not prepare our ſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely to receaue it, and as in all other poyntes of the chriſten religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo in the belefe of it, geue credite to fayth, and bryng reaſon, and our ſenſes, in ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder fayth, but ſuffer our ghoſtly enemy by carnall reaſons, to bryng vs away into hereſie, &amp; quyte and cleane to pull the ryghte faythe out of oure hartes? Let vs all, good people, from hence forth be conſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the trueth, and as all the catholyke churche bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and hath alwayes beleued, let vs vndoutedlye perſwade our ſelues, that in the bleſſed ſacrament of the Aultare, there is vnder the fourmes of breade &amp; wine, the ſelfe ſame body of our ſauiour Chriſt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which was borne of the Vyrgin Mary, and ſuffered death on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe for vs, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father &amp; the holy goſt, be all honor &amp; glory, world wythout ende Amen.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris, et Archidiaconi London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:173756:58"/>
            <head>¶ And Homelye of Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the aultare, ii. thinges ſpeciallye to be conſidered, the one is, the body and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt, ther really co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other is the fourmes of breade &amp; wine, vnder whych the ſaid body &amp; blud are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined. Of the firſt parte ye hard in the laſt homely. Touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the general belefe of the catholyke Churche (if there were nothing els) ought, and may be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent grounde, for euery godly man, to build hys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vpon, which churche, doth beleue, that there is no ſubſtaunce of material bread, and wyne remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning: but onely the fourmes of breade and wyne, &amp; the ſubſtaunce of Chriſtes body and bloude, there ſo contayned. And yet, becauſe ſome haue vainely, and curiouſly, of late yeares talked of this ſecond part, and haue put many fonde doutes, and ſcruples into peoples heades, concerning the ſame, ye ſhall nowe at large, and fully (I truſt) be inſtructed therin. And fyrſt this is to be noted, that God hath from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the worlde, manye tymes appeared to man, ſome tymes in one ſorte,<note place="margin">Gene. xviii.</note> and ſomtymes in an other. In the .xviii. Chapiter of Geneſis it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:173756:59"/> howe God, and two Aungelles with him, dyd appeare vnto Abraham, in the lykeneſſe of men, and howe Abraham feaſted them. Howe vaine a matter were it, (I pray you) for vs here buſelye to reaſon, howe God or Aungell, coulde appeare lyke man? and whether they had true bodyes or no? and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they dyd eate in dede or no? and yf they hadde not true bodyes in dede, howe the appearaunce of bodyes coulde be, where the ſubſtaunce of bodyes was not? In the thirde chapter of the booke called Exodus, we rede, that God appeared to Moyſes in the lykenes of flamynge fyre,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.</note> and that oute of a buſhe. In the .v. of Ioſue it is recorded, how one ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly appeared vnto Ioſue lyke a man,<note place="margin">Ioſue. 5.</note> hauynge a ſworde drawen in his hand. What can anye manne ſaye, howe God ſhoulde appeare in a flame of fyre, or what ſubſtaunce of a ſworde was, in that which appeared to Ioſue? Hereby it is eaſy to vnderſtande how daungerous a thing it is, to go about by mans wyt or reaſon, to diſcuſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. Who ſeyth not, that by the meane of ſuch preſumptuous curioſitie, men haue of late falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into mooſt deteſtable errours, touching the mooſte bleſſed Sacramente of the aultare, and haue mooſt ſpytefully rayled agaynſt the ſame, and with mooſt vyle termes haue geſted thereof, and finallye, mooſt vily haue vſed the mooſt precious bodye and bloude of our ſauiour Chryſt in the ſame? In which doing, how can they loke for anye fauour at the handes of their heauenly father, ſeyng in ſuch diſpituous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they entreate the Bodye and bloud of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173756:59"/> Chriſt his ſonne? But now to procede forth, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> declaration of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thing, to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aultare: Ye muſt knowe that the preſence of our ſauioure Chryſte in this ſacrament of the aulter, is not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> intente, that Chryſt ſhould be conuerſaunt with vs here in thys Sacrament, in ſuch ſort and maner, as he was with his Apoſtles when he liued here on earth, that is to ſaye: in the viſible ſhape and fourme of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but his preſence in the Sacrament, is to the intent to be to vs an heauenly fode, and therefore he is preſente in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnder the fourmes of bread and wine ſo that our outwarde eyes and ſenſes, are certifyed with the outwarde fourmes, and ſenſyble quality<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and the whole man with al, receaueth the verye bodi and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt. S. Auguſtine (as is writen in a boke called <hi>Sententie proſperi</hi>) dothe ſay,<note place="margin">Auguſte in Sente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peri.</note> that <hi>chriſten men do honour vnder the for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of breade and wine, which thei ſee with their bodely eies, the bodie and bloude of our Sauiour Chriſt, which they do not ſee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenus.</note> Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Emiſſenus alſo, an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient father of the Greke churche, ſpeaking of the foreſayd two partes contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Sacrament of the aultar, ſayeth in thys maner. <hi>This is the thing which bi al meanes we intend to proue, that the Sacrifice of the churche doth conſiſt, and is made of two par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, that is, of the viſible fourmes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and of the inuiſible body &amp; bloud of oure
<pb facs="tcp:173756:60"/> Sauiour Chryſt.</hi> S Ciprian in his treatiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,<note place="margin">Cipriane de coena domini,</note> 
               <hi>De coena domini,</hi> doeth moſt playnelye ſaye, that <hi>the bread which our Lord did giue to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples, was by the omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of god made fleſhe, &amp; was chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in nature, but not in fourme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebius Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenus in a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di of Christ.</note> The forenamed Euſebius in a ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his made of the body of Chryſt, dothe farder ſaye: that <hi>Chriſt the inuiſible prieſt doth tourne viſible creatures bi his word, through his ſecret po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, into the ſubſtaunce of his body &amp; blud.</hi> Now for to ſignify this chaunge, or turning of bread and wyne, into the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtes bodye and bloude, the catholyke church vſeth this word, Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is as much to ſay, as the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of one ſubſtaunce into another: Nether is it to be counted vnfyt, that there ſhould in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aultare, be the fourme of bread, &amp; yet not the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread, ſeyng God is the doer &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker therof,<note place="margin">Exo. 20:</note> to whom nothing is impoſſible. We read in the nynetenth Chapiter of Exodus, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when God came downe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen vnto Mounte Sinai, there was heard a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of a trumpet, and yet mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial trumpet was there none.<note place="margin">vii. chapiter of the fourth of the kinges.</note> In the fourth boke of the Kynges, &amp; the .vii. chapiter, God cauſed a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to be heard in the tentes of the Sirians, as if it had bene of horſes, charets, and of a greate armye, &amp; yet was there nother horſe, charet, nor armye. In the thirde chapiter of Daniel, it is recorded, howe the three chyldren were in the myddeſt of the flamyng furnes, and yet felte no heate, ſoo that there was the ſubſtaunce of fyre, and yet it dyd not bourne,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173756:60"/> which to nature is impoſſible, but to GOD is an eaſye matter. In the .xvii. of Mathewe we reade,<note place="margin">Math. 17.</note> howe that Chryſte was tranſfygurated, and that hys face dyd ſhyne as the Sonne, and that hys apparel was made as whyte as ſnowe. In the .xxiiii. of Luke,<note place="margin">Ln. 34.</note> Chryſt appeared to two of his dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples goyng to Emaus, like a ſtraunger. In al theſe foreſayd examples, we ſee as ſtraunge a woorke as is tranſubſtantiation, &amp; yet no man douteth of them bycauſe God is the worker, nor anye man aſketh howe this, or that coulde be, but beleuethe it, and ſoo oughte we to doo, concernynge the chaunge of the ſubſtaunce, of breade and wyne, into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of Chriſtes bodye and bloude, and not aſke howe it may be. The bleſſed martyr Iuſtinus, affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that this queſtion, howe,<note place="margin">Iuſtinus mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir.</note> is a token of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe, and S. Ciril, writing vpon the .vi. Chapiter of S. Iohn, blameth the Capernaites,<note place="margin">Ciril vpon the Vi. of S. Iohn.</note> bycauſe they dyd aſke howe Chryſt was able to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fleſhe to eate. The wordes of ſaincte Cyryll be theſe. <hi>They aſke not without great impietie how canne this man geue vs hys fleſhe, and they remember not that nothing is impoſſible to God, but let vs</hi> (ſayeth he) <hi>haue firme faith in the miſteries, and let vs neuer in ſo high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, eyther thincke, or aſke this, how. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God is the worker, let vs not aſke how, but let vs leaue the knowledge of his worke to hym ſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſoſtome vpon Iohn the Vi.</note> S. Chriſoſtome lykewyſe vpon the ſayde .vi. Chapiter ſayeth, that <hi>when this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:61"/> howe any thing is done, commyth into our myndes, then with all, there commeth vnbelefe alſo</hi> But bycauſe in ſcrypture the thyng that we receyue, when we come to the ſacramente, is called bread, therefore men haue fanſied with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, that there muſt be the ſubſtaunce of materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al breade, deceauing themſelues, by myſtakyng, the ſignification of this worde, breade. For thoughe in our common ſpeach we vſe to ſignify by this word, bread, that one kinde of materiall ſubſtaunce which is made of corne or graine, yet in ſcripture, it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all kynde of fode, whether it be the fode of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, or the fode of the ſoule, and ſo dothe alſo the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne worde, <hi>Panis,</hi> elles when we deſyre god in our Pater noſter, to geue vs our dayly bread, we ſhold make an vnperfytte petition, which yet is a mooſte perfyt petition,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> wherby we aſke of our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all neceſſary fode. In the .vi. of Ihon, Manna is called breade, and yet was it made of no kynde of corne, or grayne, and in the ſame chapiter Chriſte is called breade, bycauſe he is the fode of the ſoule, and there lykewyſe, the fleſhe of Chriſt in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is called breade, and not there onely, but in S. Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les Epyſtle alſo to the Corinthians, for that it is the fode, whereon we fede, when we receaue the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Agayne it is a commen trade in ſcripture, to cal thinges by the name of that thinge whyche they once were, as Adam is called earth, becauſe he was made of Earth,<note place="margin">Math. 11</note> and Chryſt ſayeth, the blinde ſee, the lame walke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deafe heare, the dumme, ſpeake, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng by the blynde, lame, deafe, and dumme, ſuche
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173756:61"/> as before had bene ſoo, but then were otherwyſe. Thyrdlye, for that the fourme of breade doeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, it is in that reſpecte too, called breade. For theſe cauſes, good faythful hartes, are nothyng gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued wyth the callynge of it breade in the ſcrypture, but groundynge them ſelfes vpon the woordes of oure ſauioure Chriſte, when he ſayde, thys is my bodye, and knowynge that it to be bothe breade, and hys bodye alſo at once is impoſſyble, they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doutedlye beleue, that by the power of GOD, the ſubſtaunce of bread, is turned into the ſubſtaunce of Chriſtes bodye, and ſo muſte all men beleue, that wyll be lyuely members of the catholyke churche, and in that there belefe, they muſte honoure the bodye and bloude of oure ſauioure Chriſte, in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of the Aultare, as alwayes chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haue vſed to doo.</p>
            <p>Saincte Auſtin in hys expoſition made vpon the .99. Pſalme<note place="margin">S. Augustine vpon the .99. Pſalme.</note> ſayeth: that <hi>it is ſynne, not to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure the bodye of Chriſte,</hi> meanynge in the Sacramente of the Aultare. And (as it is before in thys Homily alledged) he alſo ſayeth in the name of all men. <hi>We doo honoure vnder the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of breade and wyne, whyche we ſe, the bodye and bloude of Chriſte, whyche we do not ſee.</hi> Wherefore, good chriſten people, knowing nowe what is the ryght belefe, touchynge the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of the aultare, embrace, and folowe the ſame, and cleaue faſte to the catholyke churche, the
<pb facs="tcp:173756:62"/> ſpouſe of Chryſte, that you maye be true members of Chriſte, to whome wyth the father, and the holye Ghoſte, be all honoure, and glorye worlde wythoute ende. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <byline>Io. Harpesfelde, ſacrae theologiae profeſſoris et Archidiaconi London.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:173756:62"/>
            <head>¶ An Homily wherein is aunſwere made to certayne common obiections, agaynſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſtes bodye, and bloude in the ſacramente of the Aultare.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ete it were, dearely beloued in our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Chriſt, that we all ſhould ſo fully, &amp; wholy, cleaue to the faith of Chriſtes ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhoulde cauſe vs once to doute or ſtagger, in any part part of the ſame. For ſuch a kinde of faith, doth God requyre of vs, and for ſuche kynde of faythe, good chriſten people, are in ſcripture called Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:<note place="margin">Roma. 4</note> which Abraham (as it is wrytten in the fourth to the Romaynes) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to hope, beleued in hope, that he ſhould be the father of many nations, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to that, which was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>So ſhal thy ſede be. And he fainted not in the faith, nor yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered his owne bodi, which was now dead euen when he was almoſt an hundred yeare olde: nether yet that Sara was paſte chylde bearynge, he ſtaggered not at the promyſe of god, through vnbelefe, but was ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the
<pb facs="tcp:173756:63"/> faith, and gaue honor to god, fully certified y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what he had promyſed, the ſame he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make good.</hi> Yf we then wilbe the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Abraham, we muſte not faynt in faith, nor conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gods woordes after the courſe of nature. Saint Paule in the .x.<note place="margin">2. Corin. x.</note> chapiter of his ſeconde epiſtle to the Corinthians, geueth vs an example in hym ſelfe, howe we ſhoulde alwayes brynge reaſon in ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to faithe, ſayng. <hi>The weapons of our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are not carnall, but mighty in God, to ouerthrowe ſtronge holdes, to deſtroy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles, and euery hyghe thynge that exalteth it ſelfe agaynſte the knowledge of God, and to brynge in captiuitye vnto the ſeruyce of Chriſte, all vnderſtandinge:</hi> What (thinke you) is the cauſe why the Iewes beleue not on Chriſte? Verely fyrſte, becauſe he was borne of a Vyrgyn, which is contrary to the courſe of nature. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lykewyſe, he was in vnitie of perſon, God &amp; man, whyche how it may be, no mans wyt is able, by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural power, to conceaue: thyrdly, becauſe he beyng God and man, ſuffered the death of the croſſe, which for God to be content to do, ſemeth to naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a thynge mooſt abſurde, but good chriſten folke geuyng place to faith, do moſt vndoutedly beleue on Chriſt, God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crucified, according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, S. Paule writeth in his fyrſte Chapter of his fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">i. Corin. 1.</note> ſaying: <hi>We preache Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, to the Iewes a ſtumblyng blocke, to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173756:63"/> the gentels, a foliſhnes, but to ſo many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tels as ar called, Chriſt the power, &amp; wyſedome of God.</hi> And agreably here vnto, he ſayeth alſo in the nexte Chapiter folowynge. <hi>My talke, &amp; my preaching was not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſible woordes of mans wyſedome, but in ſhewynge of power, and of the ſpyryte, that youre faythe ſhould not reſt in the wiſedome of man, but in the power of God.</hi> This gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aduyſe and counſel of S. Paule, may and ought ſo to ſtaye vs in the faythe of the catholyke churche, that nether carnall reaſons, grounded vpon the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intelligence of mans natural wyt, nether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceatfull iudgement of oure ſenſes, ſhoulde make vs once to doute, of any one trueth in Chriſtes religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were it neuer ſo contrarye to the courſe of nature, neuer ſo farre aboue our capacities, and neuer ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde to the appearaunce of our outwarde ſenſes. But foraſmuch, as throughe the iniquitie of theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euyll yeares, dyuers haue hadde ſondrye fonde dowtes and ſcruples, put into theyr heades, eſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, agaynſt the preſence of Chriſtes body &amp; bloude, in the Sacrament of the aultare, and throughe ſuch dowtes haue ſwarued from the true belefe therein, therefore here ſhall folowe aunſweres, and ſoluty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ſuch dowtes as haue ben moſt commen, that from henceforthe no man ſhall nede to be ſeduced by them, or other lyke.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> ¶ Fyrſt it hath bene obiected, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauiour Chriſt, immediatlye after that he had inſtituted, and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:173756:64"/> to his Apoſtles the ſacramente, dyd ſay vnto them. <hi>Do this in remembraunce of me.</hi> Vppon which wordes ſome haue concluded, that the bodye of our ſauiour Chriſt, cannot be in the ſacramente. ¶ But let vs duely waye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes,<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> and meaning of the ſame, and we ſhall mooſt plainly perceaue theyr erroure, and myſvnderſtandyng. Saincte Paule in hys fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Corin. xi.</note> and in the .xi. chapter of the ſame Epiſtle, intreating of the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacrament of the aultare, and ther ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the true ſenſe of that commaundemente of Chriſt, ſaythe in this maner. <hi>As oft as you eate of that bread, and drinke of that cuppe, you ſhal ſhew forthe the Lordes death vntil he come.</hi> So then the remembraunce whyche oure ſauioure there requyreth of vs, is the remembraunce of hys death, which is paſt, and not preſente, and therefore after moſt proper maner of ſpeache, may well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred. Now this remembraunce, can in no wyſe poſſibly be ſo lyuely, and ſo effectually worke in oure hartes, as when we moſt certenly beleue, that in the ſacrament of the aultare, is veryly the ſelfe ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in ſubſtaunce, which died for vs, and therfore the Prophet Dauid, foreſeyng in ſpirit, this ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a memorye, ſayeth in hys .cx. Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.</note> 
               <hi>Oure mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gratious Lord, hath made a memory of all his merueylous workes,</hi> and by &amp; by, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in what maner he maketh that memory, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thoſe woordes, <hi>he hathe geuen a foode to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173756:64"/> ſuche as feare him.</hi> This fode (which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet ſayeth, that Chriſt ſhould leaue in remembraunce of al his maruelous workes, that is, of his incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his paſſion, his aſcenſion, and glorye in heauen, and other lyke workes) mooſt chiefely is to be verifyed of the body and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſte, in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of the aultare. Beſydes this, the body and bloude of our ſauiour Chriſt (as it is in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnder the fourmes of breade and wine) maye in that reſpecte alſo very well be a remembraunce of it ſelfe, as it honge on the croſſe, in the vyſyble fourme of a mortall man, and as it is nowe in heauen, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of an immortall man. Farthermore, when our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſayde. <hi>Do this in the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me,</hi> he ment they ſhould do the whole miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he then dyd in remembraunce of hym, which whole miniſtration, cannot be accordynglye, doone other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, but that there muſt nedes be preſent, the verye body and bloude of our ſauioure Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiections. </seg>
               </label> ¶ Another common obiection, there is gathered of the woordes of Chriſt. Mathew. xxvi.<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> When he ſaid: <hi>Poore men ye ſhal haue alwayes with you, but me ſhall ye not alwayes haue with you.</hi> Some haue vpon theſe woordes concluded, that the body and bloude of our ſauioure Chriſt, cannot be in the ſacrament of the aulter for then (ſaye they) Chriſt ſhould be alway with vs. whereof hym ſelfe ſaythe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. ¶ But yf thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo concluding,<note place="margin">Aunſvvere</note> would no more, but confer ſainct Marke, and ſaincte Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew together, touchynge the foreſayde woordes of
<pb facs="tcp:173756:65"/> Chriſt, and by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt ſayeth, would ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely iudge what the other ment, they ſhoulde ſone perceue this their obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be of no force or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth at al, to proue, that they thereby goo about to proue. For ſainct Marke in his .xiiij.<note place="margin">Mar. 14.</note> Chapiter, fyrſte telleth the ſtory of the woman, whiche came to Chriſte, and brought with her an Alabaſter boxe of mooſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous oyntment, and poured the ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t on his head, next he telleth howe certen of the dyſciples did mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, and grudge at that facte of the woman, and ſayd: <hi>What meaneth this loſſe, and waſte of oyntement? Might it not haue bene ſold for more then thre .C. pence, &amp; geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the poore?</hi> Thyrdely he telleth, howe oure ſauioure beynge of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended wyth the dyſciples, for theyr murmurynge agaynſt the woman, and how withall he allowyng and commendynge her facte, dyd ſay in this maner. <hi>Let her alone: Why are ye greuouſe vnto her? ſhe hath done a good dede: for alwayes ſhal you haue poore men amongeſt you, and when ye ſhall pleaſe, you may beſtowe your charitie on them, but me ſhall ye not haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes amongeſt you. This woman hath beſtowed on me that ſhe had, and ſhe hathe preuented to anoynt my body, againſt it ſhal be buryed.</hi> By this proceſſe of S. Marke, it is euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that our ſauiour in al that his talke, had a reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte to the charitie, whiche that woman then ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon hym, when ſhe poured the precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173756:65"/> on his heade, the lyke whereof, he ſayeth, no man ſhould be able to ſhew on him in time to come, meaning, that when he ſhould once ryſe from death to lyfe, and haue an immortall bodye, that then he woulde not looke to receyue the lyke at anye man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes handes, but that then men myght at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure beſtowe on the poore, who alwayes are in the worlde in the mortall eſtate, and may by charitye of good folke, be releued and comforted. In ſuch ſorte in dede, our ſauiour is not nowe amongeſt vs, but the beynge of hys body and bloud in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aultar is after another ſorte. For in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament he is, to fede vs with his body and bloude, and not vyſybly to ſhewe him ſelfe vnto vs, as he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did to his apoſtles, nor to haue ointment poured on him, as he then had. ¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> Another obiection is there gathered, partely of S. Paule in the .x. of his firſte Epyſtle to the Corinthians (where he ſpeaketh of a ſpirituall meate,<note place="margin">1. Corin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſpirituall drynke) partelye of Chriſtes wordes in the .vi. of Ihon<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> (where he ſaith that. <hi>It is the ſpirite which geueth lyfe, and that the fleſhe profyteth nothyng</hi>) partly vpon the common maner of ſpeakyng, vſed of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche, whiche calleth the Bodye and bloude of our Sauiour Chryſte, in the ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, a ſpirituall meate and a ſpirituall drynke. ¶ For aunſwere<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> to which obiection, it is fyrſte to be vnderſtanded, that one ſelfe thing may be bothe ſpirituall, and yet neuertheleſſe of a corporall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce to.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:66"/>
            <p>As for example, the body of man after the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall (as S. Paule wytneſſheth in the .xv. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of his fyrſt Epyſtle to the Corinthians) be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,<note place="margin">i. Corin. 15.</note> &amp; yet it ſhalbe then the ſame in ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that it is nowe. Agayne, Manna a meate which God ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the children of Iſraell in wyldernes, is bothe in Scripture, and of the catholyke churche alſo, called a ſpiritual meat, and the water lykewyſe which god gaue them out of a rocke, is called a ſpiritual drinke, and yet as well Manna, as the water, were of a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſubſtaunce. In the .vi. to the Galathians,<note place="margin">Galath. 6.</note> ſainct Paule calleth mortall men, liuing then on the earth, ſpiritual. Wherefore ſpirituall, is not ſo to be taken alwayes, as to exclude corporall, but that thynge whatſoeuer it be, may be called ſpirituall, wherin is a worke wrought by god, aboue nature. For as god is a ſpirite, ſo are his ſupernatural workes called ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituall, and the thinges alſo, on, and in whome, ſuch workes are wrought, are named ſpiritual thynges: and therefore Manna, though it were of a bodelye ſubſtaunce, yet for that it came miraculouſlye from aboue, by the onelye power of God, and not of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is, and may wel be called, a ſpiritual meate. And the dryncke whiche iſſued oute of the rocke, albeit it was inſubſtaunce very water, yet for that God by his omnipotency, made it ſodenlye to iſſue out of a rocke, it is named a ſpirituall drynke. Oure bodyes lykewyſe after the reſurrection, ſhal haue in them immediatly of God, aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of nature, immortalitie, incorruptibilitie, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other lyke ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall qualities, and for that cauſe, they ſhal after the reſurrection, be ſpirituall bodyes. Nowe then
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173756:66"/> what neceſſity is there, that becauſe the body of our ſauiour Chryſt in the Sacrament of the Aultar, is a ſpirituall meate, therefore it ſhoulde not be alſo the corporall ſubſtaunce of his body? When the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke churche doth ſaye, that the bodye of Chryſte in the Sacrament, is a ſpirituall bodye, it meaneth, that it is there onelye thoroughe the almightye po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, and not by the power, or manoure of nature. Lykewyſe, when the catholyke churche ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the body of Chryſte is to be receyued there ſpiritually, it meaneth not that therefore the verye body of Chryſt is not there to be receaued really &amp; in very dede. For this worde, ſpiritually, dothe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye onely the maner of the receauyng, and doth not importe the ſubſtaunce of the thynge ſo receyued. Beſides this, the catholike churche, beleuynge that in the Sacrament of the aultare, is alwayes reallye the body and bloude of our ſauiour Chryſt, doth yet put a difference in the maner of receauyng thereof, and vſeth to ſaye, that when good men receaue the ſacrament, that they receaue the bodye and bloude of Chriſt, both ſacramentally, and ſpiritually to, but when euyll men receaue it, that they receaue the body of Chryſt ſacramentally only, &amp; not ſpiritually, becauſe they come vnto it vnworthely, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they procure thereby, to theim ſelues damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. But nowe to open fardar the very meaning of thoſe wordes of Chryſt. <hi>It is the ſpirit that ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth lyfe, the fleſhe profiteth nothing,</hi> you ſhal vnderſtande, that theſe wordes are taken of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke church, in two moſt godly ſenſes, the one is,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:67"/> to meane by the ſpirite, the godhed, and by the fleſhe the nature of man, as yf he had ſayd, it is the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed that cauſeth my fleſhe to be able to gyue lyfe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is my fleſhe the fleſhe of a bare man, for then it beyng eaten coulde not profyt you, but my fleſhe is vnited in vnitie of perſon to the godhed, ſo that it is thereby able to brynge lyfe to the worthy eater ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thus doeth Cyryll<note place="margin">Cirill.</note> vpon the .vi, of Saynte Iohn expounde theſe wordes. And to lyke purpoſe ſaincte Auguſtyne<note place="margin">Augustine.</note> ſayeth vppon the .vi. of Ihon, that as knowledge beyng ſeperated from charitie, maketh men proude, but beynge ioyned with charytye doth edyfye: euen ſo mans fleſhe not vnyted to the Godhed, and beyng eaten, doth not profytte, but the fleſhe of Chryſt, which is in him, in vnitie of perſon, inſeperably vnited to the godhed, being worthelye receaued, muſt nedes hyghly profyt. The other ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe of thoſe wordes, to meane by the ſpirit, a ſpirituall vnderſtandyng of Chriſtes promyſe, made in Caper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naum when he ſayde,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the foode that I wyl giue vnto you is my fleſhe,</hi> which wordes be then vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanded ſpiritually, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be taken, to meane that thing which paſſeth the power of nature to doo and mans wyt by naturall reaſon to comprehende: lykewyſe by the fleſhe, is to be ment a fleſhely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of the ſayde promyſſe, as to vnderſtande without fayth in Chriſtes deitie, as the Capernai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes did, which toke Chryſt but for a bare man, &amp; ſo conceaued no otherwyſe of the eatyng of his fleſhe, then of commen meat bought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhambles. Thys ſenſe hath S. Chryſoſtome<note place="margin">Chriſostome.</note> wryting vpon the .vi. of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173756:67"/> Iohn, and S. Auguſtyne wryting vppon the ſame Chapter. ¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>
               </label> An other obiection is ther, by occaſion that this truth is not expreſſed in the comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crede, ¶ Which obiection doth procede of an ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">Aunſvver.</note> &amp; lacke of knowledge of the fyrſt inſtitution of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crede. For in the primatyue church, when men of all ages dyd ſodenly turne from gentility, to the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and yet then were not by and by, vpon ſuche there turne, admitted to any ſacramente, but fyrſte were inſtructed in artycles, neceſſary for them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, before they were baptiſed, this common crede was taught them, and they were for that tyme cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Catechumini, that is younglynges in Chryſtes religion, and begynners admytted, but to the fyrſte principles of the chryſtian faythe, durynge whyche tyme they were not ſuffered, ſo muche as to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the maſſe, but after the goſpel, were quyte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the ſame, as by the vndoubted wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the auncient fathers in chriſtes church, maye moſt euidently appeare: So that this reaſon is fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and to no purpoſe to ſay, that becauſe it is not in the commen crede expreſly ſet fourth, that in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aultar, is the very bodye and bloude of our ſauiour chriſt, therfore no chriſtian man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleue it ſo to be. S. Chryſoſtome,<note place="margin">Chriſostome.</note> and S. Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne<note place="margin">Auguſtine</note> hauyng occaſion many tymes in their ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes made by them, to ſpeake of this Sacrament, for aſmuch as amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theire audience were as wel yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, not yet baptyſed, as other faythfull, already chriſtened did vſe oft to ſay. <hi>Quod fideles noru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, which <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful, or they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be al redy baptiſed know</hi> or ſuch lyke thing, and would not then expreſlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb facs="tcp:173756:68"/> the trueth, touching the ſacramente of the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, for that it was not the maner to reueyle ſuch miſteries to thoſe yonglinges: but to them was in general, as ſufficient for ſaluation, preſcribed in that common crede, that they ſhould beleue the catholike churche: which not onely was ſufficient tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beleuynge the other articles of there crede, but is ſufficient at this preſent alſo for vs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firminge oure ſelues in all poyntes to the common belefe of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke church, which is the ſureſt pyller that men may lene vnto, be they learned, or vnlearned, and ſuch a pyller, as who that moſt ſtrongly cleueth to, is in moſt aſſured ſtate of euerlaſtyng lyfe. ¶ There are other obiections<note place="margin">obiection.</note> vppon .iii. particuler artycles of our crede which are, that Chriſt is aſcended, and ſytteth at the right hand of God the father, &amp; from thenſe ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the deade. ¶ Which articles yet being rightly vnderſtanded,<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> ſhould rather confyrme vs in the true catholyke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe, of the preſence of chriſtes body in the ſacrament of the aultare. For as it is aboue nature for a mans bodye to aſcende, and aboue the worthynes of mans nature, to ſyt at the ryghte hande of God the father, that is, to be of equall power, and glory with God the father, and fynally, as it is aboue the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of mans nature, to gyue ſentence of eternal death, and lyfe, vpon all mankynde, and yet euerye good manne ſtedfaſtly beleueth al theſe ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall powers in Chriſt, touching his manhed, bicauſe he is both God and man, and to god nothing is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, euen ſo ſhuld we with like belefe, knowing that Chriſt is omnipotent, credite al other thynges
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173756:68"/> done, or ſpoken by Chriſt, and be mooſt certen, that how ſo euer they ſeme in appearaunce to our reaſon, yet in very dede they agree, and ſtand ryghte well with thoſe foreſayd .iii. articles of our crede, &amp; that though we cannot by oure wittes conceaue, howe Chryſt is aſcended, and is neuertheles in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment alſo, yet they muſt nedes be both beleued, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe gods worde doth affyrme them bothe, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholyke churche dothe beleue them bothe, whyche churche hath alwayes taught that Chryſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in the viſyble fourme of a man, and in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vnder the viſible fourmes of bread and wine, hys wyſedome ſo ordeyning, that with our hartes we ſhoulde beholde hys glory, as he ſytteth in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, at the ryghte hande of the father, and wythall ſhould fede on his very body in the ſacrament, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue the more grace, and thervpon ſo to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his ſpirite, that hereafter we alſo myghte be partakers of the lyke glory in heauen.</p>
            <p>And albeit theſe ſolutions mighte ſufffiſe, and inſtructe ſufficientlye the vnlearned people, to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, bothe to theſe, and all other common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, made agaynſte the Sacramente of the Aultare, troublynge moche the heades of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people, by their folye, in crediting euill, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious ſcholemayſters, to theyr deſtruction, wher giuing credite to the catholike churche, they myght auoyde all daunger, and meryte a great deale, yet to open further the falſhed, and noughtines of the heretique teachers, in our tyme, and howe glad, &amp; willinge they are to abuſe the ſimplicitie of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerned people, ye ſhall haue here added, ſome moo
<pb facs="tcp:173756:69"/> obiections, and ſolutions geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them, to this ende that if the ſayd ſymple people haue bene infected with the ſayd obiections, or ſuch like, they maye be wel ſatiſfied in their conſcience, &amp; therevpon adhere vnto the catholyke faythe, maynteyned, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in the catholique churche, out of whych, there is no ſaluation. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> And to procede herein, this is one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther common obiection that much troubleth the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people, it is to witte. ¶ How can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and bloude, of our Sauiour Chryſt, be in the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the aultar, ſeing that not only euyll men do many tymes receue the ſame, but fyre alſo maye conſume it, and other like chaunces may happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it? ¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſvvere. </seg>
               </label> For aunſwer to which obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is fyrſt and principally to be ſayd, that this obiection procedeth of a vayne curioſitie of them whiche rather delyte, fondly to talke of this high myſtery, then to prepare them ſelues to receyue the ſame accordyngly. Sure we are that our Sauiour Chryſte is nowe man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, and impaſſible, &amp; nether by fire, nor by ought els, can ſuffer violence, and therefore where it pleaſeth hym of hys tender mercy and goodnes, &amp; for our great comforte and ſoule helth, by hys omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent worde, to tourne the ſubſtaunce of bread and wyne, into his moſt precious body and bloude, in the ſacrament of the aultare, and yet ſo to make thys turne, that neuertheleſſe he ſuffereth the fourmes &amp; ſenſible qualities of the breade and wine to remaine in there nature, as they were before the conſecraty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is to be vnderſtanded, that the violence or force that is, or may be done to thys ſacramente, is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173756:69"/> done onely to the fourmes, and qualities ſenſible, whiche in dede are ſubiecte to paſſibilite, &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in no wiſe, to the vncorruptible body &amp; bloud, of oure ſauioure Chriſt, vnder them conteyned. Doo we not reade, I pray you in the fourth of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, howe that our ſauiour ſuffered the deuyll, to take hym, and carye hym vp into the pinacle of the temple, &amp; afterwarde to the toppe of an hygh moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, and yet who doth not knowe that he ſuffered no vilany thereby at all? The ſonne beames alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes, do ſhyne on thynges impure, &amp; vncleane, yet are they no whyt thereby defyled. The bodye of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is with a greater vnion ioyned to the ſoule, then are the fourmes of breade and wine, to the body and bloude of our ſauiour Chriſte, in the Sacramente of the aultar, and yet we know that mortification, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction, and other ſuche lyke thinges chauncynge to our body, the ſoule hath in it no ſuche paſſion, for that it is immortall. The very Godhed of oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Chriſt, was in vnitye of perſon, vnited to hys manhod, &amp; yet none of the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, paines, or griefes, whiche he ſuſtayned in hys manhod, broughte vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, alteration, or chaunge to hys godhed. For the godhed is in alterable, &amp; vnpaſſible. The ſimplicity of Chriſten people, in the primatyue churche, was ſuche, that they beleuynge mooſte certenly, the body and bloude of our ſauiour Chryſte to be in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter, vnder the fourmes of breade and wyne, dyd wythout al curious talke of the fourmes, &amp; accidentes, bende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be preſent at maſſe, wherein the myghtye woorke of conſecration is
<pb facs="tcp:173756:70"/> wrought by god, and wherin our ſauiour Chriſt alſo is, in fourmes of breade and wyne, offered vp to the heauenly father, by the prieſt, for the ſoner obteinyng of mercy, and fauoure towardes vs, and the ſayde people beynge at maſſe, they wyth mooſt feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, dyd praye, and dyd honour, the bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aulter, the body and bloude of oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſte: and beſydes this, they dyd oftentymes, wyth feare and tremblynge, prepare them ſelues to the worthy receyte thereof, and by ſuche theyr godly behauiour, they dyd purchaſe to them ſelues greate abundaunce of grace, where we by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, and mooſt vnchriſtian behauour, prouoke gods wrathe dayly, more and more, vpon our ſelues, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole realme. For nothyng ſoner ſtyrreth God to auenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, then the preſumption of ſuche as wyl curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into hys hydden ſecrettes, and therevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doo contempne all that, whiche by theyr feble wyttes, they are not able to vnderſtande.</p>
            <p>¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>
               </label> Another obiection is of the woordes of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure, in the .vi. of Iohn,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> where he ſaieth. <hi>Qui manducat meam carnem et bibit meum ſanguinem habet vitam eternam.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>He that eateth my fleſhe, and drinketh my bloude, hathe euerlaſtynge lyfe.</hi> Vppon theſe wordes they gather, that if in the ſacrament of the aulter, be really the body and bloude of oure ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Chriſt, then who ſo receueth the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, muſt nedes enioye euerlaſtyng life. But the ſcripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, that Iudas receaued it, and ſainct Paule in the .xi.<note place="margin">1. Corin. xi</note> of his fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians ſaieth,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173756:70"/> that. <hi>Who ſo receueth the ſacrament vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely, receaueth it to his dampnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection </seg>
               </label> To this obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is to be aunſwered, that many ſentences of ſcripture, are to be vnderſtande, wyth a certayne reſtraynte, or limittation, as for example the ſcrypture ſayeth. <hi>Qui credit in me habit vitam eternam.</hi> That is to ſay. <hi>He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth in me, hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe.</hi> And in the fyrſt Epiſtle of S. Iohn,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4</note> &amp; the fourthe chapter it is written. <hi>Quisquis confeſſus fuerit quoniam Ieſus est filius dei, deus in eo manet et ipſe in deo.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>Who ſoeuer ſhall confeſſe, that Ieſus is the ſonne of God, in him dwelleth God, and he in God.</hi> There haue bene, and are thouſandes whyche beleue in Chriſte, and that Chriſte is the very ſonne of God, and yet ſhall not for all that be ſaued, but either for lacke of true belefe, in other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the chriſtian religion, or for lacke of good lyfe, ſhalbe dampned. This condition than is to be added to the forſayde ſentences, yf in ſuche beleif a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dye, and therewith is faythful, in the neceſſarye articles, and out of ſtate of all deadely ſinne, he ſhall tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with out any doute inherite the kyngedome of heauen. So in thys preſent obiection, we muſte make a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, and ſaye, that who ſo eateth, and drynketh worthely. &amp;c. ¶ To the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmacion hereof.<note place="margin">August ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon .xi. De verbis domini.</note> Sainct Auguſtine ſaieth, in hys eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>De verbis domini. Profecto est quidam modus manducandi illam carnem quomodo qui manducauerit, in Chriſto manet, et Chriſtus in eo. Non ergo quocum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que modo quiſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manducauerit carnem Chriſti, et biberit ſanguinem Christi, manet in Chriſto, et in illo Christus, ſed certo quodam modo: quem
<pb facs="tcp:173756:71"/> modum vtique ipſe videbat quando ista dicebat.</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>Verily, there is a certayne maner of eatynge that fleſhe, after whiche maner, he that ſhall haue eaten it, doeth dwell in Chriſt, &amp; Chriſte in hym. Wherefore, note in what maner ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man doeth eate Chriſte fleſhe, and drinketh hys bloude, he dwelleth in Chriſte, and Chriſte in hym, but he that eateth, and drinketh after a certayne ſpeciall maner, to whiche maner Chriſt had reſpecte, when he ſpake the foreſayde woordes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem contra. Creſco. gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticum. li. i. Capi. 24.</note> The ſame ſaincte Auguſtine in his fyrſte boke. <hi>Contra Chreſcouium gramaticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> and the .xxiiii. Chapiter ſayeth thus. <hi>Quid de ipſo corpore et ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guine domini, vnico ſacrificio pro ſalute nostra, guamuis ipſe dominus dicat Niſi manducaueritis carne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filij hominis. &amp;c. non ne ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apoſtolus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet etiam hoc pernicioſum male vtentibus fieri?</hi> That is to ſaye. <hi>What of the very body, and bloude of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure, the onely ſacrifyce for our ſaluation? thoughe there of our Lord dothe ſaye, vnles ye eate the fleſhe of the ſonne of man. &amp;c. doeth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Apoſtle</hi> (meanynge Paule) <hi>teache that it alſo is pernicious to them, that doo vſe it not duely, and ryghtfully?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> ¶ An other obiection there is alſo, and it is thys, Chriſt.<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.15.</note> (Iohn .x. and .xv.) dothe ſay, <hi>I am a dore, I am a vyne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">i. Corin. 10.</note> and ſainct Paule. (Pri. ad. Corin. x.) vſeth ſuche lyke ſpeache, whiche ſpeache of Chriſte, and of ſainct Paule, in thoſe places, doth not import,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173756:71"/> that Chriſt in euery dede, by that ſaying was a dore, or a vyne, or ſuche lyke, but ſpeakyng after that figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyfe ſpeache, or maner, he dyd meane that he was a fygure of a dore, of a vyne, and ſuche lyke, and that he had the propertie, of a doore, of a vyne, &amp; ſo forthe. Semblably (ſaye they) when Chriſt at his laſte ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (takynge breade, and bleſſynge it) dyd ſaye. <hi>This is my bodye.</hi> And takyng the cup, &amp; giuing thankes, dyd ſaye, <hi>this is my blood of the new teſtamente,</hi> &amp;c. hys ſpeache ſoo pronounced, and vttered, dyd not import, that Chriſte thereby dothe make of the breade and wyne, his body, and bloude, but eyther he ment, that the breade and wyne was ſygnes, and tokens of his bodye, and bloude, or els that they ſhould be fygures of hys body, and bloude, and not hys very body, and bloude in dede, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently therefore, they ſaye, that in the ſacrament of the aulter, there is neyther the bodye, neyther the bloude of Chriſte, but bare material breade, &amp; wyne, beyng onely ſygnes, tokens, and fygures of Chriſtes body and bloud there. ¶ For ſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> this maye be ſayd, that it is trouthe, that Chriſt, and ſaincte Paule in the places before alleged, doo ſoo ſaye, as is deduced in the begynnynge of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, or obiection, and trouthe it is alſo, that the ſpeache of Chriſt, <hi>I am a dore, I am a vyne &amp;c.</hi> dothe not importe that Chriſte, by that ſpeakynge was in very dede a doore, or a vyne, but that he was a fygure of a doore, and of a vyne, and had the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertye of the doore, and of the vyne. But when it is ſayde that the ſemblable is of Chriſtes woordes,
<pb facs="tcp:173756:72"/> 
               <hi>This is my bodye, this is my bloude,</hi> that is neyther true, nor dothe folow, eyther by the rules of reaſon, or of ſcripture: for concerninge reaſon, eyther muſte we reaſon, and ſaye, that Chriſte alwayes in hys ſpeakynge dyd vſe fygures, metaphores, and tropes, (which to ſaye, is mooſt falſe, as it appeareth in the .xvi. of S. Iohn<note place="margin">Iohn. 16</note>), eyther els we muſt ſay, that Chriſte dyd but onely ſometymes ſpeake in fygures, and not ſoo alwayes, whiche beyng true, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be graunted, it foloweth not in reaſon, that thoughe Chriſte in the .x. and .xv. of ſainct Iohn. &amp;c. dyd ſpeake fyguratiflye,<note place="margin">Iohn x. and .16.</note> that therefore, here in theſe woordes of Chriſt, <hi>this is my bodye, this is my bloude,</hi> he dyd alſo ſpeake fyguratiflye, wherefore, let theſe ſely ſoules, that haue bene ſeduced by thys kynde of argumentes, aſke theyr teachers, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can mayntayne, and defende this theyr owne argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with ſoo feble a conſequent, or noo. And yf they can not, then tel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be very var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettes in dede: and as for the rule of ſcriptures, that is of the circumſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letter, and of other places of ſcripture, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame, to gather therof y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very meaning of the thing, an example, whereof we haue.<note place="margin">Iohn. 2. and .16.</note> Iohan. ii. and .xvi. And here the vnlearned are to be taughte, that althoughe in the prophetes, and the hiſtories of the olde teſtamente, tropes, and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures are receyued, and allowed, foraſmuche as by ſuche tropes, and fygures, the thing ſpoken, is more vehemently declared, and ſet forth, yet (as the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prelate, and notable great clerke, the Lorde by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of wincheſter, nowe moſt worthy Lord chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celer
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173756:72"/> of England, in his learned booke of confutacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſies, againſt the ſacrament of the aulter, doth prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly aduertiſe vs, &amp; clerly affyrme) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine, &amp; preceptes of the now milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t churche, al thinges of our religion, &amp; faith, ought to be taken ſymply, &amp; plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely. And in very dede, yf in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter were not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true body of Chriſt, but a figure, &amp; a ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely of it, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhold haue nothing more, but rather leſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had, which is againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke doctrine of the churche, &amp; againſt al good reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> An other obiection is this, Chriſt at his laſte ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, takynge the chalice, or cup into his handes, dyd after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had bleſſed it, ſaye. <hi>This cuppe is the newe teſtament, in my bloude.</hi> And ſeyng theſe woordes muſt nedes, as they ſay be taken fygurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely, inaſmuch as the very material cup it ſelfe, was neyther the newe teſtamente, ne yet the bloude of Chriſt, therefore lykewyſe, theſe wordes alſo whych Chriſt, taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g bread into his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, bleſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it, ſaying. <hi>This is my body,</hi> muſt nedes be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. ¶ For anſwer whereunto, we may ſay,<note place="margin">Aunſvvere</note> as we did ſay before, to the ſame obiection, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this argument is noughte, &amp; very euyl framed, for thoughe we did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a figure to be herein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuppe, yet it foloweth not therby, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt nedes take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſpeche, touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body to be fyguratyue alſo, eſpecially for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſpeache, it is to wit, touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, al the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the texte, &amp; courſe of ſcripture, doo enforce vs to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpeache, properlye wherein y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſpeache touchynge the cup, al the circumſtances of the texte, and courſe of ſcripture dothe importe the contrary.
<pb facs="tcp:173756:73"/> ¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> An other obiection is, that Chriſte hathe but one true natural body: nowe (ſay they) one true natural body can not truely be but in one place, therefore ſay they, ſeynge Chriſtes body, is truely in heauen, it can not be truely alſo in the ſacrament of the aulter.</p>
            <p>¶ For aunſwere<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> whereunto maye be ſayde, that in dede it is true, that Chriſte hathe but one true natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bodye, and where they ſaye, that one true natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body, can not be, but in one place, it is alſo true, after one, &amp; the ſelfe ſame maner of beyng, but after dyuerſe maners of beyng, one body, maye be ſondry where, yea, and at one time to, it is to wyt, in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the viſyble fourme, and maner of man, and in the ſacrament of the aulter, vnder the forme, and maner of breade and wyne, and in eueryche of them, really, and truely to, in thoſe reſpectes, God beynge therein the doer, who is omnipotent.</p>
            <p>¶ <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> There is alſo an other obiection, and that is this, God can make man, but man can not make God: nowe ſaye they, yf the true body of Chriſte were, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and in dede, in the ſacrament of the aulter, than the prieſt which is a man, ſhould therby make God, but ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not make God, therefore in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aulter, ther is not the very true body of Chriſt. ¶ For aunſwere<note place="margin">Aunſwere.</note> whereunto, is to be ſaied, that this obiection procedeth of a greate ignoraunce, for he that maketh this obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, taketh that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt ſaying maſſe, and pronouncing the woordes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracion, doeth make God, where in very dede, the prieſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aboute no ſuche thynges, and yf he dyd, neyther he, ne yet god him ſelfe can make God, but the trueth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:173756:73"/> is that the preiſt being the miniſter of God, and god beyng ther the worker with his worde, by the preiſt pronounced, there is cauſed the very body of Chryſt to be ther preſent, wher it was not ther before, &amp; yet no new body ther made, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body ther preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ago was borne of the Vyrgyn Mary the, ſame (I ſay) in ſubſtaunce is there preſente onelye, vnder the formes of breade, and wyne.</p>
            <p>¶ An other obiection<note place="margin">obiection,</note> there is, and that is thys S. Luke, in the .xvii. chapiter of the actes, doth teſtifye that S. Paule, beyng at athens, and in mars ſtrete, before the councell there, did ſaye, amongeſt other wordes, that God doth not dwell in temples made with handes, wherevpon the vnlearned, vnlernedly doth gather, that ſeyng the material temple is made with handes, and the ſacrament of the aultar is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd materiall temple, it foloweth (ſay they) that the body and bloude of Chryſt, can not be in it, becauſe God doth not dwell in temples made with handes, And this obiection hath bene ſoo muche liked, and commended amonges the proceding preachers abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignoraunt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they thought it ineuitable, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abuſing the ſayd people they cauſed it to be ſette vp, and paynted for a gaye ſhew in the temples.</p>
            <p>¶ For aunſwere<note place="margin">Aunſvvere.</note> whervnto, this is to be tolde you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a great difference betwene beyng, &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng in a place, for a greate manye of you, (I doubte not) haue bene both in the cheape ſyde, in Paules churche yarde, yea and Paules churche to, wher ye haue not, with mooſt due reuerence, vſed, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your ſelues, and yet I am ſure that ye dwell not
<pb facs="tcp:173756:74"/> there. In dede, God is properlye ſayde to dwell in heauen, becauſe he there doth ſhew, and manifeſt his great glory, and in the hartes of iuſt, and good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he is alſo ſayde to dwell by grace, but as for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, he is in them beyng, but not dwellyng. And as concernyng the beyng of God in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the aultare, foraſmuch as there is the verye ſubſtaunce of chryſtes natural, and true bodye, and bloude, taken of the Vyrgyn Mary, and that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie is, in vnitie of perſon, inſeperably vnited, and ioyned to the ſayd bodye and bloude, therefore we muſt ſay and beleue, that the godhed of Chryſt is in the ſacrament of the aultar, with his humanitie, in a very ſpeciall ſorte, and doth not thereby dwell in the ſayde ſacramente, and ſoo this obiection is not worth a good button, for all the bragges that hath bene made of it.</p>
            <p>Other fond, and folyſh obiections, there are, which are not worthy to be anſwered vnto, and therefore are not nedefull to be touched, exhortyng you ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Chryſt, fyrmely, and ſtedfaſtly, to beleue the doctrine of the catholyke churche herein, and ſo ſhal you auoyde daunger, pleaſe God, profit your ſelfe, and (lyuinge well) come at the laſt to ioy euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, which graunte vnto vs the father, the ſonne, and the holy goſt, to whom be honor and glory for euer AMEN.</p>
            <closer>Domine ſaluos fac regem, et reginam et omnes, qui eis bene uolunt.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:74"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don in Poules churcheyarde, at the ſygne of the holy Ghoſt, by Ihon Cawodde, Pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Kynge and Queenes Maieſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173756:75"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
